<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" cache:ref-path="IV|656">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>656</num>
  <heading>FUEL STATION</heading>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History">Adopted by the Legislature of the Menominee Indian Tribe 10-6-2005 by Ord. No. 05-29; amended in its entirety 7-19-2012 by Ord. No. 12-19. Subsequent amendments noted where applicable</annotation>
  </annotations>
  <section>
    <prefix>§</prefix>
    <num>656-1</num>
    <heading>Name of tribal business.</heading>
    <text>This charter is issued to a tribal business to be known as "Menominee Fuel Station."</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>§</prefix>
    <num>656-2</num>
    <heading>Purpose of chartered business.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of the chartered business shall be to manage the operation of the Menominee Fuel Station business for the Menominee Indian Tribe. The chartered business is to be operated solely as a profit-making enterprise, dedicated to maximizing the financial resources available for appropriation by the Menominee Tribal Legislature on behalf of the Menominee people. The Menominee Fuel Station shall conduct the following type of business: provide gasoline and diesel fuel and other related goods and services, including but not limited to soft drinks and refreshments, to members of the Menominee Indian Tribe, members of other tribes and other people who wish to utilize the services provided by the Menominee Fuel Station.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>§</prefix>
    <num>656-3</num>
    <heading>Definitions.</heading>
    <text>For the purpose of this charter, the following terms shall have the following meanings: CONSTITUTION — The Constitution and Bylaws of the Tribe.</text>
    <text>MFS — The Menominee Fuel Station, a tribal business enterprise chartered by the Tribal Legislature to direct the fuel station of the Tribe.</text>
    <text>TRIBAL LEGISLATURE — The tribal governing body elected pursuant to Section 3, Article IV of the Constitution.</text>
    <text>TRIBAL MEMBER — Any person included on the official roll of the Tribe.</text>
    <text>TRIBAL REAL PROPERTY — Land held in trust for the Tribe by the Secretary of the Interior. TRIBE — The Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>§</prefix>
    <num>656-4</num>
    <heading>Form of management.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>MFS shall be managed by a five-member Board of Directors selected by a majority vote of the Tribal Legislature for three-year terms. One of the members will be selected from the Department of Finance based upon the recommendation of the Financial Manager to the Tribal Legislature. One of the selected Board members must be a member of the Tribal Legislature, selected by the Tribal Chairperson and approved by the Tribal Legislature, whose term will extend only as long as his/her current term on the Tribal Legislature. The terms of the Board of Directors will be staggered terms. In order to ensure that the terms are staggered, the initial five members, with the exception of the appointed Tribal Legislator, selected under this charter, will draw for two three-year terms, one two-year term, and one one-year term at their first regular meeting. After these initial terms expire, all future selections will be for three-year terms. Board members may be removed and replaced by other eligible persons when the Tribal Legislature determines such action is in the best interests of the Tribe. After appointment of the Board by the Legislature, the Board shall organize itself by a set of laws which provide for the orderly conduct of business, including but not limited to officers, meetings, reports and other matters. The Board members shall receive payment of $50 per meeting plus mileage reimbursement at the federal rates for their services.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>General powers. In general, the Board of Directors shall be responsible for establishing overall policies and objectives for the management of the affairs and assets of MFS; however, in order to assure that the Tribal Legislature may appropriately discharge its governmental and sovereign functions over MFS operations, the Board of Directors shall submit quarterly reports to the Tribal Legislature and may be subject to more frequent periodic review and evaluation if the Tribal Legislature determines that such review is necessary. The Board of Directors may utilize the services of a qualified individual to operate the day-to-day activities of the MFS.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Conflicts of interest prohibited. In carrying out the duties of MFS, neither the Board of Directors nor any agent or employee of MFS shall make or participate in making decisions which involve balancing a substantial personal interest, financial or otherwise, other than interests held in common by all tribal members.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>Indemnification of Board of Directors and agents and employees of MFS. Each manager, employee and agent of MFS shall be entitled, without prejudice to any other rights he/she may have, to be reimbursed and indemnified from assets of MFS for any of the following: all legal and other expenses reasonably incurred by him/her in connection with any claim, action, suit, or proceeding of whatever nature in which he may be involved as a party or otherwise by reason of his having served as Board of Directors, agent or employee of MFS or of any subsidiary of MFS, whether or not wholly owned, or by reason of any action alleged to have been taken or omitted by him as any such Manager, agent or employee. Reimbursement and indemnification under <cite path="§656-4|D.">this subsection</cite> include amounts paid or incurred in connection with reasonable settlements made with a view to curtailment of costs of litigation and with the approval of the Board of Directors then in office. No such reimbursement or indemnification shall relate to any expense incurred or settlement made in connection with any matter arising out of the negligence or misconduct of such Manager, agent or employee as determined by a court of competent jurisdiction or, in the absence of such a determination, by the Manager acting on the advice of counsel. MFS and its Board of Directors, employees, and agents shall not be liable to anyone for making any determination as to the existence or absence of liability, or for making or refusing to make any payment hereunder on the basis of such determination, or for taking or omitting to take any other action hereunder, in reliance upon the advice of counsel.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>§</prefix>
    <num>656-5</num>
    <heading>Annual business meeting.</heading>
    <text>An annual business meeting of the tribal members shall be held in January of each year for the purposes of informing tribal members on the operation of MFS for the past year.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section cache:ref-path="IV|§656-6">
    <prefix>§</prefix>
    <num>656-6</num>
    <heading>Assets.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The assets described in Exhibit "A" attached hereto shall be leased to MFS from the Tribe pursuant to a separate written agreement.<fn path="|IV|§656-6|footnotes|1">1</fn></text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Tribal property. MFS shall have no interest in tribal real property, other than a leasehold interest pursuant to tribal law, and shall have the right to manage and operate MFS in the manner set forth in this charter. No tribal property, real or personal, shall be an asset of MFS for any purpose.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Reserve requirement. MFS will be required to establish a reserve replacement account for replacement of capital assets. A fixed asset is defined as an asset purchase exceeding $500. This account will be funded annually by MFS with the transfer of funds to an interest-bearing account in the amount of $25,000. The funds held in the account shall not exceed $100,000. The transfer of funds will be increased annually by 3%. Any withdrawal from this account will require Board approval. The MFS Board will review the adequacy of the account cap of $100,000 every three years or as necessary. The MFS shall also establish a tax reserve account. This account shall be $60,000 and will offset monthly state tax reimbursements that the MFS must retain until reimbursement is made from the state. This tax refund reserve fund will ensure MFS's cash flow is not impacted while awaiting reimbursement.</text>
    </para>
    <footnotes>
      <footnote>
        <num>1</num>
        <text>Editor's Note: Exhibit "A" is included at the end of <cite path="|IV|656">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </footnote>
    </footnotes>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>§</prefix>
    <num>656-7</num>
    <heading>Fiscal practices.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>General method of operation. MFS shall be operated in an efficient, businesslike manner in accordance with this charter.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The Manager shall cause the following to be achieved:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Oversee an established accounting system;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>An inventory control system, including an inventory of property taken as of the last day of business of each fiscal year of MFS, shall be established;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An annual financial statement of the operations of MFS shall be prepared and presented at the annual business meeting;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A proposed budget, which shall constitute a plan of operation for MFS, shall be prepared and submitted to the Tribal Legislature for approval prior to the beginning of each fiscal year. The budget may be amended during the year if the Board of Directors deems it necessary; however, any increases in the budget of MFS shall require the approval of the Tribal Legislature; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>MFS shall adopt general policies which shall include, among other appropriate matters, a statement of purpose, a statement of policy, a statement of administrative policies, and a statement of personnel policies.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The Tribe's Internal Audit Department shall have authority to conduct an audit of MFS upon a request by the Tribal Legislature.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The Tribe's audit can act as the fulfillment of the audit requirement of the Charter in place of an audit conducted by an independent certified public accounting firm.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Distribution of net profits. The profits of MFS shall be allocated in the following manner: annually, an amount equal to 70% of the actual net profits shall be disbursed by MFS to the Tribal Legislature; 30% of actual net profits shall be retained by MFS. Net profits are arrived at by subtracting the total expenses of MFS from the total revenue of MFS.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Creation of debt and encumbrance of assets. The Board of Directors shall not be allowed to create debt or encumber assets without the prior written approval of the Tribal Legislature.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>§</prefix>
    <num>656-8</num>
    <heading>Tribal sovereignty and immunity.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>The Tribal Legislature hereby gives its consent to allowing MFS, by specific written agreement with any party, to sue and be sued in its capacity as a tribal business upon any contract, claim or obligation arising out of its activities authorized by this charter and hereby authorizes MFS to agree, by specific written agreement, to waive any immunity from suit which it might otherwise have. Subject to the provisions of this charter, MFS is authorized to pledge, mortgage, or otherwise encumber the assets of MFS as security for debts and to acquire, sell, lease, exchange, transfer, or assign personal property or interests therein. In no event shall any assets of the Tribe, including tribal forestland and other tribal land, be subject to any obligations of MFS unless specifically authorized by the Constitution.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>This charter shall not, except as specifically provided, operate as a partial or total waiver of the sovereign immunity of MFS. This charter does not act as a waiver of the sovereign immunity of the Tribe in any manner. The Tribe in no way waives or limits its sovereign and governmental powers in regard to MFS or operations of MFS.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>MFS shall be entitled to, and the Tribe in no way waives, the exemptions and immunities from taxation to which American Indian tribes, their members, and their businesses are entitled by law.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>§</prefix>
    <num>656-9</num>
    <heading>Termination of charter.</heading>
    <text>If this charter is terminated by the Tribal Legislature, the Manager shall promptly relinquish control over all assets and liabilities of MFS to the Tribal Legislature, acting on behalf of the Tribe, or to such other entity as the Tribal Legislature shall designate. The Manager shall also promptly deliver all books and records of MFS to the Tribal Legislature, acting on behalf of the Tribe, or to such other entity as the Tribal Legislature shall designate.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>§</prefix>
    <num>656-10</num>
    <heading>General provisions.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Principal place of business. The principal office of MFS shall be located on the Menominee Indian Reservation. MFS may have such other offices as the Board of Directors may designate and as the business of MFS may require, subject to the approval of the Tribal Legislature.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Duration. This charter shall remain in effect until terminated by ordinance. If this charter is terminated, the Board of Directors shall promptly relinquish control over the assets and liabilities of MFS to the Tribal Legislature or to such other entity as the tribal governing body shall designate. Upon termination pursuant to <cite path="§656-10|B.">this subsection</cite>, this charter shall be null and void.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>C.</num>
      <text>Cooperation between the Board of Directors and Tribal Legislature. In the implementation of this charter, the Board of Directors and the Tribal Legislature shall work together and cooperate in order to promote the best interests of the Tribe.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>D.</num>
      <text>The Tribal Legislature shall adopt regulations and ordinances from time to time governing the operation of fuel stations on the Menominee Indian Reservation.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
</container>
