<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" cache:ref-path="II|306">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>306</num>
  <heading>DRUGS AND DRUG PARAPHERNALIA</heading>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History">Adopted by the Legislature of the Menominee Indian Tribe as indicated in part histories. Amendments noted where applicable</annotation>
    <annotation type="General References">Alcoholic beverages — See <cite path="|II|250">Ch. 250</cite>.</annotation>
    <annotation type="General References">Cigarettes and tobacco products — See <cite path="|II|281">Ch. 281</cite>.</annotation>
    <annotation type="General References">Criminal Code — See <cite path="|II|290">Ch. 290</cite>.</annotation>
  </annotations>
  <container cache:ref-path="II|306|1">
    <prefix>Part</prefix>
    <num>1</num>
    <heading>Controlled Substances</heading>
    <annotations>
      <annotation type="History">Adopted 12-5-2013 By Ord. No. 13-47<fn path="|II|306|1|footnotes|1">1</fn></annotation>
    </annotations>
    <footnotes>
      <footnote>
        <num>1</num>
        <text>Editor's Note: This Ordinance Also Superseded Former <cite path="|II|306">Ch. 306</cite>, Drugs And Drug Paraphernalia, Comprised Of Art. I, Controlled Substances, Adopted 8-7-1980 By Ord. No. 80-17, As Amended, And Art. II, Cleanup Of Clandestine Drug Lab Sites, Adopted 7-20-2007 By Ord. No. 07-14.</text>
      </footnote>
    </footnotes>
    <container>
      <prefix>Article</prefix>
      <num>I</num>
      <heading>General Provisions</heading>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-1</num>
        <heading>Title.</heading>
        <text><cite path="|II|306|1">This Part</cite> 1 shall be titled "Controlled Substances Act."</text>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-2</num>
        <heading>Findings and purpose.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>The Menominee Tribal Legislature finds that the use and abuse of controlled substances constitute a serious problem for the community. As a partial solution, <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1 regulating controlled substances has been enacted with penalties. The legislature recognizes a need for differentiation among those who would violate these laws and make the following declaration:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Many of the controlled substances included in <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1 have useful and legitimate medical and scientific purposes and are necessary to maintain the health and general welfare of the Menominee people.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The illegal manufacture, distribution, delivery, possession and the improper use of controlled substances have a substantial and detrimental effect on the health and general welfare of the Menominee people.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Persons who illicitly traffic in controlled substances constitute a substantial menace to the public health and safety. The possibility of incarceration must exist as a deterrent to trafficking by such persons. Upon conviction for trafficking, such persons must be sentenced in a manner which will deter further trafficking from them and others in the community, protect the public from their harmful activities, and restore them to legitimate and socially useful endeavors.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Persons who habitually or professionally engage in trafficking in controlled substances and harmful substances should, upon conviction, be sentenced to substantial terms of incarceration to shield the public from their predatory acts. However, persons addicted to or dependent on controlled substances should, upon conviction, be sentenced in a manner most likely to produce rehabilitation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Upon conviction, persons who casually use or experiment with controlled substances should be sentenced in a manner that will best induce them to have no further contact with controlled substances and to develop acceptable alternatives to drug abuse.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-3</num>
        <heading>Definitions.</heading>
        <text>As used in Articles I, II, and III, the following terms shall have the meanings indicated:</text>
        <text>ADMINISTER — Direct application of a controlled substance to the body of a patient or research subject by a practitioner (or, in his presence, by his authorized agent), or the patient or research subject at the direction and in the presence of the practitioner.</text>
        <text>AGENT — An authorized person who acts on behalf of or at the direction of a manufacturer, distributor, or dispenser; except that such term does not include a common or contract carrier, public warehouseman, or employee of the carrier or warehouseman, when acting in the usual and lawful course of the carrier's or warehouseman's business.</text>
        <text>ANABOLIC STEROID — Any drug or hormonal substance, chemically and pharmacologically related to testosterone (other than estrogens, progestins, corticosteroids, and dehydroepiandrosterone), and includes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Androstanediol:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>3β,17β-dihydroxy-5α-androstane; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>3α,17β-dihydroxy-5α-androstane;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Androstanedione (5α-androstan-3,17-dione);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>Androstenediol:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>1-androstenediol (3β,17β-dihydroxy-5α-androst-1-ene);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>1-androstenediol (3α,17β-dihydroxy-5α-androst-1-ene);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>4-androstenediol (3β,17β-dihydroxy-androst-4-ene); and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>5-androstenediol (3β,17β-dihydroxy-androst-5-ene);</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>Androstenedione:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>1-androstenedione [(5α)-androst-1-en-3,17-dione];</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>4-androstenedione (androst-4-en-3,17-dione); and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>5-androstenedione (androst-5-en-3,17-dione);</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>Bolasterone (7α,17α-dimethyl-17β-hydroxyandrost-4-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>F.</num>
          <text>Boldenone (17β-hydroxyandrost-1,4,-diene-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>G.</num>
          <text>Calusterone (7β, 17α-dimethyl-17β-hydroxyandrost-4-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>H.</num>
          <text>Clostebol (4-chloro-17β-hydroxyandrost-4-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>I.</num>
          <text>Dehydrochloromethyltestosterone (4-chloro-17β-hydroxy-17α-methyl-androst-1,4-dien-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>J.</num>
          <text>Δ 1-dihydrotestosterone (a.k.a. "1-testosterone") (17β-hydroxy-5α-androst-1-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>K.</num>
          <text>4-dihydrotestosterone (17β-hydroxy-androstan-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>L.</num>
          <text>Drostanolone (17β-hydroxy-2α-methyl-5α-androstan-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>M.</num>
          <text>Ethylestrenol (17α-ethyl-17β-hydroxyestr-4-ene);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>N.</num>
          <text>Fluoxymesterone (9-fluoro-17α-methyl-11β, 17β-dihydroxyandrost-4-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>O.</num>
          <text>Formebolone (2-formyl-17α-methyl-11α, 17β-dihydroxyandrost-1,4-dien-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>P.</num>
          <text>Furazabol [17α-methyl-17β-hydroxyandrostano(2,3-c)-furazan];</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>Q.</num>
          <text>13β-ethyl-17β-hydroxygon-4-en-3-one;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>R.</num>
          <text>4-hydroxytestosterone (4,17β-dihydroxy-androst-4-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>S.</num>
          <text>4-hydroxy-19-nortestosterone (4,17β-dihydroxy-estr-4-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>T.</num>
          <text>Methandienone (17α-methyl-17β-hydroxy-5α-androstan-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>U.</num>
          <text>Mesterolone [1α-methyl-17β-hydroxy-(5α)-androstan-3-one];</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>V.</num>
          <text>Mestandienone (17α-methyl-17β-hydroxyandrost-1,4-dien-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>W.</num>
          <text>Methandriol (17α-methyl-3β,17β-dihydroxyandrost-5-ene);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>X.</num>
          <text>Methenolone (1-methyl-17β-hydroxy-5α-androst-1-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>Y.</num>
          <text>17α-methyl-3β, 17β-dihydroxy-5α-androstane;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>Z.</num>
          <text>17α-methyl-3α, 17β-dihydroxy-5α-androstane;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>AA.</num>
          <text>17α-methyl-3β, 17β-dihydroxyandrost-4-ene;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>BB.</num>
          <text>17α-methyl-4-hydroxynandrolone (17α-methyl-4-hydroxy-17β-hydroxyestr-4-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>CC.</num>
          <text>Methyldienolone (17α-methyl-17β-hydroxyestra-4,9(10)-dien-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>DD.</num>
          <text>Methyltrienolone (17α-methyl-17β-hydroxyestra-4,9-11-trien-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>EE.</num>
          <text>Methyltestosterone (17α-methyl-17β-hydroxyandrost-4-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>FF.</num>
          <text>Mibolerone (7α, 17α-dimethyl-17β-hydroxyestr-4-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>GG.</num>
          <text>17α-methyl-Δ	1-dihydrotestosterone	(17β-hydroxy-17α-methyl-5α-androst-1-en-3-one)	(a.k.a. "17-α-methyl-1-testosterone");</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>HH.</num>
          <text>Nandrolone(17β-hydroxyestr-4-en-3-one); Norandrostenediol:</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>II.</num>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>19-nor-4-androstenediol (3β, 17β-dihydroxyestr-4-ene);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>19-nor-4-androstenediol (3α, 17β-dihydroxyestr-4-ene);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>19-nor-5-androstenediol (3β, 17β-dihydroxyestr-5-ene); and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>19-nor-5-androstenediol (3α, 17β-dihydroxyestr-5-ene);</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>JJ.</num>
          <text>Norandrostenedione:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>19-nor-4-androstenedione (estr-4-en-3,17-dione); and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>19-nor-5-androstenedione (estr-5-en-3,17-dione);</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>KK.</num>
          <text>Norbolethone (13β, 17α-diethyl-17β-hydroxygon-4-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>LL.</num>
          <text>Norclostebol (4-chloro-17β-hydroxyestr-4-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>MM.</num>
          <text>Norethandrolone (17α-ethyl-17β-hydroxyestr-4-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>NN.</num>
          <text>Normethandrolone (17α-methyl-17β-hydroxyestr-4-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>OO.</num>
          <text>Oxandrolone [17α-methyl-17β-hydroxy-2-oxa-(5α)-androstan-3-one];</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>PP.</num>
          <text>Oxymesterone (17α-methyl-4,17β-dihydroxyandrost-4-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>QQ.</num>
          <text>Oxymetholone [17α-methyl-2-hydroxymethylene-17β-hydroxy-(5α)-androstan-3-one];</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>RR.</num>
          <text>Stanozolol [17α-methyl-17β-hydroxy-(5α)-androst-2-eno(3,2-c)-pyrazole];</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>SS.</num>
          <text>Stenbolone [17β-hydroxy-2-methyl-(5α)-androst-1-en-3-one];</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>TT.</num>
          <text>Testolactone (13-hydroxy-3-oxo-13,17-secoandrosta-1,4-dien-17-oic acid lactone);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>UU.</num>
          <text>Testosterone (17β-hydroxyandrost-4-en-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>VV.</num>
          <text>Tetrahydrogestrinone (13β,17α-diethyl-17β-hydroxygon-4,9, 11-trien-3-one);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>WW.</num>
          <text>Trenbolone (17β-hydroxyestr-4,9,11-trien-3-one); and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>XX.</num>
          <text>Any salt, ester, or ether of a drug or substance described in this definition.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>YY.</num>
          <text>The substances excluded under this definition may at any time be scheduled by the Menominee Tribal Legislative Committee in accordance with its authority.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Except as provided in Subsection YY(2), such term does not include an anabolic steroid which is expressly intended for administration through implants to cattle or other nonhuman species and which has been approved by the Secretary of Health and Human Services for such administration.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>If any person prescribes, dispenses, or distributes such steroid for human use, such person shall be considered to have prescribed, dispensed, or distributed an anabolic steroid within the meaning of Subsection YY.</text>
          </para>
          <aftertext>ATTEMPT — An overt act that is done with the intent to commit a crime but falls short of completing the crime.</aftertext>
          <aftertext>CONSPIRACY — Occurs when two or more persons combine, confederate, and/or agree together and with each other to commit an unlawful act.</aftertext>
          <aftertext>CONTROLLED SUBSTANCE — A drug substance or immediate precursor included in Schedule I, II, III, IV, or V of §§ 306-6, 306-7, 306-8, 306-9, and 306-10 of this chapter. The Menominee Tribal Legislature reserves the right to add, delete, or reschedule any controlled substances among these schedules.</aftertext>
          <aftertext>CONTROLLED SUBSTANCE ANALOG — Except as provided in Subsection D(3), the term "controlled substance analog" means a substance:</aftertext>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>The chemical structure of which is substantially similar to the chemical structure of a controlled substance in Schedule I or II;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Which has a stimulant, depressant, or hallucinogenic effect on the central nervous system that is substantially similar to or greater than the stimulant, depressant, or hallucinogenic effect on the central nervous system of a controlled substance in Schedule I or II; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>With respect to a particular person, which such person represents or intends to have a stimulant, depressant, or hallucinogenic effect on the central nervous system that is substantially similar to or greater than the stimulant, depressant, or hallucinogenic effect on the central nervous system of a controlled substance in Schedule I or II.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>Such term does not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>A controlled substance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Any substance for which there is an approved new drug application;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Any substance to the extent not intended for human consumption before such an exemption takes effect with respect to that substance.</text>
          </para>
          <aftertext>COUNTERFEIT SUBSTANCE — A controlled substance which, or the container or labeling of which, without authorization, bears the trademark, trade name or other identifying mark, imprint, number or device, or any likeness thereof, or a manufacturer, distributor or dispenser other than the person who in fact manufactured, distributed or dispensed the substance.</aftertext>
          <aftertext>DELIVER or DELIVERY — The actual, constructive, or attempted transfer of a controlled substance or controlled substance analog, whether or not there exists an agency relationship.</aftertext>
          <aftertext>DEPRESSANT — A drug which contains any quantity of barbituric acid or any of the salts of barbituric acid; or any drug which contains any quantity of a substance which the Legislature has found to have, and by regulation is designated as having, a potential for abuse because of its depressant or stimulant effect on the central nervous system or its hallucinogenic effect.</aftertext>
          <aftertext>DISPENSE — To deliver a controlled substance to an ultimate user or research subject by, or pursuant to the lawful order of, a practitioner, including the prescribing and the administering of a controlled substance and the packaging, labeling or compounding necessary to prepare the substance for such delivery.</aftertext>
          <aftertext>DISPENSER — A person who so delivers a controlled substance or controlled substance analog.</aftertext>
          <aftertext>DISTRIBUTE — To deliver (other than by administering or dispensing) a controlled substance or controlled substance analog.</aftertext>
          <aftertext>DISTRIBUTOR — A person who so distributes a controlled substance or controlled substance analog. DRUG — Any of the following, with the exception of devices or their components, parts or accessories:</aftertext>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>A substance recognized as a drug in the official United States Pharmacopoeia, official Homeopathic Pharmacopoeia of the United States or official National Formulary or any supplement to any of them.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>A substance intended for use in the diagnosis, cure, mitigation, treatment, or prevention of disease in humans or animals.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>A substance, other than food, intended to affect the structure or any function of the body of humans or animals.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>A substance intended for use as a component of any article in Subsections A, B, or C, as stated above.</text>
          <text>DRUG PARAPHERNALIA — All equipment, products and materials of any kind that are used, designed for use or primarily intended for use in planting, propagating, cultivating, growing, harvesting, manufacturing, compounding, converting, producing, processing, preparing, testing, analyzing, packaging, repackaging, storing, containing, concealing, injecting, ingesting, inhaling or otherwise introducing into the human body a controlled substance or controlled substance analog in violation of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1. "Drug paraphernalia" includes, but is not limited to, any of the following:</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Kits used, designed for use or primarily intended for use in planting, propagating, cultivating, growing or harvesting of any species of plant that is a controlled substance or from which a controlled substance or controlled substance analog can be derived.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Kits used, designed for use or primarily intended for use in manufacturing, compounding, converting, producing, processing or preparing controlled substances or controlled substance analogs.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>Isomerization devices used, designed for use or primarily intended for use in increasing the potency of any species of plant that is a controlled substance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>Testing equipment used, designed for use or primarily intended for use in identifying, or in analyzing the strength, effectiveness or purity of, controlled substances or controlled substance analogs.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>Scales and balances used, designed for use or primarily intended for use in weighing or measuring controlled substances or controlled substance analogs.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>F.</num>
          <text>Diluents and adulterants, such as quinine hydrochloride, mannitol, mannite, dextrose and lactose, used, designed for use or primarily intended for use in cutting controlled substances or controlled substance analogs.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>G.</num>
          <text>Separation gins and sifters used, designed for use or primarily intended for use in removing twigs and seeds from, or in otherwise cleaning or refining, marijuana.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>H.</num>
          <text>Blenders, bowls, containers, spoons and mixing devices used, designed for use or primarily intended for use in compounding controlled substances or controlled substance analogs.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>I.</num>
          <text>Capsules, balloons, envelopes and other containers used, designed for use or primarily intended for use in packaging small quantities of controlled substances or controlled substance analogs.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>J.</num>
          <text>Containers and other objects used, designed for use or primarily intended for use in storing or concealing controlled substances or controlled substance analogs.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>K.</num>
          <text>Objects used, designed for use or primarily intended for use in ingesting, inhaling or otherwise introducing marijuana, cocaine, hashish or hashish oil into the human body, such as:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Metal, wooden, acrylic, glass, stone, plastic or ceramic pipes, with or without screens, permanent screens, hashish heads or punctured metal bowls.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Water pipes.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Carburetion tubes and devices.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Smoking and carburetion masks.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Roach clips, meaning objects used to hold burning material, such as a marijuana cigarette, that has become too small or too short to be held in the hand.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Miniature cocaine spoons and cocaine vials.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Chamber pipes.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>Carburetor pipes.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>Electric pipes.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text>Air-driven pipes.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(11)</num>
            <text>Bongs.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(12)</num>
            <text>Ice pipes or chillers.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>L.</num>
          <text>Drug paraphernalia excludes:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Hypodermic syringes, needles and other objects used or intended for use in parenterally injecting substances, which the user is lawfully in possession of and/or prescribed to use, into the human body.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Any items, including pipes, papers and accessories, that are designed for use or primarily intended for use with tobacco products, and which evidence tends to show were being used with tobacco products.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>M.</num>
          <text>"Primarily" means chiefly or mainly.</text>
          <text>EPHEDRINE PRODUCT — Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation that contains any quantity of ephedrine or any of its salts, isomers, and salts of isomers.</text>
          <text>GAMMA-BUTYROLACTONE — Gamma-butyolactone as packaged, marketed, manufactured, or promoted for human consumption, but does not include gamma-butyrolactone intended for use or consumption in or for mechanical, industrial, manufacturing, or scientific applications or purposes.</text>
          <text>IMMEDIATE PRECURSOR — A substance which the Menominee Tribal Legislature has found to be and by rule designates as being the principal compound commonly used or produced primarily for use, and which is an immediate chemical intermediary used or likely to be used in the manufacture of a controlled substance, the control of which is necessary to prevent, curtail or limit manufacture.</text>
          <text>ISOMER — The optical isomer, geometric, or positional isomer.</text>
        </para>
        <aftertext>MANUFACTURE — The production (See definition.), preparation, propagation, compounding, or processing of a drug or other substance, either directly or indirectly or by extraction from substances of natural origin, or independently by means of chemical synthesis or by a combination of extraction and chemical synthesis, and includes any packaging or repackaging of such substance or labeling or relabeling of its container; except that such term does not include the preparation, compounding, packaging, or labeling of a drug or other substance in conformity with applicable federal, state, or tribal law by a practitioner as an incident to his administration or dispensing of such drug or substance in the course of his professional practice.</aftertext>
        <aftertext>MANUFACTURER — A person who manufactures a drug or other substance.</aftertext>
        <aftertext>MARIJUANA — All parts of the plant Cannabis sativa L., whether growing or not; the seeds thereof; the resin extracted from any part of such plant; and every compound, manufacture, salt, derivative, mixture, or preparation of such plant, its seeds or resin. Such term does not include the mature stalks of such plant, fiber produced from such stalks, oil or cake made from the seeds of such plant, any other compound, manufacture, salt, derivative, mixture, or preparation of such mature stalks (except the resin extracted therefrom), fiber, oil, or cake, or the sterilized seed of such plant which is incapable of germination.</aftertext>
        <aftertext>NARCOTIC DRUG — Any of the following, whether produced directly or indirectly by extraction from substances of vegetable origin or independently by means of chemical synthesis or by a combination of extraction and chemical synthesis:</aftertext>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Opium, opiates, derivatives of opium and opiates, including their isomers, esters, ethers, salts, and salts of isomers, esters, and ethers, whenever the existence of such isomers, esters, ethers, and salts is possible within the specific chemical designation. Such term does not include the isoquinoline alkaloids of opium.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Poppy straw and concentrate of poppy straw.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>Coca leaves, except coca leaves and extracts of coca leaves from which cocaine, ecgonine, and derivatives of ecgonine or their salts have been removed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>Cocaine, its salts, optical and geometric isomers, and salts of isomers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>Ecgonine, its derivatives, their salts, isomers, and salts of isomers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>F.</num>
          <text>Any compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of any of the substances referred to in <cite>Subsections A through E</cite>.</text>
          <text>OPIATE — Any drug or other substance having an addiction-forming or addiction-sustaining liability similar to morphine or being capable of conversion into a drug having such addiction-forming or addiction-sustaining liability.</text>
          <text>OPIUM POPPY — The plant of the species Papaver somniferum L., except the seed thereof.</text>
          <text>PARK — For the purposes of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1, a park shall be defined as a piece of land that is kept free of houses and is to be used for pleasure, gathering of the public, exercise, or recreational activities.</text>
          <text>POPPY STRAW — All parts, except the seeds, of the opium poppy, after mowing.</text>
          <text>PRACTITIONER — A physician, dentist, veterinarian, scientific investigator, pharmacy, hospital, or other person licensed, registered, or otherwise permitted, by the United States or the jurisdiction in which he practices or does research, to distribute, dispense, conduct research with respect to, administer, or use in teaching or chemical analysis a controlled substance in the course of professional practice or research.</text>
          <text>PRODUCTION — Includes the manufacture, planting, cultivation, growing, or harvesting of a controlled substance.</text>
          <text>PSEUDOEPHEDRINE PRODUCT — A material, compound, mixture, or preparation containing any quantity of pseudoephedrine or any of its salts, isomers, or salts of isomers, but does not include such a product if any of the following applies:</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>The product is a pseudoephedrine liquid or a liquid-filled pseudoephedrine gel cap. <cite path="§306-3|A.">This subsection</cite> does not apply if the Menominee Tribal Legislature has determined that the product can be readily used in the manufacture of methamphetamine.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>The Menominee Tribal Legislature determined that the product cannot be used in the manufacture of methamphetamine.</text>
          <text>PSEUDOEPHEDRINE LIQUID — A product that is intended to be sold at retail, that is liquid at room temperature, and that contains pseudoephedrine or any of its salts, isomers, or salts of its isomers.</text>
          <text>STIMULANT SUBSTANCE — A drug which contains any quantity of amphetamine or any of its optical isomers; any salt of amphetamine or any salt of an optical isomer of amphetamine; or any substance which the Menominee Tribal Legislature has found to be, and by regulation designated as, habit forming or having a potential for abuse because of its stimulant effect on the central nervous system or its hallucinogenic effect.</text>
          <text>TRAFFICKING/TRAFFIC — The actual or constructive transfer of a controlled substance from one person to another.</text>
          <text>TREATMENT PROGRAM — An agency, hospital, or other institution licensed, certified, registered, or recognized by the Menominee Tribal Legislature to provide outpatient or inpatient treatment for drug use and/or abuse.</text>
          <text>ULTIMATE USER — A person who has lawfully obtained, and who possesses, a controlled substance for his own use or for the use of a member of his household or for an animal owned by him or by a member of his household.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container cache:ref-path="II|306|1|II">
      <prefix>Article</prefix>
      <num>II</num>
      <heading>Provisions for Scheduling; Schedules I, II, III, IV and V</heading>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-3.1</num>
        <heading>Industrial hemp excluded. [Added 5-7-2015 by Ord. No. 15-06]</heading>
        <text>Industrial hemp, as defined under <cite path="|II|307">Chapter 307 of the Menominee Tribal Code</cite>, is excluded from the categories of controlled substances identified under <cite path="|II|306">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-3.2</num>
        <heading>Personal possession and use of marijuana. [Added 2-4-2016 by Ord. No. 15-35]</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding any other provision of <cite path="|II|306">Chapter 306</cite> or any other tribal law, any person 21 years of age or older who uses or possesses 25 grams or less of marijuana shall be assessed a civil penalty of $20 for a first offense; $30 for a second offense; and $40 for a third or any additional offense, in addition to such routine assessments necessary for the administration of civil violations, and such marijuana shall be subject to confiscation. The person shall not be subject to any other form of criminal or civil punishment related solely to such use or possession.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding any other provision of <cite path="|II|306">Chapter 306</cite> or any other tribal law, any person under the age of 21 who uses or possesses 25 grams or less of marijuana shall be subject to the penalties listed in <cite>Subsections E through G</cite>. The marijuana in question shall be subject to confiscation, and the person shall not be subject to any other form of criminal or civil punishment solely related to such use or possession.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding any other provision of <cite path="|II|306">Chapter 306</cite> or any other tribal law, the possession or use of drug paraphernalia associated with the use or possession of 25 grams or less of marijuana shall not subject any person to any form of criminal or civil punishment under the laws of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin solely related to such use or possession.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>Nothing contained in this section shall be construed to repeal or modify existing laws, policies, regulations, or agreements, related to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The operation of motor vehicles or other actions taken while under the influence of marijuana.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Personnel practices or policies governing employee conduct, including, but not limited to, drug testing policies and policies related to the use or possession of marijuana.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The policy of any entity related to the prohibition of possession or use of marijuana on such entity's premises.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>A tenant's use or possession of marijuana.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Punishment for public use of marijuana as provided by tribal law.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>The manufacture, distribution, or sale of marijuana prohibited by <cite path="|II|306">Chapter 306 of the Menominee Tribal Code</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>The possession of over 25 grams of marijuana.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>The imposition of a punishment resulting from a failure to make timely payment of a civil forfeiture or other penalty provided for in <cite path="§306-3.2|A">Subsection A</cite> or B.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>Any person violating <cite path="§306-3.2|B">Subsection B of this section</cite> is subject to the following penalties:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>For a first violation, a forfeiture of not less than $100 nor more than $200, suspension of the person's operating privilege, participation in a supervised work program or other community service work under, or any combination of these penalties.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>For a violation committed within 12 months of one previous violation, either a forfeiture of not less than $200 nor more than $300, participation in a supervised work program or other community service work, or any combination of these penalties. In addition, the person's operating privilege may be suspended, except that if the violation involved a motor vehicle, the person's operating privilege shall be suspended.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>For a violation committed within 12 months of two previous violations, either a forfeiture of not less than $300 nor more than $500, participation in a supervised work program or other community service work, or any combination of these penalties. In addition, the person's operating privilege may be suspended, except that if the violation involved a motor vehicle, the person's operating privilege shall be suspended.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>For a violation committed within 12 months of three or more previous violations, either a forfeiture of not less than $500 nor more than $1,000, participation in a supervised work program or other community service work, or any combination of these penalties. In addition, the person's operating privilege may be suspended, except that if the violation involved a motor vehicle the person's operating privilege shall be suspended.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>F.</num>
          <text>A person who is under 17 years of age on the date of disposition is subject to <cite path="|I|124">Chapter 124 of the Menominee Tribal Code</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>G.</num>
          <text>After ordering a penalty under <cite path="§306-3.2|E">Subsection E</cite> for any person 17, 18, 19, or 20 years of age, the court, with the agreement of the defendant, may enter an additional order staying the execution of the penalty order and suspending or modifying the penalty imposed. The order may require the defendant to do any of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Submit to an AODA assessment.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Participate in an outpatient AODA treatment program at an approved treatment facility, if an assessment recommends treatment.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Participate in a court-approved AODA education program.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Participate in any other program the court finds applicable.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>H.</num>
          <text>Any actions taken to enforce such laws, policies, regulations, or agreements shall not be deemed a punishment prohibited by <cite>Subsections A through C</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-3.3</num>
        <heading>Public use or consumption of marijuana prohibited. [Added 2-4-2016 by Ord. No. 15-36]</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>The following words and terms shall have the following meanings for the purposes of this section: MARIJUANA — Has the meaning provided in <cite path="|II|306">Chapter 306 of the Menominee Tribal Code</cite>. PRIVATE PROPERTY — Any private residence which is owned or leased by:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The person using marijuana or in open possession of marijuana;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>An immediate member of said person's family; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>A person who has granted permission to the person using or in open possession of marijuana to be on the property.</text>
            <text>PRIVATE RESIDENCE — A house or apartment where persons reside and shall not include any commercial establishment.</text>
            <text>PUBLIC PLACE — Any place:</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>That is within view of a public road; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>That is where the conduct involved may reasonably be expected to be viewed by people other than members of the actor's family or household; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>That is not private property.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful for any person to use or be in open possession of marijuana in a public place within the exterior boundaries of the Menominee Indian Reservation. Persons violating <cite path="|II|306|1|II">this article</cite> shall be issued a citation by a Menominee tribal police or Menominee tribal conservation officer and have any marijuana in their possession confiscated. Open possession, for the purposes of <cite path="§306-3.3|A.">this subsection</cite>, does not mean any situation where a person has removed marijuana from their person or possessions at the request or requirement of a law enforcement officer, and is otherwise in compliance with tribal law.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>The penalty for violation of <cite path="§306-3.3|B">Subsection B</cite> shall be a forfeiture of not less than $50 nor more than $100. The Court may, upon a second or subsequent conviction, order the offender to obtain an alcohol and other drug abuse (AODA) assessment and to follow the recommendations resulting from said assessment.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-3.4</num>
        <heading>Medical use or possession of marijuana. [Added 1-21-2016 by Ord. No. 15-37; amended 6-20-2024 by Ord. No. 24-29]</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding any other provision of <cite path="|II|306">Chapter 306</cite> or any other tribal law, the possession or use of 50 grams or less of marijuana shall not subject any person who has been issued a current valid Medical Registration Card by the Tribe pursuant to this <cite path="§306-3">§ 306-3</cite>.4 to any form of criminal or civil punishment under the laws of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin related to such use or possession.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding any other provision of <cite path="|II|306">Chapter 306</cite> or any other tribal law, the possession or uses of drug paraphernalia associated with the use or possession of 50 grams or less of marijuana shall not subject any person who has been issued a current valid Medical Registration Card by the Tribe pursuant to this <cite path="§306-3">§ 306-3</cite>.4 to any form of criminal or civil punishment under the laws of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin related to such use or possession.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>The Department shall issue Medical Registration Cards to persons 18 years of age or older who submit the following, in accordance with rules promulgated by the Department:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>A written signed statement that the applicant has a Qualifying Condition; or a registration card issued by any state or federally recognized Indian Tribe authorizing the person to possess Marijuana if such card is unexpired, and the individual can verify identification; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The name, address, and date of birth of the applicant, except that if the applicant is homeless, no address is required;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The name, address, and date of birth of the person making medical decisions for the applicant as stated in <cite path="§306-3.4|D">subsection D</cite> below (if any) and proof of said persons authority to make such decisions;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The application or renewal fee for a Medical Marijuana Registration Card determined by the Department;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>If the applicant is unable to submit the information required of <cite path="|II|306">this chapter</cite> due to the person's age or medical condition, the person responsible for making medical decisions for the qualifying patient may do so on behalf of the qualifying patient.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>A Qualifying Condition for the purposes of this <cite path="§306-3">§ 306-3</cite>.4(1) is a condition or its treatment that produces one or more of the following: cachexia or wasting syndrome; pain; nausea; seizures; muscle spasms; depression; anxiety; or any other condition that, in the opinion of the applicant would benefit from the use of Marijuana.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>F.</num>
          <text>The Department shall give written notice to the applicant of the reason for denying a Medical Registration Card to the applicant.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>G.</num>
          <text>Medical Registration Cards shall be effective for one year from the date of issue.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>H.</num>
          <text>The Department for the purposes of this <cite path="§306-3">§ 306-3</cite>.4 shall mean the Member Services Department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>I.</num>
          <text>Nothing contained in this section shall be construed to repeal or modify existing laws, policies, regulations, or agreements, related to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The operation of motor vehicles or other actions taken while under the influence of marijuana.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Personnel practices or policies governing employee conduct, including, but not limited to, drug testing policies and policies related to the use or possession of marijuana.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The policy of any entity related to the prohibition of possession or use of marijuana on such entity's premises.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>A tenant's use or possession of marijuana.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Punishment for public use of marijuana as provided by tribal law.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>The manufacture, distribution, or sale of marijuana prohibited by <cite path="|II|306">Chapter 306 of the Menominee Tribal Code</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>The possession of marijuana by any person who has not been issued a valid, current Medical Registration Card pursuant to this <cite path="§306-4">§ 306-4</cite>.3.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>J.</num>
          <text>Any actions taken to enforce such laws, policies, regulations, or agreements shall not be deemed a punishment prohibited by <cite path="§306-3.4|B">Subsection B</cite>."</text>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-4</num>
        <heading>Authority and criteria for classification of substances.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Hearing rules and regulations of the Legislature. The Legislature shall apply the provisions of <cite path="|II|306|1|II">this article</cite> to the controlled substances listed in the schedules established by §<cite path="§306-6">§ 306-6</cite>, 306-7, 306-8, 306-9, and 306-10 of <cite path="|II|306|1|II">this article</cite> and to any other drug or other substance added to such schedules under this subchapter.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Add to such a schedule or transfer between such schedules any drug or other substance if the Legislature:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>Finds that such drug or other substance has a potential for abuse, and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>Makes, with respect to such drug or other substance, the findings prescribed by <cite path="§306-5|B">§ 306-5B</cite> of <cite path="|II|306|1|II">this article</cite> for the schedule in which such drug is to be placed; or</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Remove any drug or other substance from the schedules if it finds that the drug or other substance does not meet the requirements for inclusion in any schedule.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Factors determinative of control or removal from schedules. In making any finding under <cite path="§306-4|A">Subsection A</cite> or under <cite path="§306-5|B">§ 306-5B</cite> of this article, the Legislature shall consider the following factors with respect to each drug or other substance proposed to be controlled or removed from the schedules:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Its actual or relative potential for abuse.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Scientific evidence of its pharmacological effect, if known.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The state of current scientific knowledge regarding the drug or other substance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Its history and current pattern of abuse.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The scope, duration, and significance of abuse.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>What, if any, risk there is to the public health.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Its psychic or physiological dependence liability.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>Whether the substance is an immediate precursor of a substance already controlled under this subchapter.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>The Legislature may consider findings of the federal Food and Drug Administration, decisions made by the United States Attorney General, the State of Wisconsin, or Drug Enforcement Administration as prima facie evidence relating to one or more of the determinative factors.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-5</num>
        <heading>Scheduling of controlled substances.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Five schedules of controlled substances are established, to be known as Schedules I, II, III, IV, and</text>
          <para>
            <num>V.</num>
            <text>Such schedules shall initially consist of the substances listed in this section. The schedules established by this section shall be updated and republished on a semiannual basis during the two-year period beginning one year after September 1, 2013.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>The Menominee Tribal Legislature may add a substance to an appropriate schedule upon finding the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Schedule I.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>The drug or other substance has a high potential for abuse.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>The drug or other substance has no currently accepted medical use in treatment in the United States.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>There is a lack of accepted safety for use of the drug or other substance under medical supervision.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Schedule II.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>The drug or other substance has a high potential for abuse.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>The drug or other substance has a currently accepted medical use in treatment in the United States or a currently accepted medical use with severe restrictions.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>Abuse of the drug or other substances may lead to severe psychological or physical dependence.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Schedule III.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>The drug or other substance has a potential for abuse less than the drugs or other substances in Schedules I and II.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>The drug or other substance has a currently accepted medical use in treatment in the United States.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>Abuse of the drug or other substance may lead to moderate or low physical dependence or high psychological dependence.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Schedule IV.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>The drug or other substance has a low potential for abuse relative to the drugs or other substances in Schedule III.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>The drug or other substance has a currently accepted medical use in treatment in the United States.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>Abuse of the drug or other substance may lead to limited physical dependence or psychological dependence relative to the drugs or other substances in Schedule III.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Schedule V.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>The drug or other substance has a low potential for abuse relative to the drugs or other substances in Schedule IV.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>The drug or other substance has a currently accepted medical use in treatment in the United States.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>Abuse of the drug or other substance may lead to limited physical dependence or psychological dependence relative to the drugs or other substances in Schedule IV.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>Initial Schedules I, II, III, IV, and V of controlled substances shall, unless and until amended, consist of the following drugs or other substances, by whatever official name, common or usual name, chemical name, or brand name designated.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-6</num>
        <heading>Schedule I.</heading>
        <text>Unless specifically excepted by tribal regulation or unless listed in another schedule, any of the following substances, whether produced directly or indirectly by extraction from substances of vegetable origin, or independently by means of chemical synthesis, or by a combination of extraction and chemical synthesis, are listed in Schedule I:</text>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Opiates. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any of the following opiates, including their isomers, esters, ethers, salts, and salts of isomers, esters and ethers, whenever the existence of such isomers, esters, ethers and salts is possible within the specific chemical designation:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Acetyl-alpha-methylfentanyl	[N-(1-[1-methyl-2-phenethyl)-4-piperidinyl)-N-phenylacetamide].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Acetylmethadol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Allylprodine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Alphacetylmethadol	(except	levo-alphacetylmethadol,	also	known	as	levo-alpha-acetylmethadol, levomethadyl acetate, or LAAM).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Alphameprodine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Alphamethadol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Alpha-methylfentanyl [N-(1-[alpha-methyl-beta-phenyl]ethyl-4-piperidyl) propiona- nilide; 1-(1-methyl-2-phenylethyl)-4-(N-propanilido) piperidine].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>Alpha-methylthiofentanyl	[N-(1-methyl-2-[2-thienyl]ethyl-4-piperidinyl)-N-phenyl-propanamide].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>Benzethidine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text>Betacetylmethadol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(11)</num>
            <text>Beta-hydroxyfentanyl [N-(1-[2-hydroxy-2-phenethyl]-4-piperidinyl)-N-phenyl- propanamide].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(12)</num>
            <text>Beta-hydroxy-3-methylfentanyl [other name: N-(1-[2-hydroxy-2-phenethyl]-3-methyl-4-piperidinyl)-N-phenylpropanamide].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(13)</num>
            <text>Betameprodine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(14)</num>
            <text>Betamethadol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(15)</num>
            <text>Betaprodine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(16)</num>
            <text>Clonitazene.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(17)</num>
            <text>Dextromoramide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(18)</num>
            <text>Diampromide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(19)</num>
            <text>Diethylthiambutene.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(20)</num>
            <text>Difenoxin.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(21)</num>
            <text>Dimenoxadol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(22)</num>
            <text>Dimepheptanol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(23)</num>
            <text>Dimethylthiambutene.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(24)</num>
            <text>Dioxaphetyl butyrate.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(25)</num>
            <text>Dipipanone.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(26)</num>
            <text>Ethylmethylthiambutene.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(27)</num>
            <text>Etonitazene.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(28)</num>
            <text>Etoxeridine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(29)</num>
            <text>Furethidine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(30)</num>
            <text>Hydroxypethidine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(31)</num>
            <text>Ketobemidone.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(32)</num>
            <text>Levomoramide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(33)</num>
            <text>Levophenacylmorphan.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(34)</num>
            <text>3-Methylfentanyl [N-(3-methyl-1-[2-phenylethyl]-4-piperidyl)-N-phenylpro- panamide].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(35)</num>
            <text>3-methylthiofentanyl [N-(3-methyl-1-[2-thienyl]ethyl-4-piperidinyl)-N-phenylpro- panamide].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(36)</num>
            <text>Morpheridine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(37)</num>
            <text>MPPP (1-methyl-4-phenyl-4-propionoxypiperidine).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(38)</num>
            <text>Noracymethadol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(39)</num>
            <text>Norlevorphanol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(40)</num>
            <text>Normethadone.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(41)</num>
            <text>Norpipanone.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(42)</num>
            <text>Para-fluorofentanyl [N-(4-fluorophenyl)-N-(1-[2-phenethyl]-4-piperidinyl) propan- amide].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(43)</num>
            <text>PEPAP[1-(-2-phenethyl)-4-phenyl-4-acetoxypiperidine].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(44)</num>
            <text>Phenadoxone.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(45)</num>
            <text>Phenampromide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(46)</num>
            <text>Phenomorphan.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(47)</num>
            <text>Phenoperidine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(48)</num>
            <text>Piritramide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(49)</num>
            <text>Proheptazine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(50)</num>
            <text>Properidine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(51)</num>
            <text>Propiram.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(52)</num>
            <text>Racemoramide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(53)</num>
            <text>Thiofentanyl [N-phenyl-N-(1-[2-thienyl]ethyl-4-piperidinyl)-propanamide].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(54)</num>
            <text>Tilidine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(55)</num>
            <text>Trimeperidine.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Opium derivatives. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any of the following opium derivatives, its salts, isomers, and salts of isomers, whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible within the specific chemical designation:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Acetorphine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Acetyldihydrocodeine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Benzylmorphine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Codeine methylbromide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Codeine-N-Oxide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Cyprenorphine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Desomorphine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>Dihydromorphine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>Drotebanol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text>Etorphine (except hydrochloride salt).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(11)</num>
            <text>Heroin.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(12)</num>
            <text>Hydromorphinol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(13)</num>
            <text>Methyldesorphine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(14)</num>
            <text>Methyldihydromorphine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(15)</num>
            <text>Morphine methylbromide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(16)</num>
            <text>Morphine methylsulfonate.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(17)</num>
            <text>Morphine-N-Oxide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(18)</num>
            <text>Myrophine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(19)</num>
            <text>Nicocodeine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(20)</num>
            <text>Nicomorphine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(21)</num>
            <text>Normorphine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(22)</num>
            <text>Pholcodine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(23)</num>
            <text>Thebacon.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>Hallucinogenic substances. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following hallucinogenic substances, or which contains any of its salts, isomers, and salts of isomers, whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible within the specific chemical designation (For purposes of <cite path="§306-6|C.">this subsection</cite> only, the term "isomer" includes the optical, position and geometric isomers.):</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Alpha-ethyltryptamine [some trade or other names: etryptamine; Monase; α-ethyl-1H-indole-3-ethanamine; 3-(2-aminobutyl) indole; α-ET; and AET].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>4-bromo-2,5-dimethoxy-amphetamine (some trade or other names: 4-bromo-2, 5-dimethoxy-α-methylphenethylamine; 4-bromo-2,5-DMA).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>4-Bromo-2,5-dimethoxyphenethylamine  [some  trade  or  other  names:  2-(4-bromo-2, 5-dimethoxyphenyl)-1-aminoethane; alpha-desmethyl DOB; 2C-B, Nexus].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>2,5-dimethoxyamphetamine (some trade or other names: 2,5-dimethoxy-α-methylphenethylamine; 2,5-DMA).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>2,5-dimethoxy-4-ethylamphet-amine (some trade or other names: DOET).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>2,5-dimethoxy-4-(n)-propylthiophenethylamine (some trade or other names: 2C-T-7).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>4-methoxyamphetamine (some trade or other names: 4-methoxy-α- methylphenethylamine; paramethoxyamphetamine, PMA).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>5-methoxy-3,4-methylenedioxy-amphetamine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>4-methyl-2,5-dimethoxy-amphetamine (some trade and other names: 4-methyl-2,5-dimethoxy-α-methylphenethylamine; "DOM"; and "STP").</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text>3,4-methylenedioxy amphetamine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(11)</num>
            <text>3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(12)</num>
            <text>3,4-methylenedioxy-N-ethylamphetamine [also known as N-ethyl-alpha-methyl-3,4 (methylenedioxy)phenethylamine, N-ethyl MDA, MDE, MDEA].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(13)</num>
            <text>N-hydroxy-3,4-methylenedioxyamphetamine [also known as N-hydroxy-alpha -methyl-3, 4(methylenedioxy)phenethylamine, and N-hydroxy MDA].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(14)</num>
            <text>3,4,5-trimethoxy amphetamine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(15)</num>
            <text>5-methoxy-N,N-dimethyltryptamine  [some  trade  or  other  names:  5-methoxy-3-(2-[dimethylamino]ethyl) indole; 5-MeO-DMT].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(16)</num>
            <text>Alpha-methyltryptamine (other name: AMT).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(17)</num>
            <text>Bufotenine [some trade and other names: 3-(β-Dimethylaminoethyl) -5-hydroxyindole; 3-(2-dimethylaminoethyl)-5-indolol;	N,N-dimethylserotonin;	5-hydroxy-N,N-dimethyltryptamine; mappine].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(18)</num>
            <text>Diethyltryptamine (some trade and other names: N,N-Diethyltryptamine; DET).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(19)</num>
            <text>Dimethyltryptamine (some trade or other names: DMT).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(20)</num>
            <text>5-methoxy-N, N-diisopropyltryptamine (other name: 5-MeO-DIPT).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(21)</num>
            <text>Ibogaine  [some  trade  and  other  names:  7-Ethyl-6;6β,7,8,9,10,12,13-octahydro-2-methoxy-6,9-methano-5H-pyrido (1', 2':1,2) azepino (5,4-b) indole; Tabernanthe iboga].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(22)</num>
            <text>Lysergic acid diethylamide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(23)</num>
            <text>Marijuana, also marihuana.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(24)</num>
            <text>Mescaline.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(25)</num>
            <text>Parahexyl;  some  trade  or  other  names:  3-Hexyl-1-hydroxy-7,8,9,10-tetrahydro-6, 6,9-trimethyl-6H-dibenzo(b,d)pyran; Synhexyl.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(26)</num>
            <text>Peyote: meaning all parts of the plant presently classified botanically as Lophophora williamsii Lemaire, whether growing or not, the seeds thereof, any extract from any part of such plant, and every compound, manufacture, salts, derivative, mixture, or preparation of such plant, its seeds or extracts. (A religious exception is found in <cite path="§306-11">§ 306-11</cite>.)</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(27)</num>
            <text>N-ethyl-3-piperidyl benzilate.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(28)</num>
            <text>N-methyl-3-piperidyl benzilate.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(29)</num>
            <text>Psilocybin.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(30)</num>
            <text>Psilocyn.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(31)</num>
            <text>Tetrahydrocannabinols: meaning tetrahydrocannabinols naturally contained in a plant of the genus Cannabis (cannabis plant), as well as synthetic equivalents of the substances contained in the cannabis plant, or in the resinous extractives of such plant, and/or synthetic substances, derivatives, and their isomers with similar chemical structure and pharmacological activity to those substances contained in the plant, such as the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>1 cis or trans tetrahydrocannabinol, and their optical isomers.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>6 cis or trans tetrahydrocannabinol, and their optical isomers.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>3,4 cis or trans tetrahydrocannabinol, and its optical isomers.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(d)</num>
              <text>(Since nomenclature of these substances is not internationally standardized, compounds of these structures, regardless of numerical designation of atomic positions covered.)</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(e)</num>
              <text>Ethylamine  analog  of  phencyclidine  [some  trade  or  other  names:  N-ethyl-1-phenylcyclohexylamine,	(1-phenylcyclohexyl)ethylamine,	N-(1-phenylcyclohexyl)ethylamine, cyclohexamine, PCE].</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(f)</num>
              <text>Pyrrolidine analog of phencyclidine [some trade or other names: 1-(1-phenylcyclohexyl)-pyrrolidine, PCPy, PHP].</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(g)</num>
              <text>Thiophene analog of phencyclidine [some trade or other names: 1-(1-[2-thienyl]-cyclohexyl)-piperidine, 2-thienylanalog of phencyclidine, TPCP, TCP].</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(h)</num>
              <text>1-[1-(2-thienyl)cyclohexyl]pyrrolidine (some other names: TCPy).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>4-methylmethcathinone (Mephedrone).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(j)</num>
              <text>3,4-methylenedioxypyrovalerone (MDPV).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(k)</num>
              <text>2-(2,5-Dimethoxy-4-ethylphenyl)ethanamine (2C-E).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(l)</num>
              <text>2-(2,5-Dimethoxy-4-methylphenyl)ethanamine (2C-D).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(m)</num>
              <text>2-(4-Chloro-2,5-dimethoxyphenyl)ethanamine (2C-C).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(n)</num>
              <text>2-(4-Iodo-2,5-dimethoxyphenyl)ethanamine (2C-I).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(o)</num>
              <text>2-[4-(Ethylthio)-2,5-dimethoxyphenyl]ethanamine (2C-T-2).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(p)</num>
              <text>2-[4-(Isopropylthio)-2,5-dimethoxyphenyl]ethanamine (2C-T-4).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(q)</num>
              <text>2-(2,5-Dimethoxyphenyl)ethanamine (2C-H).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(r)</num>
              <text>2-(2,5-Dimethoxy-4-nitro-phenyl)ethanamine (2C-N).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(s)</num>
              <text>2-(2,5-Dimethoxy-4-(n)-propylphenyl)ethanamine (2C-P).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>Unless specifically exempted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of cannabimimetic agents, or which contains their salts, isomers, and salts of isomers, whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible within the specific chemical designation.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The term "cannabimimetic agents" means any substance that is a cannabinoid receptor type 1 (CB1 receptor) agonist as demonstrated by binding studies and functional assays within any of the following structural classes:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>2-(3-hydroxycyclohexyl)phenol with substitution at the 5-position of the phenolic ring by alkyl or alkenyl, whether or not substituted on the cyclohexyl ring to any extent.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>3-(1-naphthoyl)indole or 3-(1-naphthylmethane)indole by substitution at the nitrogen atom of the indole ring, whether or not further substituted on the indole ring to any extent, whether or not substituted on the naphthoyl or naphthyl ring to any extent.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>3-(1-naphthoyl)pyrrole by substitution at the nitrogen atom of the pyrrole ring, whether or not further substituted in the pyrrole ring to any extent, whether or not substituted on the naphthoyl ring to any extent.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(d)</num>
              <text>1-(1-naphthylmethylene)indene by substitution of the 3-position of the indene ring, whether or not further substituted in the indene ring to any extent, whether or not substituted on the naphthyl ring to any extent.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(e)</num>
              <text>3-phenylacetylindole or 3-benzoylindole by substitution at the nitrogen atom of the indole ring, whether or not further substituted in the indole ring to any extent, whether or not substituted on the phenyl ring to any extent.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Such term includes:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>5-(1,1-dimethylheptyl)-2-[(1R,3S)-3-hydroxycyclohexyl]-phenol (CP-47,497);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>5-(1,1-dimethyloctyl)-2-[(1R,3S)-3-hydroxycyclohexyl]-phenol (cannabicyclohexanol or CP-47,497 C8-homo1og);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>1 -pentyl-3-(1-naphthoyl)indole (JWH-018 and AM678);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(d)</num>
              <text>(6aR,10aR)- 9-(Hydroxymethyl)- 6,6-dimethyl- 3-(2-methyloctan-2-yl)-6a, 7,10,10a-tetrahydrobenzo [c]chromen- 1-ol (HU-210);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(e)</num>
              <text>1-butyl-3-(1-naphthoyl)indole (JWH-073);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(f)</num>
              <text>1-hexyl-3-(1-naphthoyl)indole (JWH-019);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(g)</num>
              <text>1-[2-(4-morpholinyl)ethyl]-3-(1-naphthoyl)indole (JWH-200);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(h)</num>
              <text>1-pentyl-3-(2-methoxyphenylacetyl)indole (JWH-250);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>1-pentyl-3-[1-(4-methoxynaphthoyl)]indole (JWH-081);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(j)</num>
              <text>1-pentyl-3-(4-methyl-1-naphthoyl)indole (JWH-122);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(k)</num>
              <text>1-pentyl-3-(4-chloro-1-naphthoyl)indole (JWH-398);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(l)</num>
              <text>1-(5-fluoropentyl)-3-(1-naphthoyl)indole (AM2201);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(m)</num>
              <text>1-(5-fluoropentyl)-3-(2-iodobenzoyl)indole (AM694);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(n)</num>
              <text>1-pentyl-3-[(4-methoxy)-benzoyl]indole (SR-19 and RCS-4);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(o)</num>
              <text>1-cyclohexylethyl-3-(2-methoxyphenylacetyl)indole (SR-18 and RCS-8);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(p)</num>
              <text>1-pentyl-3-(2-chlorophenylacetyl)indole (JWH-203);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(q)</num>
              <text>1-pentyl-1H-indol-3-yl(2,2,3,3-tetramethylcyclopropyl)methanone (UR-144) (Some trade or other names include TCMP-018 and KM-X1.); and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(r)</num>
              <text>[1-(5-fluoropentyl)-1H-indol-3-yl](2,2,3,3-tetramethylcyclo-propyl)methanone (XLR11) (Some other trade names include 5-F-UR-144.).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>Depressants. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a depressant effect on the central nervous system, including its salts, isomers, and salts of isomers, whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible within the specific chemical designation:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Gamma-hydroxybutyric acid. (Some other names include GHB; gamma-hydroxybutyrate; 4-hydroxybutyrate; 4-hydroxybutanoic acid; sodium oxybate; sodium oxybutyrate.)</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Mecloqualone.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Methaqualone.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>F.</num>
          <text>Stimulants. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a stimulant effect on the central nervous system, including its salts, isomers, and salts of isomers:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Aminorex  (some  other  names:  aminoxaphen;  2-amino-5-phenyl-2-oxazoline;  or 4,5-dihydro-5-phenly-2-oxazolamine).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>N-Benzylpiperazine (some other names: BZP, 1-benzylpiperazine).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Cathinone (some trade or other names: 2-amino-1-phenyl-1-propanone, alpha-aminopropiophenone, 2-aminopropiophenone, and norephedrone).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Fenethylline.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Methcathinone [some other names: 2-(methylamino)-propiophenone; alpha-(methylamino) propiophenone; 2-(methylamino)-1-phenylpropan-1-one; alpha-N-methylaminopropiophenone; monomethylpropion; ephedrone; N-methylcathinone; methylcathinone; AL-464; AL-422; AL-463 and UR1432], its salts, optical isomers and salts of optical isomers.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>(±)cis-4-methylaminorex [(±)cis-4,5-dihydro-4-methyl-5-phenyl-2-oxazolamine].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>N-ethylamphetamine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>N,N-dimethylamphetamine (also known as N,N-alpha-trimethyl- benzeneethanamine; N,N-alpha-trimethylphenethylamine).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-7</num>
        <heading>Schedule II.</heading>
        <text>Unless specifically excepted by tribal regulation or unless listed in another schedule, any of the following substances, whether produced directly or indirectly by extraction from substances of vegetable origin, or independently by means of chemical synthesis, or by a combination of extraction and chemical synthesis, are listed in Schedule II:</text>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Substances, plant origin or chemical synthesis. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any of the following substances, whether produced directly or indirectly by extraction from substances of plant origin, or independently by means of chemical synthesis, or by a combination of extraction and chemical synthesis:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Opium and opiate, and any salt, compound, derivative, or preparation of opium or opiate, excluding apomorphine, thebaine-derived butorphanol, dextrorphan, nalbuphine, nalmefene, naloxone, and naltrexone, and their respective salts, isomers, and salts of isomers, but including the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>Codeine.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>Dihydroetorphine.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>Ethylmorphine.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(d)</num>
              <text>Etorphine hydrochloride.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(e)</num>
              <text>Granulated opium.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(f)</num>
              <text>Hydrocodone.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(g)</num>
              <text>Hydromorphone.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(h)</num>
              <text>Metopon.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>Morphine.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(j)</num>
              <text>Opium extracts.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(k)</num>
              <text>Opium fluid.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(l)</num>
              <text>Oripavine.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(m)</num>
              <text>Oxycodone.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(n)</num>
              <text>Oxymorphone.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(o)</num>
              <text>Powdered opium.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(p)</num>
              <text>Raw opium.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(q)</num>
              <text>Thebaine.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(r)</num>
              <text>Tincture of opium.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Any salt, compound, derivative, or preparation thereof which is chemically equivalent or identical with any of the substances referred to in this section, except that these substances shall not include the isoquinoline alkaloids of opium.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Opium poppy and poppy straw.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Coca leaves and any salt, compound, derivative or preparation of coca leaves (including cocaine and ecgonine and their salts, isomers, derivatives and salts of isomers and derivatives), and any salt, compound, derivative, or preparation thereof which is chemically equivalent or identical with any of these substances, except that the substances shall not include decocainized coca leaves or extraction of coca leaves, which extractions do not contain cocaine or ecgonine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Concentrate of poppy straw (the crude extract of poppy straw in either liquid, solid or powder form which contains the phenanthrene alkaloids of the opium poppy).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Opiates. Unless specifically excepted or unless in another schedule, any of the following opiates, including their isomers, esters, ethers, salts and salts of isomers, esters and ethers, whenever the existence of such isomers, esters, ethers, and salts is possible within the specific chemical designation, dextrorphan and levopropoxyphene excepted:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Alfentanil.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Alphaprodine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Anileridine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Bezitramide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Bulk dextropropoxyphene (nondosage forms).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Carfentanil.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Dihydrocodeine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>Diphenoxylate.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>Fentanyl.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text>Isomethadone.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(11)</num>
            <text>Levo-alphacetylmethadol (some other names: levo-alpha-acetylmethadol, levomethadyl acetate, LAAM).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(12)</num>
            <text>Levomethorphan.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(13)</num>
            <text>Levorphanol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(14)</num>
            <text>Metazocine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(15)</num>
            <text>Methadone.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(16)</num>
            <text>Methadone-Intermediate, 4-cyano-2-dimethylamino-4,4-diphenyl butane.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(17)</num>
            <text>Moramide-Intermediate, 2-methyl-3-morpholino-1, 1-diphenylpropane-carboxylic acid.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(18)</num>
            <text>Pethidine (meperidine).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(19)</num>
            <text>Pethidine-Intermediate-A, 4-cyano-1-methyl-4-phenylpiperidine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(20)</num>
            <text>Pethidine-Intermediate-B, ethyl-4-phenylpiperidine-4-carboxylate.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(21)</num>
            <text>Pethidine-Intermediate-C, 1-methyl-4-phenylpiperidine-4-carboxylic acid.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(22)</num>
            <text>Phenazocine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(23)</num>
            <text>Piminodine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(24)</num>
            <text>Racemethorphan.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(25)</num>
            <text>Racemorphan.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(26)</num>
            <text>Remifentanil.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(27)</num>
            <text>Sufentanil.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(28)</num>
            <text>Tapentadol.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>Stimulants. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a stimulant effect on the central nervous system:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Amphetamine, its salts, optical isomers, and salts of its optical isomers.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Methamphetamine, its salts, isomers, and salts of its isomers.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Phenmetrazine and its salts.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Methylphenidate.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Lisdexamfetamine, its salts, isomers, and salts of its isomers.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>Depressants. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a depressant effect on the central nervous system, including its salts, isomers, and salts of isomers, whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible within the specific chemical designation:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Amobarbital.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Glutethimide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Pentobarbital.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Phencyclidine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Secobarbital.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>Hallucinogenic substances.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Nabilone [another name for nabilone: (+/-)-trans-3-(1,1-dimethylheptyl)-6, 6a,7,8,10,10a-hexahydro-1-hydroxy-6, 6-dimethyl-9H-dibenzo[b,d]pyran-9-one].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>(Reserved)</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>F.</num>
          <text>Immediate precursors. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Immediate precursor to amphetamine and methamphetamine:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>Phenylacetone (some trade or other names: phenyl-2-propanone; P2P; benzyl methyl ketone; methyl benzyl ketone).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Immediate precursors to phencyclidine (PCP):</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>1-phenylcyclohexylamine.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>1-piperidinocyclohexanecarbonitrile (PCC).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Immediate precursor to fentanyl:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>4-anilino-N-phenethyl-4-piperidine (ANPP).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>(Reserved)</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section cache:ref-path="II|§306-8">
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-8</num>
        <heading>Schedule III.</heading>
        <text>Unless specifically excepted by tribal regulation or unless listed in another schedule, any of the following substances, whether produced directly or indirectly by extraction from substances of vegetable origin, or independently by means of chemical synthesis, or by a combination of extraction and chemical synthesis, are listed in Schedule III:</text>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Stimulants. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a stimulant effect on the central nervous system, including its salts, isomers (whether optical, positional, or geometric), and salts of such isomers, whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible within the specific chemical designation:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Benzphetamine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Chlorphentermine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Clortermine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Phendimetrazine.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Depressants. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a depressant effect on the central nervous system:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Any compound, mixture or preparation containing:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>Amobarbital;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>Secobarbital;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>Pentobarbital; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(d)</num>
              <text>Any salt thereof and one or more other active medicinal ingredients which are not listed in any schedule.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Any suppository dosage form containing:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>Amobarbital;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>Secobarbital;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>Pentobarbital; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(d)</num>
              <text>Any salt of any of these drugs and approved by the Food and Drug Administration for marketing only as a suppository.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Any substance which contains any quantity of a derivative of barbituric acid or any salt thereof.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Chlorhexadol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Embutramide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Any drug product containing gamma hydroxybutyric acid, including its salts, isomers, and salts of isomers, for which an application is approved under Section 505 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act.<fn path="|II|§306-8|footnotes|2">2</fn></text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Ketamine, its salts, isomers, and salts of isomers [some other names for ketamine: (±)-2-(2-chlorophenyl)-2-(methylamino)-cyclohexanone].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>Lysergic acid.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>Lysergic acid amide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text>Methyprylon.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(11)</num>
            <text>Sulfondiethylmethane.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(12)</num>
            <text>Sulfonethylmethane.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(13)</num>
            <text>Sulfonmethane.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(14)</num>
            <text>Tiletamine and zolazepam or any salt thereof (some trade or other names for a tiletamine-zolazepam combination product: Telazol; some trade or other names for tiletamine: 2-(ethylamino)-2-(2-thienyl)-cyclohexanone; some trade or other names for zolazepam: 4-(2-fluorophenyl)-6,8-dihydro-1,3,8-trimethylpyrazolo-[3,4-e] [1,4]-diazepin-7(1H)-one, flupyrazapon).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(15)</num>
            <text>Nalorphine 9400.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>Narcotic drugs. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation containing any of the following narcotic drugs, or their salts calculated as the free anhydrous base or alkaloid, in limited quantities as set forth below:</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Not more than 1.8 grams of codeine per 100 milliliters or not more than 90 milligrams per dosage unit, with an equal or greater quantity of an isoquinoline alkaloid of opium.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Not more than 1.8 grams of codeine per 100 milliliters or not more than 90 milligrams per dosage unit, with one or more active, nonnarcotic ingredients in recognized therapeutic amounts.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Not more than 300 milligrams of dihydrocodeinone (hydrocodone) per 100 milliliters or not more than 15 milligrams per dosage unit, with a fourfold or greater quantity of an isoquinoline alkaloid of opium.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Not more than 300 milligrams of dihydrocodeinone (hydrocodone) per 100 milliliters or not more than 15 milligrams per dosage unit, with one or more active nonnarcotic ingredients in recognized therapeutic amounts.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Not more than 1.8 grams of dihydrocodeine per 100 milliliters or not more than 90 milligrams per dosage unit, with one or more active nonnarcotic ingredients in recognized therapeutic amounts.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Not more than 300 milligrams of ethylmorphine per 100 milliliters or not more than 15 milligrams per dosage unit, with one or more active, nonnarcotic ingredients in recognized therapeutic amounts.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>Not more than 500 milligrams of opium per 100 milliliters or per 100 grams or not more than 25 milligrams per dosage unit, with one or more active, nonnarcotic ingredients in recognized therapeutic amounts.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>Not more than 50 milligrams of morphine per 100 milliliters or per 100 grams, with one or more active, nonnarcotic ingredients in recognized therapeutic amounts.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>Narcotic drugs not limited by quantity. Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation containing any of the following narcotic drugs or their salts, as set forth below:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Buprenorphine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>(Reserved)</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>Anabolic steroids. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture or preparation containing any quantity of the following substances, including its salts, esters and ethers:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Anabolic steroids. (See <cite path="§306-3">§ 306-3</cite> of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1.)</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>(Reserved)</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>F.</num>
          <text>Hallucinogenic substances.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Dronabinol (synthetic) in sesame oil and encapsulated in a soft gelatin capsule in a U.S. Food and Drug Administration approved product [some other names for dronabinol: (6aR-trans)-6a,7,8,10a-tetrahydro-6,6,9-trimethyl-3-pentyl-6H-dibenzo [b,d]pyran-1-ol] or (-)-delta-9-(trans)-tetrahydrocannabinol].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>(Reserved)</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <footnotes>
          <footnote>
            <num>2</num>
            <text>Editor's Note: See 21 U.S.C. § 301 et seq.</text>
          </footnote>
        </footnotes>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-9</num>
        <heading>Schedule IV.</heading>
        <text>Unless specifically excepted by tribal regulation or unless listed in another schedule, any of the following substances, whether produced directly or indirectly by extraction from substances of vegetable origin, or independently by means of chemical synthesis, or by a combination of extraction and chemical synthesis, are listed in Schedule IV:</text>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Narcotic drugs. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation containing any of the following narcotic drugs, or their salts, calculated as the free anhydrous base or alkaloid, in limited quantities as set forth below:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Not more than one milligram of difenoxin and not less than 25 micrograms of atropine sulfate per dosage unit.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Dextropropoxyphene	[alpha-(+)-4-dimethylamino-1,2-diphenyl-3-methyl-2-propionoxybutane].</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Depressants. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances, including its salts, isomers, and salts of isomers, whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible within the specific chemical designation:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Alprazolam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Barbital.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Bromazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Camazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Carisoprodol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Chloral betaine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Chloral hydrate.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>Chlordiazepoxide.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>Clobazam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text>Clonazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(11)</num>
            <text>Clorazepate.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(12)</num>
            <text>Clotiazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(13)</num>
            <text>Cloxazolam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(14)</num>
            <text>Delorazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(15)</num>
            <text>Diazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(16)</num>
            <text>Dichloraphenazone.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(17)</num>
            <text>Estazolam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(18)</num>
            <text>Ethchlorvynol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(19)</num>
            <text>Ethinamate.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(20)</num>
            <text>Ethyl loflazepate.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(21)</num>
            <text>Fludiazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(22)</num>
            <text>Flunitrazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(23)</num>
            <text>Flurazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(24)</num>
            <text>Fospropofol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(25)</num>
            <text>Halazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(26)</num>
            <text>Haloxazolam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(27)</num>
            <text>Ketazolam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(28)</num>
            <text>Loprazolam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(29)</num>
            <text>Lorazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(30)</num>
            <text>Lormetazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(31)</num>
            <text>Mebutamate.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(32)</num>
            <text>Medazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(33)</num>
            <text>Meprobamate.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(34)</num>
            <text>Methohexital.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(35)</num>
            <text>Methylphenobarbital (mephobarbital).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(36)</num>
            <text>Midazolam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(37)</num>
            <text>Nimetazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(38)</num>
            <text>Nitrazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(39)</num>
            <text>Nordiazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(40)</num>
            <text>Oxazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(41)</num>
            <text>Oxazolam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(42)</num>
            <text>Paraldehyde.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(43)</num>
            <text>Petrichloral.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(44)</num>
            <text>Phenobarbital.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(45)</num>
            <text>Pinazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(46)</num>
            <text>Prazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(47)</num>
            <text>Quazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(48)</num>
            <text>Temazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(49)</num>
            <text>Tetrazepam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(50)</num>
            <text>Triazolam.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(51)</num>
            <text>Zaleplon.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(52)</num>
            <text>Zolpidem.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(53)</num>
            <text>Zopiclone.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>Fenfluramine. Any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances, including its salts, isomers (whether optical, position, or geometric), and salts of such isomers, whenever the existence of such salts, isomers, and salts of isomers is possible:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Fenfluramine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>(Reserved)</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>Stimulants. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a stimulant effect on the central nervous system, including its salts, isomers and salts of isomers:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Cathine [(+)-norpseudoephedrine].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Diethylpropion.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Fencamfamin.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Fenproporex.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Mazindol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Mefenorex.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Modafinil.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>Pemoline (including organometallic complexes and chelates thereof).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>Phentermine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text>Pipradrol.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(11)</num>
            <text>Sibutramine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(12)</num>
            <text>SPA[(-)-1-dimethylamino- 1,2-diphenylethane].</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>Other substances. Unless specifically excepted or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances, including its salts:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Pentazocine.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Butorphanol (including its optical isomers).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-10</num>
        <heading>Schedule V.</heading>
        <text>Unless specifically excepted by tribal regulation or unless listed in another schedule, any of the following substances, whether produced directly or indirectly by extraction from substances of vegetable origin, or independently by means of chemical synthesis, or by a combination of extraction and chemical synthesis, are listed in Schedule V:</text>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Narcotic drugs containing nonnarcotic active medicinal ingredients. Any compound, mixture, or preparation containing any of the following narcotic drugs, or their salts calculated as the free anhydrous base or alkaloid, in limited quantities as set forth below, which shall include one or more nonnarcotic active medicinal ingredients in sufficient proportion to confer upon the compound, mixture, or preparation valuable medicinal qualities other than those possessed by narcotic drugs alone:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Not more than 200 milligrams of codeine per 100 milliliters or per 100 grams.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Not more than 100 milligrams of dihydrocodeine per 100 milliliters or per 100 grams.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Not more than 100 milligrams of ethylmorphine per 100 milliliters or per 100 grams.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Not more than 2.5 milligrams of diphenoxylate and not less than 25 micrograms of atropine sulfate per dosage unit.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Not more than 100 milligrams of opium per 100 milliliters or per 100 grams.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Not more than 0.5 milligram of difenoxin and not less than 25 micrograms of atropine sulfate per dosage unit.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Stimulants. Unless specifically exempted or excluded or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a stimulant effect on the central nervous system, including its salts, isomers and salts of isomers:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Pyrovalerone.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>(Reserved)</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>Depressants. Unless specifically exempted or excluded or unless listed in another schedule, any material, compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of the following substances having a depressant effect on the central nervous system, including its salts:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Ezogabine [N-(2-amino-4-[4-fluorobenzylamino]-phenyl)-carbamic acid ethyl ester].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Lacosamide [(R)-2-acetoamido- N -benzyl-3-methoxy-propionamide].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Pregabalin [(S)-3-(aminomethyl)-5-methylhexanoic acid].</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Gabapentin [241-(aminomethyl) cyclohexyl] acetic acid]. <strong>[Added 2-6-2020 by Ord. No. 19-40]</strong></text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-11</num>
        <heading>Exception for certain religious ceremonies.</heading>
        <text><cite path="|II|306|1|II">This article</cite> does not apply to the holistic (sacred) use of peyote in the bona fide religious ceremonies of the Native American Church. Use, possession, or transfer of such substance in connection with such religious ceremonies shall not be punishable under <cite path="|II|306|1|II">this article</cite>.</text>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-12</num>
        <heading>Manufacture, distribution, and dispensing of controlled substances.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Persons registered under federal law to manufacture, distribute, dispense or conduct research with controlled substances may possess, manufacture, distribute, dispense or conduct research with those substances on this Reservation to the extent authorized by their federal registration and in conformity with the other provisions of <cite path="|II|306|1|II">this article</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Businesses and persons licensed under Tribal Law to manufacture, distribute, dispense or conduct research with marijuana or cannabis may possess, manufacture, distribute, dispense or conduct research with marijuana or cannabis on this Reservation to the extent authorized by their Tribal license. The provisions of <cite path="§306-13">§ 306-13</cite> are not applicable to such licensed businesses.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>The following persons need not be registered under federal law to lawfully possess controlled substances on the Menominee Indian Reservation:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>An agent or employee of any registered manufacturer, distributor or dispenser of any controlled substance if the agent or employee is acting in the usual course of the agent's or employee's business or employment.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>A common or contract carrier or warehouse keeper, or an employee thereof, whose possession of any controlled substance is in the usual course of business or employment.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>An ultimate user or a person in possession of any controlled substance pursuant to a lawful order of a practitioner or in lawful possession of a Schedule V substance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Any person exempted under federal law or for whom federal registration requirements have been waived.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>A licensed agent or employee of a business licensed to manufacture, distribute, dispense or conduct research with marijuana or cannabis under Tribal Law if the agent or employee is acting in the usual course of the agent or employee's business or employment.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Any employee or agent of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin acting within the scope of their duties in regard to regulation of businesses licensed to manufacture, distribute, dispense or conduct research with marijuana or cannabis under Tribal Law, and any person or entity performing tests on marijuana or cannabis pursuant to an agreement with such a licensed business.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Amended 6-20-2024 by Ord. No. 24-29</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-13</num>
        <heading>Prescriptions.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>In this section, "medical treatment" includes dispensing or administering a narcotic drug for pain, including intractable pain.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Except when dispensed directly by a practitioner, other than a pharmacy, to an ultimate user, no controlled substance included in Schedule II may be dispensed without the written hard copy or electronic prescription of a practitioner.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>In emergency situations, as defined by rule of the Legislature, Schedule II drugs may be dispensed upon an oral prescription of a practitioner, reduced promptly to a written hard copy or electronic record and filed by the pharmacy. Prescriptions shall be retained in conformity with rules of the pharmacy examining board of the State of Wisconsin and must have an active DEA certificate. No prescription for a Schedule II substance may be refilled.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>Except when dispensed directly by a practitioner, other than a pharmacy, to an ultimate user, a controlled substance included in Schedule III or IV, which is a prescription drug, shall not be dispensed without a written, oral or electronic prescription of a practitioner. The prescription shall not be filled or refilled except as designated on the prescription and in any case not more than six months after the date thereof, nor may it be refilled more than five times, unless renewed by the practitioner.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>A substance included in Schedule V may be distributed or dispensed only for a medical purpose, including medical treatment or authorized research.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>A practitioner may dispense or deliver a controlled substance to or for an individual or animal only for medical treatment or authorized research in the ordinary course of that practitioner's profession.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>A pharmacist is immune from any civil or criminal liability and from discipline for any act taken by the pharmacist in reliance on a reasonable belief that an order purporting to be a prescription was issued by a practitioner in the usual course of professional treatment or in authorized research.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>F.</num>
          <text>No practitioner shall prescribe, orally, electronically or in writing, or take without a prescription a controlled substance included in Schedule I, II, III or IV for the practitioner's own personal use.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-14</num>
        <heading>Optometrist limitations.</heading>
        <text>An optometrist who is allowed to use therapeutic pharmaceutical agents and to dispense a contact lens that delivers a therapeutic pharmaceutical agent:</text>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>May not prescribe, dispense, or administer a controlled substance included in Schedule I or II.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>May prescribe, dispense, or administer only those controlled substances included in Schedules III, IV, and V that are permitted for prescription or administration.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>Shall include with each prescription order all of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>A statement that he or she is allowed to use therapeutic pharmaceutical agents.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The indicated use of the controlled substance included in Schedule III, IV or V so prescribed.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-15</num>
        <heading>Advanced practice nurse limitations.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>An advanced practice nurse, also referred to as "nurse practioner," who is certified under <cite doc="Wis. Stat." path="§441.16">§ 441.16, Wis. Stats.</cite>, or certified by a national board and must have been approved for prescriptive authority and must also have an active DEA certificate, may prescribe controlled substances only as permitted by the rules promulgated under the certifying body and the rules governing the prescriptive authority.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>An advanced practice nurse as defined above in <cite path="§306-15|A">Subsection A</cite> shall include with each prescription order the advanced practice nurse prescriber certification number issued to him or her by the board of nursing.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>An advanced practice nurse as defined above in <cite path="§306-15|A">Subsection A</cite> may dispense a controlled substance only by prescribing or administering the controlled substance or as otherwise permitted by the rules promulgated under <cite doc="Wis. Stat." path="§441.16|(3)">§ 441.16(3), Wis. Stats.</cite>, or any federal guidelines governing the national board certification and prescriptive authority.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container cache:ref-path="II|306|1|III">
      <prefix>Article</prefix>
      <num>III</num>
      <heading>Prohibited Acts and Penalties</heading>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-16</num>
        <heading>Manufacture, distribution or delivery of controlled substances or controlled substance analogs.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Prohibited acts. Except as authorized by <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1, it is unlawful for any person to knowingly or intentionally manufacture, traffic, distribute, dispense or deliver, or possess with the intent to manufacture, distribute, dispense, sell, or deliver, a controlled substance or controlled substance analog. Intent under <cite path="§306-16|A.">this subsection</cite> may be demonstrated by, without limitation because of enumeration, evidence of the quantity and monetary value of the substances possessed, the possession of manufacturing implements or paraphernalia, and the activities or statements of the person in possession of the controlled substance or a controlled substance analog prior to and after the alleged violation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Penalties. Except as otherwise provided in <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1, any person who violates <cite path="§306-16|A">Subsection A</cite> shall be sentenced as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Any person who violates <cite path="§306-16|B.|(1)">this subsection</cite>, except as provided for in §<cite path="§306-11">§ 306-11</cite>, 306-12, 306-13, 306-14, and 306-15, with respect to a controlled substance, or a controlled substance analog, that person shall be subject to a Class A misdemeanor. See <cite path="§306-29">§ 306-29</cite>, Classification of misdemeanors.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>Anyone convicted under this section may be banished from the Reservation as part of sentencing for one year for the first offense.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>Anyone convicted under this section shall be banished as part of sentencing for two years for their second offense.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>Anyone convicted under this section for a third or subsequent conviction shall be referred to the Tribal Legislature for lifetime banishment pursuant to <cite path="|I|80">Chapter 80</cite>.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(d)</num>
              <text>If banishment is ordered, in the event of a death in the immediate family of the convicted/ banished person, the Tribal Court, in its discretion, may order permission for such person to return to the Reservation for a period not to exceed four days. The convicted/banished individual must notify the Tribal Police Department of the request and any subsequent Court order.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(e)</num>
              <text>The Tribal Court shall require that the defendant complete an AODA assessment from a licensed professional approved by the court and attend and complete any certified alcohol or drug rehabilitation program if required by the assessment.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Minor enhancer. If a person 18 years of age or over violates <cite path="§306-16|A">§ 306-16A</cite> by distributing or delivering a controlled substance or a controlled substance analog to a person 17 years of age or under, the maximum term of a Class A misdemeanor shall be imposed. See <cite path="§306-29">§ 306-29</cite>, Classification of misdemeanors.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>Anyone convicted under this section may be banished from the Reservation as part of sentencing for one year for the first offense.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>Anyone convicted under this section shall banished as part of sentencing for five years for their second offense.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>Anyone convicted under this section for a third or subsequent conviction shall be referred to the Tribal Legislature for lifetime banishment pursuant to <cite path="|I|80">Chapter 80</cite>.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Causing death enhancer. If a person violates <cite path="§306-16|A">§ 306-16A</cite> by distributing, selling, or delivering a controlled substance or a controlled substance analog and such violation results in or causes a <cite>part i</cite>n the overdose death of the receiver of the controlled substance, the maximum term of a Class A misdemeanor shall be imposed and the person shall be referred to the Tribal Legislature for lifetime banishment pursuant to <cite path="|I|80">Chapter 80</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The Court, in assessing the penalties, shall take into consideration the amount of controlled substance possessed, the relative danger of the drug, prior convictions for possession and other factors the Court finds relevant.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>This offense may be subject to federal prosecution in addition to Tribal prosecution. If the Tribal prosecution is dismissed due to federal prosecution, the federal conviction(s) may be used by the Tribal Legislature for banishment pursuant to <cite path="|I|80">Chapter 80</cite>. Nothing in <cite path="|II|306">this chapter</cite> restricts or limits the ability of the Tribal Legislature to assert their inherent, sovereign right of exclusion or banishment under tribal law.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Amended 11-19-2020 by Ord. No. 20-35</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-17</num>
        <heading>Counterfeit controlled substances.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Prohibited act. Except as authorized by <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1, it is unlawful for any person to create, manufacture, distribute, deliver or possess with intent to distribute or deliver a counterfeit controlled substance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Penalty. Any person who violates this section with respect to a counterfeit controlled substance shall be subject to a Class C misdemeanor. See <cite path="§306-29">§ 306-29</cite>, Classification of misdemeanors.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>Banishment. Anyone convicted under this section:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>May be banished from the Reservation as part of sentencing for one year for the first offense;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Shall be banished from the Reservation as part of sentencing for two years for the second offense; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>For a third or subsequent conviction shall be referred to the Tribal Legislature for lifetime banishment pursuant to <cite path="|I|80">Chapter 80</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>This offense may be subject to federal prosecution in addition to Tribal prosecution.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Amended 11-19-2020 by Ord. No. 20-35</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-18</num>
        <heading>Possession of controlled substances or controlled substance analogs.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Prohibited act. No person may possess or attempt to possess a controlled substance or a controlled substance analog on his person, in any type of vehicle under his control, or within any type of dwelling in which he lives, visits, or happens to be found, unless the person obtains the substance or the analog directly from, or pursuant to a valid prescription or order of, a practitioner who is acting in the course of his or her professional practice, or unless the person is otherwise authorized by <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1 to possess the substance or the analog.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Penalties.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Any person who violates this section shall be subject to a Class C misdemeanor. See <cite path="§306-29">§ 306-29</cite>, Classification of misdemeanors.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>If the offense is a second drug offense violation under this code, then the penalty shall increase to a Class B misdemeanor. See <cite path="§306-29">§ 306-29</cite>, Classification of misdemeanors.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Third or subsequent drug offense violations shall follow <cite path="§306-27">§ 306-27</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>In addition to the above penalties, the Court shall require that the defendant complete an AODA assessment from a licensed professional approved by the court and attend and complete any certified alcohol or drug rehabilitation program if required by the assessment.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>This offense may be subject to federal prosecution in addition to Tribal prosecution.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Amended 11-19-2020 by Ord. No. 20-35</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-19</num>
        <heading>Imitation controlled substances.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Prohibited act. No person may knowingly distribute or deliver, attempt to distribute or deliver or cause to be distributed or delivered a noncontrolled substance and expressly or impliedly represent any of the following to the recipient:</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>That the substance is a controlled substance.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>That the substance is of a nature, appearance or effect that will allow the recipient to display, sell, distribute, deliver or use the noncontrolled substance as a controlled substance, if the representation is made under circumstances in which the person has reasonable cause to believe that the noncontrolled substance will be used or distributed for use as a controlled substance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Proof of any of the following is prima facie evidence of a representation specified in <cite path="§306-19|A|(1)">Subsection A(1)</cite> or (2).</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>The physical appearance of the finished product containing the substance is substantially the same as that of a specific controlled substance.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>The substance is unpackaged or is packaged in a manner normally used for the illegal delivery of a controlled substance.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The substance is not labeled in accordance with 21 U.S.C. §§ 352 or 353.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The person distributing or delivering, attempting to distribute or deliver or causing distribution or delivery of the substance to be made states to the recipient that the substance may be resold at a price that substantially exceeds the value of the substance.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Penalty. Any person who violates <cite path="§306-19|B.">this subsection</cite> is guilty of a Class D misdemeanor. See <cite path="§306-29">§ 306-29</cite>, Classification of misdemeanors.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>Banishment. Anyone convicted under this section:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>May be banished from the Reservation as part of sentencing for one year for the first offense;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Shall be banished from the Reservation as part of sentencing for two years for the second offense; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>For a third or subsequent conviction shall be referred to the Tribal Legislature for lifetime banishment pursuant to <cite path="|I|80">Chapter 80</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>This offense may be subject to federal prosecution in addition to Tribal prosecution.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Amended 11-19-2020 by Ord. No. 20-35</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-20</num>
        <heading>Maintaining drug dwellings.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Prohibited act. It is unlawful for any person knowingly to keep or maintain any store, shop, warehouse, dwelling, building, vehicle, boat, aircraft or other structure or place, which is resorted to by persons using controlled substances in violation of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1 for the purpose of using these substances, or which is used for manufacturing, keeping or delivering them in violation of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Penalty.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Any person who violates <cite path="§306-20|B.|(1)">this subsection</cite> is guilty of a Class B misdemeanor. See <cite path="§306-29">§ 306-29</cite>, Classification of misdemeanors.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Any person who violates <cite path="§306-20|B.|(2)">this subsection</cite> within 1,000 feet of any school, boys and girls club, ceremonial grounds, playgrounds, sport fields/parks, or a park is guilty of a Class A misdemeanor. See <cite path="§306-29">§ 306-29</cite>, Classification of misdemeanors.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>Banishment. Anyone convicted under this section:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>May be banished from the Reservation as part of sentencing for one year for the first offense;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Shall be banished from the Reservation as part of sentencing for five years for the second offense; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>For a third or subsequent conviction shall be referred to the Tribal Legislature for lifetime banishment pursuant to <cite path="|I|80">Chapter 80</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>This offense may be subject to federal prosecution in addition to Tribal prosecution.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Amended 11-19-2020 by Ord. No. 20-35</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-21</num>
        <heading>Possession of controlled substances by fraud.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Prohibited act. It is unlawful for any person:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>To acquire or obtain possession of a controlled substance by misrepresentation, fraud, forgery, deception or subterfuge;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Without authorization, to make, distribute or possess any punch, die, plate, stone or other instrument designed to print, imprint or reproduce the trademark, trade name or other identifying mark, imprint or device of another or any likeness of any of the foregoing upon any drug or container or labeling thereof so as:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>To make a counterfeit substance; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>To duplicate substantially the physical appearance, form, package or label of a controlled substance.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Penalty. Any person who violates <cite path="§306-21|B.">this subsection</cite> is guilty of a Class A misdemeanor. See <cite path="§306-29">§ 306-29</cite>, Classification of misdemeanors.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>This offense may be subject to federal prosecution in addition to Tribal prosecution.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Amended 11-19-2020 by Ord. No. 20-35</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-22</num>
        <heading>Use of children in illegal drug distribution or manufacturing.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Prohibited act. It is unlawful for any person who has attained the age of 17 years to knowingly solicit, hire, direct, employ or use a person who is under the age of 17 years for the purpose of violating <cite path="§306-16|A">§ 306-16A</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Penalty. For any person who violates <cite path="§306-22|B.">this subsection</cite>, the maximum term of a Class A misdemeanor shall be imposed. See <cite path="§306-29">§ 306-29</cite>, Classification of misdemeanors.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>Banishment. Anyone convicted under this section:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>May be banished from the Reservation as part of sentencing up to five years for the first offense;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Shall be banished from the Reservation as part of sentencing for 10 years for the second offense; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>For a third or subsequent conviction shall be referred to the Tribal Legislature for lifetime banishment pursuant to <cite path="|I|80">Chapter 80</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>The knowledge requirement under <cite path="§306-22|A">Subsection A</cite> does not require proof of knowledge of the age of the child. It is not a defense to a prosecution under this section that the actor mistakenly believed that the person solicited, hired, directed, employed or used under <cite path="§306-16">§ 306-16</cite> had attained the age of 18 years, even if the mistaken belief was reasonable.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>If the conduct described under <cite path="§306-22|A">§ 306-22A</cite> results in a violation under <cite path="§306-16">§ 306-16</cite>, the actor is subject to prosecution and conviction under <cite path="§306-16|A">§ 306-16A</cite> or this section, or both.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>F.</num>
          <text>This offense may be subject to federal prosecution in addition to Tribal prosecution.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Amended 11-19-2020 by Ord. No. 20-35</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-23</num>
        <heading>Possession of drug paraphernalia.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Prohibited act. No person may use, or possess with the primary intent to use, drug paraphernalia to plant, propagate, cultivate, grow, harvest, manufacture, compound, convert, produce, process, prepare, test, analyze, pack, repack, store, contain, conceal, inject, ingest, inhale or otherwise introduce into the human body a controlled substance or controlled substance analog in violation of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Penalty. Any person who violates <cite path="§306-23|B.">this subsection</cite> is subject to a Class E misdemeanor. See <cite path="§306-29">§ 306-29</cite>, Classification of misdemeanors.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>This offense may be subject to federal prosecution in addition to Tribal prosecution.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Amended 11-19-2020 by Ord. No. 20-35</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-24</num>
        <heading>Manufacture or delivery of drug paraphernalia.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Prohibited act. No person may deliver, possess with intent to deliver, or manufacture with intent to deliver drug paraphernalia, knowing that it will be primarily used to plant, propagate, cultivate, grow, harvest, manufacture, compound, convert, produce, process, prepare, test, analyze, pack, repack, store, contain, conceal, inject, ingest, inhale or otherwise introduce into the human body a controlled substance or controlled substance analog in violation of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Penalty.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Any person who violates <cite path="§306-24|B.|(1)">this subsection</cite> is subject to a Class D misdemeanor. See <cite path="§306-29">§ 306-29</cite>, Classification of misdemeanors.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>If any person 18 years of age or over violates <cite path="§306-24|A">Subsection A</cite> by delivering drug paraphernalia to a person 17 years of age or under the penalty shall be subject to a Class C misdemeanor. See <cite path="§306-29">§ 306-29</cite>, Classification of misdemeanors.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>This offense may be subject to federal prosecution in addition to Tribal prosecution.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Amended 11-19-2020 by Ord. No. 20-35</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-25</num>
        <heading>Abuse of hazardous substances.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>In this section:</text>
          <text>ABUSE — To ingest, inhale, or otherwise introduce into the human body a hazardous substance in a manner that does not comply with any cautionary labeling that is required for the hazardous substance under <cite doc="Wis. Stat." path="§100.37">§ 100.37, Wis. Stats.</cite>, under federal law, under tribal law, or in a manner that is not intended by the manufacturer of the hazardous substance, and that is intended to induce intoxication or elation, to stupefy the central nervous system, or to change the human audio, visual, or mental processes.</text>
          <text>CORROSIVE — Any substance which, in contact with living tissue, will cause destruction of tissue by chemical action, but does not refer to action on inanimate surfaces.</text>
          <text>DISTRIBUTE — To transfer a hazardous substance from one person to another.</text>
          <text>HAZARDOUS SUBSTANCE — Includes any substance or mixture of substances, including a toy or other article intended for use by children, which is toxic, is corrosive, is an irritant, is a strong sensitizer, is flammable or combustible, or generates pressure through decomposition, heat or other means, if such substance or mixture of substances may cause substantial personal injury or substantial illness during or as a proximate result of any customary or reasonably foreseeable handling or use, including reasonably foreseeable ingestion by children. "Hazardous substance" also includes any substance or mixture of substances that has the capacity to produce personal injury or illness to a person who abuses the substance and includes any household product, or any mixture of household products.</text>
          <text>HOUSEHOLD PRODUCT — Any food, drug, device or cosmetic or any article, product or commodity of any kind or class which is customarily produced or distributed for sale through retail sales agencies or instrumentalities for consumption by individuals, or use by individuals for purposes of personal care or in the performance of services ordinarily rendered within the household, and which usually is consumed or expended in the course of that consumption or use.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Whoever does any of the following is guilty of a Class B misdemeanor:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Possesses a hazardous substance with the intent to abuse the hazardous substance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Intentionally abuses a hazardous substance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Whoever distributes, or possesses with intent to distribute, a hazardous substance, knowing or having reason to know that the hazardous substance will be abused, is guilty of a Class A misdemeanor.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text><cite path="§306-25|B|(2)">Subsection B(2)</cite> does not apply to a person who possesses or uses the hazardous substance if the substance is obtained from, or pursuant to a valid prescription or order of, a practitioner, as defined in <cite path="§306-3">§ 306-3</cite>, while acting in the course of professional practice. See <cite path="§306-29">§ 306-29</cite>, Classification of misdemeanors.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text><cite path="§306-25|B|(3)">Subsection B(3)</cite> does not apply to a person who distributes a hazardous substance in an ordinary course of business.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>This offense may be subject to federal prosecution in addition to Tribal prosecution.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Amended 11-19-2020 by Ord. No. 20-35</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-26</num>
        <heading>Attempt or conspiracy.</heading>
        <text>Prohibited act. Any person who attempts or conspires to commit any offense defined in <cite path="|II|306|1|III">this article</cite> shall be subject to the same penalties as those prescribed for the offense, the commission of which was the object of the attempt or conspiracy.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Amended 11-19-2020 by Ord. No. 20-35</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-27</num>
        <heading>Third or subsequent offenses.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>If a person is charged with a third or subsequent offense within the last 10 years under <cite path="|II|306|1|III">this article</cite> or equivalent state or federal law and the person is convicted of that third or subsequent offense, the maximum term of imprisonment for the offense shall be increased one level, not to exceed 12 months in jail and/or a fine of $5,000 unless the offense is charged subject to enhanced sentencing.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Unless specified differently in the specific offense sections, anyone convicted and sentenced pursuant to this section may be banished from the Reservation as part as sentencing up to five years per offense.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>The third or subsequent offense shall be calculated within the 10 years by counting the prior offense(s) date(s) from date of conviction or release from incarceration or whichever is less, except that years banished shall not be counted.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Amended 11-19-2020 by Ord. No. 20-35</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-28</num>
        <heading>Offenses involving intent to deliver or distribute controlled substances on or near certain places.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>If any person violates any part of <cite path="|II|306|1|III">this Article</cite> III by possessing with intent to deliver or distribute a controlled substance or analog of any of these substances, and the delivery, distribution or possession takes place under any of the following circumstances, the maximum term of incarceration prescribed by law for that crime may be increased by the following, but not to exceed 12 months in jail and/or a fine of $5,000.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>While the person is in or on the premises of a public housing project, the violator shall be subjected to an additional 30 days of incarceration in the Tribal Jail.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>At a tribal or county park, the violator shall be subjected to an additional 30 days of incarceration in the Tribal Jail.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>At a jail or correctional facility, the violator shall be subjected to an additional 30 days of incarceration in the Tribal Jail.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>At a public swimming area or pool open to members of the public, the violator shall be subjected to an additional 30 days of incarceration in the Tribal Jail.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>F.</num>
          <text>At a youth center or a community center, the violator shall be subjected to an additional 30 days of incarceration in the Tribal Jail.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>G.</num>
          <text>At any private, tribal or public school premises, the violator shall be subjected to an additional 30 days of incarceration in the Tribal Jail.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>H.</num>
          <text>At any Menominee transportation vehicle or facility, the violator shall be subjected to an additional 30 days of incarceration in the Tribal Jail.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>I.</num>
          <text>While the person is in or on the premises of an approved treatment facility that provides alcohol and other drug abuse treatment, the violator shall be subjected to an additional 30 days of incarceration in the Tribal Jail.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>J.</num>
          <text>No additional penalty stated above shall make any penalty in subsection exceed 12 months in jail and/ or a fine of $5,000 unless it is done pursuant to enhanced sentencing requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>K.</num>
          <text>Banishment. Anyone convicted under this section, unless subject to greater terms of banishment:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>May be banished from the Reservation as part of sentencing up to one year for the first offense;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Shall be banished from the Reservation as part of sentencing for two years for the second offense; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>For a third or subsequent conviction shall be referred to the Tribal Legislature for lifetime banishment pursuant to <cite path="|I|80">Chapter 80</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Amended 11-19-2020 by Ord. No. 20-35</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-29</num>
        <heading>Classification of misdemeanors.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Misdemeanors in <cite path="|II|306">this chapter</cite> are criminal acts that are classified as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Class A misdemeanor. The penalty for a Class A misdemeanor shall be the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>A term of probation not to exceed one year;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>A mandatory minimum sentence of 270 days of imprisonment that must be served and of which no portion may be stayed;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>An additional term of imprisonment not to exceed one year, when combined with the mandatory minimum sentence, may be implemented at the Court's discretion (95 days); and/or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(d)</num>
              <text>A fine not less than $2,501 and not to exceed $5,000.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Class B misdemeanor. The penalty for a Class B misdemeanor shall be the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>A term of probation not to exceed one year;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>A mandatory minimum sentence of 180 days of imprisonment that must be served and of which no portion may be stayed;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>An additional term of imprisonment not to exceed 270 days, when combined with the mandatory minimum sentence, may be implemented at the Court's discretion (90 days); and/or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(d)</num>
              <text>A fine not less than $1,001 and not to exceed $2,500.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Class C misdemeanor. The penalty for a Class C misdemeanor shall be the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>A term of probation not to exceed one year;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>A mandatory minimum sentence of 90 days of imprisonment that must be served and of which no portion may be stayed;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>An additional term of imprisonment not to exceed 180 days, when combined with the mandatory minimum sentence, may be implemented at the Court's discretion (90 days); and/or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(d)</num>
              <text>A fine not less than $501 and not to exceed $1,000.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Class D misdemeanor. The penalty for a Class D misdemeanor shall be the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>A term of probation not to exceed one year;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>A mandatory minimum sentence of 30 days of imprisonment that must be served and of which no portion may be stayed;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>An additional term of imprisonment not to exceed 90 days, when combined with the mandatory minimum sentence, may be implemented at the Court's discretion (60 days); and/or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(d)</num>
              <text>A fine not less than $251 and not to exceed $500.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Class E misdemeanor. The penalty for a Class E misdemeanor shall be the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>A term of probation not to exceed one year;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>A term of imprisonment not to exceed 30 days, which may be imposed or stayed at the Court's discretion; and/or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>A fine not less than $101 and not to exceed $250.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>The sentencing guidelines in the misdemeanor schedule in <cite path="§306-29|B.">this subsection</cite> shall apply only to violations in <cite path="|II|306">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>If banishment is ordered:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The Tribal Court, in its discretion may allow a convicted and banished person to return to the Reservation for medical or behavioral health services at the Menominee Tribal Clinic and the Maehnowesekiyah Wellness Center. The convicted/banished individual must notify Tribal Police of their appointment prior to their scheduled appointment and shall carry proof, such as a letter and/or appointment card signed by an official from the service provider, of their appointment; travel must be directly to the appointment and the individual must immediately leave the reservation following the conclusion of their appointment.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>In the event of a death in the immediate family of the convicted/banished person, the Tribal Court, in its discretion, may order permission for such person to return to the Reservation for a period not to exceed four days. The convicted/banished individual must notify the Tribal Police Department of the request and any subsequent Court order.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>Referrals to Drug Treatment and Diversion Court Programs may be made by the Court for cases that qualify under established program guidelines.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>Court may require that the defendant complete an AODA assessment from a licensed professional approved by the court and attend and complete any certified alcohol or drug rehabilitation program if required by the assessment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>F.</num>
          <text>Court may order restitution.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>G.</num>
          <text>Offenses in the article may be subject to federal prosecution in addition to Tribal prosecution. If the Tribal prosecution is dismissed due to federal prosecution, the federal conviction(s) may be used by the Tribal Legislature for banishment pursuant to <cite path="|I|80">Chapter 80</cite>. Nothing in <cite path="|II|306">this chapter</cite> restricts or limits the ability of the Tribal Legislature to assert their inherent, sovereign right of exclusion or banishment under tribal law.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Amended 11-19-2020 by Ord. No. 20-35</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-30</num>
        <heading>Drug identification.</heading>
        <text>The Menominee Tribal Legislature authorizes and directs the Menominee tribal law enforcement officers to complete drug identification by use of a standard drug field test kit or use of The Drug Identification Bible and its associated website. A positive reading for any controlled substance shall be taken as prima facie evidence of a controlled substance.</text>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-31</num>
        <heading>Forfeiture.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>The following are subject to forfeiture:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>All controlled substances, controlled substance analogs which have been manufactured, delivered, distributed, dispensed or acquired in violation of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>All raw materials, products and equipment of any kind which are used, or intended for use, in manufacturing, compounding, processing, delivering, distributing, importing or exporting any controlled substance or controlled substance analog in violation of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>All property which is used, or intended for use, as a container for property described in <cite path="§306-31|A|(1)">Subsection A(1)</cite> and (2).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>All vehicles which are used, or intended for use, to transport, or in any manner to facilitate the transportation, for the purpose of sale or receipt of property described in <cite path="§306-31|A|(1)">Subsection A(1)</cite> and</text>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>or for the purpose of transporting any property or weapon used or to be used or received in the commission of any violation under <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1, but:</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>No vehicle used by any person as a common carrier in the transaction of business as a common carrier is subject to forfeiture under this section unless it appears that the owner or other person in charge of the vehicle is a consenting party or privy to a violation of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>No vehicle is subject to forfeiture under this section by reason of any act or omission established by the owner thereof to have been committed or omitted without the owner's knowledge or consent;</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A vehicle is not subject to forfeiture for a violation of §<cite path="§306-17">§ 306-17</cite>, 306-23 and 306-25; and</text>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>If forfeiture of a vehicle encumbered by a bona fide perfected security interest occurs, the holder of the security interest shall be paid from the proceeds of the forfeiture if the security interest was perfected prior to the date of the commission of the felony which forms the basis for the forfeiture and he or she neither had knowledge of nor consented to the act or omission.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>All books, records and research products and materials, including formulas, microfilm, tapes, video, and data, which are used, or intended for use, in violation of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>All property, real or personal, including money, directly or indirectly derived from or realized through the commission of any crime under <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Any drug paraphernalia, as defined by <cite path="§306-3">§ 306-3</cite>, used in violation of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Property subject to forfeiture under <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1 may be seized by any officer or employee designated in <cite path="|I|132">Chapter 132</cite> or a law enforcement officer upon process issued by any court of record have jurisdiction over the property. Seizure without process may be made if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The seizure is incident to arrest or a search under a search warrant or an inspection under an administrative inspection warrant.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The property subject to seizure has been the subject of a prior judgment in favor of the Tribe in a criminal injunction or forfeiture proceeding based upon <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The officer or employee or law enforcement officer has probable cause to believe that the property is directly or indirectly dangerous to health or safety; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The officer or employee or law enforcement officer has probable cause to believe that the property was used or is intended to be used in violation of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1, that the property was derived from or realized through a crime under <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1 or that the property is a vehicle which was used as described in <cite path="§306-31|A|(4)">Subsection A(4) of this section</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>In the event of seizure under <cite path="§306-31|B">Subsection B</cite>, proceedings under <cite path="§306-31|D">Subsection D</cite> shall be instituted promptly. All dispositions and forfeitures under this section shall be made with due provision for the rights of innocent persons under <cite path="§306-31|A|(4)(a)">Subsection A(4)(a)</cite>, (b) and (d). Any property seized but not forfeited shall be returned to its rightful owner. Any person claiming the right to possession of property seized may apply for its return to the Menominee Tribal Court. The Court shall order such notice as it deems adequate to be given the Tribal Prosecutor and all persons who have or may have an interest in the property and shall hold a hearing to hear all claims to its true ownership. If the right to possession is proved to the courts satisfaction, it shall order the property returned if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The property is not needed as evidence or, if needed, satisfactory arrangements can be made for its return for subsequent use as evidence; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>All proceedings in which it might be required have been completed.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>Property taken or detained under this section shall not be subject to replevin, but is deemed to be in the custody of the Tribal Police subject only to the orders and decrees of the court having jurisdiction over the forfeiture proceedings. When property is seized under <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1, the person seizing the property may:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Place the property under seal;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Remove the property to a place designated by it; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Require the Tribal Police Chief, or designated law enforcement officer by the Police Chief, to take custody of the property and remove it to an appropriate location for disposition in accordance with law.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>When property is forfeited under <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1, the agency whose officer or employee seized the property shall do one of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Retain it for official use by the Tribe.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Sell that which is not required to be destroyed by law and which is not harmful to the public. The agency may use 50% of the amount received for payment of forfeiture expenses. The remainders of the proceeds are to be deposited in tribal general funds. In <cite path="§306-31|E.|(2)">this subsection</cite>, "forfeiture expenses" include all proper expenses of the proceedings for forfeiture and sale, including expenses of seizure, maintenance of custody, advertising, and court costs and the costs of investigation and prosecution reasonably incurred.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Require the Tribal Police Chief, or designated law enforcement officer by the Police Chief, to take custody of the property and remove it to an appropriate location for disposition in accordance with law.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>If the property forfeited is money, retain the sum of all of the following for payment of forfeiture expenses, as defined in <cite path="§306-31|E|(2)">Subsection E(2)</cite> above, and deposit the remainder in tribal general funds.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>If the amount of money does not exceed $2,000, 70% of that amount. In excess of $2,000, 50% of the amount seized.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>F.</num>
          <text>Controlled substances included in Schedule I and controlled substance analogs of controlled substances included in Schedule I that are possessed, transferred, sold, offered for sale or attempted to be possessed in violation of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1 are contraband and shall be seized and summarily forfeited to the Tribe. Controlled substances included in Schedule I and controlled substance analogs of controlled substances included in Schedule I that are seized or come into the possession of the Tribe, the owners of which are unknown, are contraband and shall be summarily forfeited to the Tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>G.</num>
          <text>Flunitrazepam or ketamine that is possessed, transferred, sold, offered for sale or attempted to be possessed in violation of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1 is contraband and shall be seized and summarily forfeited to the Tribe. Flunitrazepam or ketamine that are seized or come into the possession of the Tribe, the owner of which is unknown, is contraband and shall be summarily forfeited to the Tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>H.</num>
          <text>Species of plants from which controlled substances in Schedules I and II may be derived which have been planted or cultivated in violation of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1, or of which the owners or cultivators are unknown, or which are wild growths, may be seized and summarily forfeited to the Tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>I.</num>
          <text>The failure, upon demand by any officer or employee designated in <cite path="|I|132">Chapter 132</cite>, of the person in occupancy or in control of land or premises upon which the species of plants are growing or being stored, to produce an appropriate federal registration, or proof that the person is the holder thereof, constitutes authority for the seizure and forfeiture of the plants.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-32</num>
        <heading>Forfeiture proceedings.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Type of action; where brought. In an action brought to cause the forfeiture of any property seized under <cite path="§306-31">§ 306-31</cite>, the court may render a judgment in rem or against a party personally, or both. The Menominee Tribal Court shall have jurisdiction over any proceedings regarding the property seized with the Menominee Reservation when the action is commenced in Tribal Court. Any property seized may be continued for cause or upon the stipulation of the parties. Any property seized may be the subject of a federal forfeiture action.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Commencement.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The Tribal Prosecutor of the Menominee Indian Reservation shall commence the forfeiture action within 60 days after the seizure of the property, except that the defendant may request that the forfeiture proceedings be adjourned until after adjudication of any charge concerning a crime which was the basis for the seizure of the property. The request shall be granted. The forfeiture action shall be commenced by filing a summons, complaint and affidavit of the person who seized the property with the Menominee Tribal Clerk of Court, provided service of authenticated copies of those papers is made within 90 days after filing upon the person from whom the property was seized and upon any person known to have a bona fide perfected security interest in the property.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Upon service of an answer, the action shall be set for hearing within 60 days of the service of the answer but may be continued for cause or upon stipulation of the parties.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>If no answer is served or no issue of law or fact has been joined and the time for that service or joining issue has expired, or if any defendant fails to appear at trial after answering or joining issue, the court may render a default judgment.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>Burden of proof. The Tribe shall have the burden of satisfying or convincing to a reasonable certainty by the greater weight of credible evidence that the property is subject to forfeiture under <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>Action against other property of the person. The court may order the forfeiture of any other property of a defendant up to the value of property found by the court to be subject to forfeiture under <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1 if the property subject to forfeiture meets any of the following conditions.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Cannot be located.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Has been transferred or conveyed to, sold to or deposited with a third party.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Is beyond the jurisdiction of the court.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Has been substantially diminished in value while not in the actual physical custody of the law enforcement agency.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Has been commingled with other property that cannot be divided without difficulty.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container cache:ref-path="II|306|1|IV">
      <prefix>Article</prefix>
      <num>IV</num>
      <heading>Cleanup of Clandestine Drug Lab Sites</heading>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-33</num>
        <heading>Findings.</heading>
        <text>The Menominee Tribal Legislature finds that the manufacture of clandestine drugs, including but not limited to methamphetamine, on the Menominee Reservation is contrary to a safe and healthy way of life. The Legislature further finds that such drug manufacture can be extremely dangerous and endanger the health and welfare of residents of the Menominee Reservation.</text>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-34</num>
        <heading>Purpose.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Professional reports, based on assessments, testing, and investigations, show that chemicals used in the production of illicit drugs can condense, penetrate, and contaminate surfaces, furnishings, and equipment of structures and adversely impact the environment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>These conditions present health and safety risks to occupants and visitors of structures through fire, explosion, and skin and respiratory exposure to chemicals.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text><cite path="|II|306|1|IV">This article</cite> establishes responsibilities and guidelines for involved parties to assure the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>People are not unnecessarily exposed to the dangers of these contaminated structures; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Proper steps are taken to remove contaminants and assure appropriate tests are done to demonstrate that affected structures are sufficiently cleaned for human contact.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text><cite path="|II|306|1|IV">This article</cite> assists and guides appropriate authorities, property owners, and occupants to prevent injury and illness to members of the public, particularly children.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text><cite path="|II|306|1|IV">This article</cite> is intended to help assure reduction of people's exposure to chemicals associated with the site of a former clandestine drug lab operation at structures such as a dwelling, building, motor vehicle, trailer, or appliance.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-35</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text><cite path="|II|306|1|IV">This article</cite> shall apply to all lands within the external boundaries of the Menominee Indian Reservation and all lands later acquired and placed into trust for the Menominee Indian Tribe by the federal government.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Where a federal law or statute applies to the subject of <cite path="|II|306|1|IV">this article</cite> and is in conflict with <cite path="|II|306|1|IV">this article</cite>, that federal law shall apply to the extent of the conflicting part of <cite path="|II|306|1|IV">this article</cite> and to the extent that the statute applies to the actions of tribal government.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-36</num>
        <heading>Interpretation and application.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>The provisions of <cite path="|II|306|1|IV">this article</cite> shall be interpreted and applied as the minimum requirements necessary to protect public health, safety, and welfare.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Where the conditions imposed by any provision of <cite path="|II|306|1|IV">this article</cite> are either more restrictive or less restrictive than comparable provisions imposed by any other tribally applicable law, ordinance, statute, resolution, or regulation of any kind, the regulations which are more restrictive or which impose higher standards or requirements shall prevail.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-37</num>
        <heading>Disclaimer of liability.</heading>
        <text>Liability on the part of, or a cause of action against, the Menominee Indian Tribe or any employee thereof for any damages that may result from reliance on <cite path="|II|306|1|IV">this article</cite> shall be eliminated to the extent allowed by the Menominee Tribal Constitution.</text>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section cache:ref-path="II|§306-38">
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-38</num>
        <heading>Definitions.</heading>
        <text>For the purpose of <cite path="|II|306|1|IV">this article</cite>, the following terms or words shall be interpreted as follows:</text>
        <text>CHEMICAL INVESTIGATION SITE — A clandestine drug lab site that is under notice and order for cleanup and/or remediation as a public health nuisance, as authorized by the Menominee Indian Tribe and/ or <cite path="|II|306|1|IV">this article</cite>.</text>
        <text>CHILD — Any person less than 18 years of age.</text>
        <text>CLANDESTINE DRUG LAB GENERAL CLEANUP GUIDANCE (CDLGCG) — Clandestine Drub Lab</text>
        <text>General Cleanup Guidance standard operating procedure guide adopted by the Menominee Indian Tribe and attached hereto.<fn path="|II|§306-38|footnotes|3">3</fn></text>
        <text>CLANDESTINE DRUG LAB SITE — Any parts of a structure, such as a dwelling, building, motor vehicle, trailer, or appliance, occupied or affected by conditions and/or chemicals typically associated with a clandestine drug lab operation.</text>
        <text>CLEANUP — Proper removal and/or containment of substances hazardous to humans and/or the environment at a chemical investigation site. Cleanup is a part of remediation.</text>
        <text>CONTROLLED SUBSTANCE — See <cite path="§306-3">§ 306-3</cite> of <cite path="|II|306|1">this Part</cite> 1.</text>
        <text>OWNER — Any person, firm, or corporation who or which owns, in whole or in part, the land and/or structures, such as building, motor vehicle, trailer, boat or other appliance, at a clandestine drug lab site. In the case of federal trust real estate property, "owner" shall mean the beneficial owner of the property and not the legal title owner, unless otherwise stated.</text>
        <text>PUBLIC HEALTH AUTHORITY — The Menominee tribal department or departments designated by the Menominee Indian Tribe that are committed to protecting and improving the health of the residents of the Menominee Indian Reservation. Until such time that the Menominee Indian Tribe designates such a committee, the Public Health Authority shall be comprised of the Director of Environmental Services, the Director of Community Health Nursing Services and the Director of the Community Development Department.</text>
        <text>PUBLIC HEALTH NUISANCE — Any activity or failure to act that adversely affects the public health.</text>
        <text>REMEDIATION — Methods such as assessment, evaluation, testing, venting, detergent scrubbing, enclosure, encapsulation, demolition, and/or removal of contaminated materials from a chemical investigation site.</text>
        <text>STRUCTURE — A dwelling, building, motor vehicle, trailer, boat or other appliance.</text>
        <footnotes>
          <footnote>
            <num>3</num>
            <text>Editor's Note: A copy of the guide is on file at the office of the Administrative Manager.</text>
          </footnote>
        </footnotes>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-39</num>
        <heading>Administration.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Declaration of site as a chemical investigation site public health nuisance. Clandestine drug lab sites as defined above are declared by <cite path="|II|306|1|IV">this article</cite> to be chemical investigation site public health nuisances.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Medical protocol for assessing health status of exposed persons. A medical protocol for assessing the health status and determining medical care needs of persons, particularly children, that are found or known to be frequent visitors at a clandestine drug lab site shall be established by the Public Health Authority of the Menominee Indian Tribe as a standing order that may be updated as necessary.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-40</num>
        <heading>Notice of identification of clandestine drug lab site or operation.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Law enforcement authorities who identify a clandestine drug lab site or clandestine drug lab operation shall promptly notify the Public Health Authority, the Tribal Environmental Services Department and both tribal and county departments responsible for public health and child protection.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>The obligation to promptly notify may be delayed to accomplish appropriate law enforcement objectives, but only to the extent that public health and child protection responsibilities are not unnecessarily compromised.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>When law enforcement completes its work and is prepared to leave such sites, it shall leave a warning sign posted on the entrance of the affected part of the structure. The warning signs shall be those that have been prepared in advance for such situations through the collaboration of law enforcement and the Public Health Authority. The warning sign shall be of an adequate size and contain information sufficient to alert visitors or returning occupants to the site that the area is a chemical investigation site, may be dangerous to enter, and must not be entered except by authorization of the Public Health Authority and/or law enforcement agency identified on the sign.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>The notices referenced in <cite path="§306-40|C">Subsection C</cite> above shall include sufficient information to inform the recipients of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Property location by street address and other identifiable location;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Property owner's and occupant's identities, especially the identities of any children and women of childbearing age found or known to be associated with the site;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Chemicals found and indications of chemical residues;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Presumed duration of the lab;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Equipment in a dwelling or structure that is typically associated with the manufacture of a controlled substance; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Conditions typically associated with a clandestine drug lab site or operation, including weapons, illicit drugs, filth, fire, or electrical shock and other harmful conditions as determined by Menominee tribal law.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section cache:ref-path="II|§306-41">
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-41</num>
        <heading>Notice of chemical investigation site public health nuisance.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>After the Public Health Authority receives adequate information from law enforcement that it has identified a clandestine drug lab site and posted the appropriate "chemical investigation site public health nuisance" sign, the Public Health Authority shall act to contact the lawful occupants and owners of the site to also inform them of their responsibilities relative to the chemical investigation site public health nuisance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>The Public Health Authority shall notify and order the property owner and occupant to have the public health nuisance removed or abated as provided by Menominee tribal law, Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin Clandestine Drug Lab General Cleanup Guidance incorporated by reference as attached hereto.<fn path="|II|§306-41|footnotes|4">4</fn> and <cite path="|II|306|1|IV">this article</cite>. The Public Health Authority shall include the following as part of the notice and order:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>A replica of the chemical investigation site public health nuisance declaration that is posted at the site's entrance(s).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Information about the potentially hazardous condition of the dwelling.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>A summary of the property owner's and occupant's responsibilities under <cite path="|II|306|1|IV">this article</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Information that can help them locate appropriate services necessary to remove and resolve the chemical investigation site public health nuisance status as provided in <cite path="|II|306|1|IV">this article</cite> and Menominee tribal law.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>The Public Health Authority shall also provide information about the chemical investigation site public health nuisance declaration and potential hazard(s) to the following concerned parties:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Occupants of the affected structure.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Neighbors in proximity that can be reasonably affected by the conditions found.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The Tribal Chairperson.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The County Board Chairperson.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Local law enforcement.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Menominee Department of Social Services.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Menominee County Health and Human Services.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>Menominee Tribal Environmental Services Department.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>Menominee Community Development Department.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text>Community Health Nursing Services.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(11)</num>
            <text>Tribal Housing Department.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <footnotes>
          <footnote>
            <num>4</num>
            <text>Editor's Note: A copy of the guide is on file at the office of the Administrative Manager.</text>
          </footnote>
        </footnotes>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-42</num>
        <heading>Notice filed with property record and/or motor vehicle record.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>If, after 10 days' notice and order, the Public Health Authority is unable to obtain any reasonable assurance or plan from the property owner or occupant that the dwelling or structure is being properly vacated, cleaned, remediated, and tested, the Public Health Authority is authorized to provide a copy of the chemical investigation site public health nuisance notice and order to the County Recorder and to the lien and mortgage holders of the affected structure and/or properties. The County Recorder is authorized to file that information with the property record to help assure that persons with interest in the property have access to information about the property's chemical investigation site public health nuisance status.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Similarly, when the affected property is a motor vehicle, boat, or trailer, the Public Health Authority shall notify the appropriate state and local agency that maintains motor vehicle, boat, or trailer records and the lien and mortgage holders of the affected properties.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-43</num>
        <heading>Responsibility of property owners and occupants.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Property owner(s) and occupant(s) provided with a notice, which may include the posted warning notice informing them about the chemical investigation site public health nuisance, shall promptly act to vacate occupants from those parts of a structure that are a chemical investigation site public health nuisance. This includes dwellings, buildings, motor vehicles, trailers, boats, or appliances.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Within 10 business days of receiving the Public Health Authority notice and order to clean up the chemical investigation site public health nuisance, the property owner(s) and/or occupant(s) shall act to accomplish the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Notify the Public Health Authority that the affected parts of the dwellings, buildings, and/or motor vehicles have been and will remain vacated and secured until the Public Health Authority acts to remove the chemical hazard investigation public health nuisance declaration.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Contract with one or more acceptable environmental hazard testing and cleaning firms (acceptable firms are those that have provided the Menominee Indian Tribe, the Menominee Environmental Services Department or the Public Health Authority assurance of appropriate equipment, procedures, and personnel) to accomplish the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>Conduct a detailed on-site assessment;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>Determine the extent of contamination;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(c)</num>
              <text>Carry out and/or direct remediation operations;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(d)</num>
              <text>Perform and/or direct follow-up sampling and testing;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(e)</num>
              <text>Determine that the risks are sufficiently reduced, according to the Clandestine Drug Lab General Cleanup Guidance (CDLGCG), to allow renewed occupancy of the dwelling; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(f)</num>
              <text>Provide the Public Health Authority with the contractor's plan and schedule for remediation leading to removal of the chemical investigation site public health nuisance declaration.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>The property owner or occupant may also seek authorization for an extension of time to allow the owner time to consider options for arranging cleanup or removal of the affected parts of the structure. The owner or occupant must show good cause for any such extension. Any such extension shall be dependent on the owner's assurance that the affected parts of the structure will not be occupied pending appropriate cleanup or demolition.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>The Public Health Authority may authorize extensions up to 90 calendar days but will make extensions beyond 90 days only with approval of the Menominee Environmental Services Department.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-44</num>
        <heading>Property owner's responsibility for costs and opportunity for recovery.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>Pursuant to <cite path="|II|306|1|IV">this article</cite>, the property owner shall be responsible for private contractor's fees, cleanup, remediation, and testing of chemical investigation site public health nuisance conditions and the Menominee Tribe's fees and costs of administering notices and enforcing vacating, cleanup, remediation, and testing of affected parts of the property.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Nothing in <cite path="|II|306|1|IV">this article</cite> is intended to limit the property owner's, occupant's, or Tribe's right to recover costs, referenced in this section, from persons contributing to the damage, such as the operators of the clandestine drug lab and/or other lawful sources.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>The fees and costs, referenced above, include but are not limited to the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Posting the site;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Notification of concerned parties;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Remediation services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Expenses related to the recovery of costs, including the property assessment process;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Administrative fees; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Other services associated with assessing, vacating, and remediation of the property.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>When a property owner transfers remediation costs to the Tribe, the property owner agrees to provide the following to the Tribe: identity of all insurance companies that have policies regarding the property and pending court or contract enforcement actions that may result in recovery of remediation costs and proceeds from pending recovery actions, including but not limited to insurance companies, applicable court actions, and enforcement of contracts. As a precondition to any tribal obligation to make any payments hereunder, the property owner shall make legally sufficient assignment to the Tribe of any of the foregoing which are applicable.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>E.</num>
          <text>If there is still an unresolved cost, the Menominee Tribe shall apply for applicable tribal, state and federal funding to offset the cost of remediation and associated eligible tribal expenses.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Such funding may include that authorized by federal programs such as the Environmental Protection Agency's Local Government Reimbursement Program.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The Tribe shall return amounts that exceed the Tribe's applicable costs to the rightful parties.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>F.</num>
          <text>Expenses such as replacement of a structure's damaged furnishings, walls, floors, and ceilings and equipment, vehicles, boats, and trailers are not eligible for tribal funding referenced in <cite path="|II|306|1|IV">this article</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-45</num>
        <heading>Recovery of public costs.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>The Tribe is authorized to proceed, under this section, within 10 business days after mailing of notification, to initiate the assessment and cleanup when the property owner is not located, or is located but fails to respond appropriately, or notifies the Public Health Authority that he or she refuses to or cannot pay the costs or arrange timely assessment and cleanup that is acceptable to the designated Public Health Authority.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>The Menominee Administrative Manager (or the Manager's formally identified designee) shall be fully authorized to act, consistent with tribal law, on behalf of the Tribe to direct funds to assure prompt remediation of chemical investigation sites.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>When the estimated cost of testing, cleanup, and remediation exceeds 75% of the assessed market value of the structure in question, the Tribal Administrative Manager (or the Manager's formally identified designee) is authorized to notify the property owner of the Tribe's intent to remove and dispose of the affected property instead of proceeding with cleaning and remediation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>D.</num>
          <text>The property owner will be given up to 10 business days to appeal to the Tribal Administrative Manager (or the Manager's formally identified designee) and if appealed will be given the opportunity to show cause as to why such removal should not occur. The appeal is also the owner's opportunity to assume responsibility and provide acceptable plans and schedule for effective cleaning, remediation, and testing of the structure. If within 10 business days of the Administrative Manager's notice the owner fails to appropriately appeal or assume responsibility, the Administrative Manager is authorized to arrange removal and disposition of the hazardous structure.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>An appeal under this section shall be limited to a review by the Menominee Tribal Court.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The Court review of this matter shall be limited to the following: was the order against the law, was the order capricious, was the order unreasonable, and was the order the will of the Administrative Manager and not his judgment.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The property owner shall reimburse the Tribe for its fees and costs of vacating, securing, and assuring cleanup and testing of the affected parts of the structure.</text>
            <para>
              <num>(a)</num>
              <text>Fees and costs not paid in any other way may be collected through legal action commenced in Tribal Court or any other court of competent jurisdiction as allowed by applicable federal, state, and tribal laws and ordinances.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(b)</num>
              <text>The Tribe may also seek recovery of costs through other methods allowed by applicable tribal, federal and state law.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-46</num>
        <heading>Authority to modify or remove declaration of chemical investigation site public health nuisance.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>A.</num>
          <text>The designated Public Health Authority may modify conditions of the declaration and order removal of the declaration of chemical investigation site public health nuisance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>B.</num>
          <text>Such modification or removal shall be only after the Public Health Authority has determined levels of contamination are sufficiently reduced through remediation to warrant modification or removal of the declaration. The Public Health Authority may rely on information from competent sources, including those supplied by the property owner and/or others such as state and local health, safety, and pollution control authorities, to reach such decision.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>C.</num>
          <text>When the declaration is modified or removed the Public Health Authority shall forward that information to the County Recorder for addition to the property record if the Recorder has been notified as described above. Similarly, notice shall be provided to the motor vehicle or other license records agency and lien holders if a notice had previously been provided to them.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <prefix>§</prefix>
        <num>306-47</num>
        <heading>Waste generated from site.</heading>
        <text>Waste generated from chemical investigation site public health nuisances shall be treated, stored, transported, and disposed of in accordance with Menominee Indian Tribe and all applicable state, local and federal rules and regulations for solid waste and for hazardous household and other hazardous wastes, including <cite path="|II|361">Chapter 361</cite>, Article I, Hazardous Waste, of this Code.</text>
        <annotations/>
      </section>
    </container>
  </container>
</container>
