<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" cache:ref-path="II|325">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>325</num>
  <heading>FIRE PREVENTION</heading>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History">Adopted by the Legislature of the Menominee Indian Tribe 4-2-1981 by Ord. No. 81-9. Amendments noted where applicable</annotation>
  </annotations>
  <section>
    <prefix>§</prefix>
    <num>325-1</num>
    <heading>Outdoor burning restricted.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>Within the exterior boundaries of the Menominee Nation, it shall be unlawful for any person to set any fire unless such fire is attended at all times and the person has first obtained a burning permit on forms supplied by the Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources from a duly appointed and designated Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources forest ranger or fire warden, or other person designated by the Tribal Legislature, except: <strong>[Amended 7-12-1990]</strong></text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>When a fire is set and designed solely for warming the person or cooking food; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>When the ground is snow covered.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Any person who sets a fire solely for warming the person or cooking food shall extinguish such fire before leaving it and upon failure to do so will be in violation of <cite path="|II|325">this chapter</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>§</prefix>
    <num>325-2</num>
    <heading>Permit considerations.</heading>
    <text>Permits shall be issued under <cite path="|II|325">this chapter</cite> only after consideration of the following conditions and a determination by the authorized permit-issuing agent and the Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources that the danger to the resources will be minimized by allowing the permittee to burn if he or she complies with the conditions of the permit and takes all reasonable precautions to prevent the escape of the fire, such as: weather, fuels, day of the week, physical and mental capacity of the permittee, time of day, area to be burned, and the assistance available.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>§</prefix>
    <num>325-3</num>
    <heading>Permit restrictions.</heading>
    <text>Permits issued pursuant to <cite path="|II|325">this chapter</cite> shall include but not be limited to restrictions concerning: time of day, location, minimum required precautionary measures, and the length of the burning period of the permit.</text>
    <annotations>
      <annotation type="History">Amended 7-12-1990</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>§</prefix>
    <num>325-4</num>
    <heading>Special authority to restrict burning.</heading>
    <text><cite path="|II|325">This chapter</cite> includes the authority for the Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources, which the Tribe contracts with for fire protection, to restrict and forbid the setting of any type of fire or burning within the exterior boundaries of the Menominee Nation by any person, resident or nonresident, when there is a dangerously dry season. Setting of a fire or burning in <cite path="|II">this part</cite>icular section will include but will not be limited to the burning of trash or garbage, burning of leaves, campfires, charcoal grill fires, outside cooking units, etc. The only exception to <cite path="|II">this part</cite>icular section will be those homes where a stove or appliance is located inside the home which is needed in the preparation of food or for heat. The Menominee Tribal Legislature will be notified when this restriction goes into effect and proper notice will be given to the public by the following notification:</text>
    <para>
      <num>A.</num>
      <text>An announcement in the Shawano newspaper.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>B.</num>
      <text>Posting of signs at predesignated locations within the exterior boundaries of the Menominee Nation (list on file at the Keshena Ranger Station and the Menominee Tribal Offices).</text>
    </para>
    <annotations>
      <annotation type="History">Amended 7-12-1990</annotation>
    </annotations>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>§</prefix>
    <num>325-5</num>
    <heading>Negligent handling of materials which might cause forest fire; vehicles causing fire. [Added 7-12-1990]</heading>
    <text>Any person who would start, kindle or otherwise encourage a forest fire through careless use of smoking materials, fireworks, motorized equipment, flammable substances, or any other material or item of equipment shall be in violation of this section. Any person whose motorbike, motorcycle, automobile, van, truck, all-terrain vehicle or other vehicle is the cause of a fire shall be in violation of this section. The term "forest fire" as used in <cite path="|II|325">this chapter</cite> means uncontrolled, wild, or running fires occurring on forest, marsh, field, cutover or other lands or involving farm, tribal or village property and improvements incidental to the uncontrolled, wild or running fires occurring on forest, marsh, field, cutover or other lands within the exterior boundaries of the Menominee Indian Reservation.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <prefix>§</prefix>
    <num>325-6</num>
    <heading>Violations and penalties.</heading>
    <text>Any person found guilty of violating <cite path="|II|325">this chapter</cite> shall forfeit a minimum amount of not less than $25 nor in excess of $500 for the first violation, not less than $75 nor in excess of $500 for the second violation, not less than $225 nor in excess of $500 for the third violation, and $500 for each additional violation beyond three violations, plus, for each violation, suppression costs determined by the Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources.</text>
    <annotations/>
  </section>
</container>
