<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" cache:ref-path="II|361">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>361</num>
  <heading>HAZARDOUS MATERIALS</heading>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History">Adopted by the Legislature of the Menominee Indian Tribe as indicated in article histories. Amendments noted where applicable</annotation>
    <annotation type="General References">Fire prevention — See <cite path="|II|325">Ch. 325</cite>. Fireworks — See <cite path="|II|329">Ch. 329</cite>.</annotation>
    <annotation type="General References">Solid waste — See <cite path="|II|504">Ch. 504</cite>.</annotation>
  </annotations>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>I</num>
    <heading>Hazardous Waste</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-1</num>
      <heading>Ordinances on file.</heading>
      <text>Ordinance No. 87-27, Hazardous Waste Management Regulations, adopted February 4, 1988, as amended, and Ordinance No. 92-14, Hazardous Waste, adopted September 23, 1992, as amended September 16, 1994, and as it may be subsequently amended, are on file at the office of the Administrative Manager.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container cache:ref-path="II|361|II">
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>II</num>
    <heading>Hazardous Materials Transportation [Adopted 6-2-1994 by Ord. No. 94-03]</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-2</num>
      <heading>Authority.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>The Menominee Tribal Legislature adopts <cite path="|II|361|II">this article</cite> regarding hazardous materials transportation under the authority of the Menominee Constitution, Article III, and Bylaw II, § 2(i).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>The provisions of <cite path="|II|361|II">this article</cite>, effective May 19, 1994, are authorized under the Hazardous Materials Transportation Uniform Safety Act of 1990 (HMTUSA), Pub. L. No. 101-615, 104 Stat. 3245 (1990) (codified as amended at 49 U.S.C. § 5101 et seq.).</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-3</num>
      <heading>Purpose.</heading>
      <text>The purpose of <cite path="|II|361|II">this article</cite> is to provide a system to regulate the transportation of hazardous materials throughout the Menominee Indian Reservation in order to provide for the safe passage of hazardous materials in a manner which protects the environment, health and safety of all persons subject to the Tribe's jurisdiction.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-4</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>The following words and terms, when used in <cite path="|II|361|II">this article</cite>, have the following meanings, unless the context clearly indicates otherwise. Definitions set forth in this section supersede the definitions which may appear in Title 49 of the Code of Federal Regulations adopted by reference in <cite path="§361-6">§ 361-6</cite>.</text>
      <text>CHAIRPERSON — The Chairperson of the Legislature of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin.</text>
      <text>CONTAINER — Any portable device in which a hazardous material is stored, transported, treated or otherwise handled.</text>
      <text>CONTINGENCY PLAN — A document setting out an organized, planned, and coordinated course of action to be followed in case of a fire, explosion, or release of hazardous material constituents which could threaten human health or the environment.</text>
      <text>DEPARTMENT — The United States Department of Transportation (DOT).</text>
      <text>DISCHARGE or HAZARDOUS MATERIAL DISCHARGE — The accidental or intentional spilling, leaking, pumping, pouring, emitting, emptying, or dumping of hazardous material into or on any land or water.</text>
      <text>EMPTY CONTAINER — A container that has had its contents removed by purging or cleaning, or both.</text>
      <text>ENVIRONMENTAL SERVICES DEPARTMENT — The tribal agency that administers environmental codes and regulations.</text>
      <text>FEDERAL AGENCY — Any department, agency, or other instrumentality of the federal government, any independent agency or establishment of the federal government, including any government corporation, and the Government Printing Office.</text>
      <text>GROSS WEIGHT — The weight of a packaging, cargo tank, container or cylinder, plus the weight of its contents.</text>
      <text>HAZARDOUS MATERIAL — A substance or material, including a hazardous substance, which has been determined by the Secretary of Transportation to be capable of posing an unreasonable risk to health, safety, and property when transported in commerce and which has been so designated.</text>
      <text>HAZARDOUS SUBSTANCE — A hazardous material meeting the definition of a hazardous substance in 49 CFR 171.8.</text>
      <text>HAZARDOUS WASTE — A hazardous material meeting the definition of a hazardous waste in 49 CFR 171.8.</text>
      <text>HIGHWAY — A highway, street or other public way.</text>
      <text>MOTOR CARRIER — A common carrier by motor vehicle; a contract carrier by motor vehicle; a private carrier by motor vehicle; or a person who, as owner, lessee, or other possessor of one or more vehicles, directs or controls the transportation of hazardous material either for his or her own account or for hire.</text>
      <text>MOTOR VEHICLE — A vehicle, machine, tractor, trailer, semitrailer or a combination thereof propelled or drawn by mechanical power and used upon the highways in the transportation of hazardous material.</text>
      <text>NET WEIGHT — The net weight of the contents of a package, cargo tank, container or cylinder. The term does not include the weight of the packaging, cargo tank, container or cylinder.</text>
      <text>OUT OF SERVICE — The temporary or permanent prohibition of a vehicle or operator from further service because of one or more violations regarding the safety of either.</text>
      <text>PERSON — An individual, firm, copartnership, corporation, company, association, joint-stock association, including any trustee, receiver, assignee, or similar representative thereof, or government, Indian tribe, or agency or instrumentality of any government or Indian tribe when it offers hazardous materials for transportation in commerce or transports hazardous materials in furtherance of a commercial enterprise, but such term does not include:</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>The United States Postal Service; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Any agency or instrumentality of the federal government in accessing civil and criminal fines and injunctive relief set forth in <cite path="§361-8">§ 361-8</cite>.</text>
        <text>QUALIFIED TRIBAL EMPLOYEE — A Menominee tribal employee authorized by the Tribe to inspect vehicles, drivers, documents, equipment, loads or cargo.</text>
        <text>RESEARCH AND SPECIAL PROGRAMS ADMINISTRATION (RSPA) — The DOT agency that administers HMTUSA.</text>
        <text>RESERVATION — All land within the exterior boundaries of the Menominee Indian Reservation and other lands held in trust by the United States for the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin or any of its members.</text>
        <text>TRANSPORTATION — Any movement of property by any mode and loading or unloading. TRANSPORTER — A person engaged in transportation and storage incidental thereto.</text>
        <text>TRIBAL LEGISLATURE — The Legislature of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin. TRIBE — The Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§361-5">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-5</num>
      <heading>Immediate notice of certain hazardous materials incidents.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>At the earliest practicable moment, each carrier who transports hazardous materials (including hazardous wastes) shall give notice in accordance with <cite path="§361-5|B">Subsection B of this section</cite> after each incident that occurs during the course of transportation (including loading, unloading and temporary storage) in which:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>As a direct result of hazardous materials:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>A person is killed;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>A person receives injuries requiring his or her hospitalization;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Estimated carrier or other property damage exceeds $50,000;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>An evacuation of the general public occurs lasting one or more hours;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>One or more major transportation arteries or facilities are closed or shut down for one hour or more; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>The operational flight pattern or routine of an aircraft is altered;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Fire, breakage, spillage, or suspected radioactive contamination occurs involving shipment of radioactive material (see also 49 CFR 174.45, 175.45, 176.48, and 177.807);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Fire, breakage, spillage, or suspected contamination occurs involving shipment of etiologic agents; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>A situation exists of such a nature (e.g., a continuing danger to life exists at the scene of the incident) that, in the judgment of the Tribe or the carrier, it should be reported to the Environmental Services Department and DOT even though it does not meet the criteria of <cite path="§361-5|A|(1)">Subsection A(1)</cite>, (2) or (3) of this section.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Each notice required by <cite path="§361-5|A">Subsection A of this section</cite> shall be given, by telephone, to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Menominee Central: (715) 799-3881.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>United States Department of Transportation: 800-424-8802.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Wisconsin Division of Emergency Management: 800-943-0003.<fn path="|II|§361-5|footnotes|1">1</fn></text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Notice involving etiologic agents shall be given to the Centers for Disease Control, United States Public Health Service, Atlanta, Georgia (404) 633-5313, in place of the notice to the Department or (toll call) at (202) 267-2675. Each notice must include the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Name of reporter.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Name and address of carrier represented by reporter.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Phone number where reporter can be contacted.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Date, time, and location of incident.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>The extent of injuries, if any.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Classification, name, and quantity of hazardous materials involved, if such information is available.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Type of incident and nature of hazardous material involvement and whether a continuing danger to life exists at the scene.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Each carrier making a report under this section shall also make the report required by 49 CFR 171.16. A copy of the report should be filed with the Menominee Indian Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>1</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Amended at time of adoption of Code (see <cite path="|I|1|II">Ch. 1, General Provisions, Art. II</cite>).</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-6</num>
      <heading>Adoption of regulations by reference.</heading>
      <text>The Tribe incorporates by reference the following portions of Title 49 of the Code of Federal Regulations, but only as they exist as of the date of adoption of <cite path="|II|361|II">this article</cite> exclusive of future amendments:</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Oil Spill Prevention and Response Plans, 58 Fed. Reg. 33,304 (1993) (to be codified at 49 CFR 130). Any document of the response plan filed with the DOT must also be filed with the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Part 171, General Information, Regulations, and Definitions, exclusive of 49 CFR § 171.15.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Part 172, Hazardous Materials Table, Special Provisions, Hazardous Materials Communications Requirements, Emergency Response Information and Training Requirements.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Part 173, Shippers General Requirements for Shipments and Packagings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Part 174, Carriage by Rail.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>F.</num>
        <text>Part 175, Carriage by Aircraft.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>G.</num>
        <text>Part 176, Carriage by Vessel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>H.</num>
        <text>Part 177, Carriage by Public Highway.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>I.</num>
        <text>Part 178, Specifications for Packagings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>J.</num>
        <text>Part 179, Specifications for Tank Cars.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>K.</num>
        <text>Part 180, Continuing Qualification and Maintenance of Packagings.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-7</num>
      <heading>Supplemental rules and regulations.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Motor carrier registration. Motor carrier registration shall be completed as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>General. Motor carriers transporting hazardous materials in quantities requiring the vehicle to display placarding under 49 CFR 177 shall register with the Tribe each calendar year between January 1 and January 31.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Forms. Registration shall be made by each carrier on forms prescribed and furnished by the Tribe. Forms may be obtained upon request from the Menominee Indian Tribe, Environmental Services Department, P.O. Box 910, Keshena, WI 54135, or by calling (715) 799-3096.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Form 94-3-1, Certificate of Ownership or Control of Vehicles.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Form 94-3-2, Hazardous Materials Hauler Application.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Form 94-3-3, Application for Tank/Container Inspection.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Form 94-3-4, Carrier Profile Information.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Retention of form. The motor carrier shall maintain a copy of the forms noted in <cite path="§361-7|A|(2)">Subsection A(2)</cite> in its files for three years.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Fees. Annual registration fee for hazardous materials transporter applicants is $37.50. Annual registration fee for hazardous waste transporter applicants is $200. One-day trip permits are $20. Container inspection fees are $35. Tank inspection fees are $45. Power unit inspection fees are $25 (MIT 94-3-3). The Tribe will waive inspection fees when the carrier can demonstrate that the container, tank or power unit has successfully passed inspection in another jurisdiction within the last 12 months.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Towing of vehicles. No motor vehicle transporting hazardous materials in a quantity requiring the motor vehicle to display markings or placarding, as required by 49 CFR 171.1 and 171.2, may be towed on a highway except to remove the motor vehicle and cargo to the nearest place of safety, in the judgment of the carrier or its representative after consultation with police, fire or other emergency personnel. The motor vehicle may not be moved until the hazardous materials are stable unless failure to do so would constitute a threat to persons or property. For requirements regarding accidents involving specific types of hazardous materials, see 49 CFR 177.854 (relating to vehicles and shipments in transit; accidents).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Extended loads. No person may transport hazardous material on a vehicle when the load extends beyond the sides, front or rear of the cargo-carrying compartment of the vehicle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Unlawful transportation. No person may transport, by vehicle on a highway, hazardous material in a reckless manner or under conditions that will unreasonably endanger persons or property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>F.</num>
        <text>Weight limitations. Vehicles subject to <cite path="|II|361">this chapter</cite> shall comply with the weight limitations set forth by the United States DOT and the Environmental Services Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>G.</num>
        <text>Railroad crossings. A vehicle transporting hazardous material must stop at all railroad crossings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>H.</num>
        <text>Presentation of documents. A driver of a vehicle transporting a hazardous material on a highway shall present upon request to a qualified tribal employee all documents required by <cite path="|II|361|II">this article</cite> to be in his possession.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Amended 10-17-2013 by Ord. No. 13-39</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-8</num>
      <heading>Enforcement; violations and penalties.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Jurisdiction. Any enforcement procedures pursuant to <cite path="|II|361|II">this article</cite> will be conducted in Tribal Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Civil fine. Any person who is determined by the Tribe, after notice and opportunity for a hearing, to have knowingly committed an act which is a violation of a provision of <cite path="|II|361|II">this article</cite> shall be liable to the Tribe for a civil fine.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Fines and assessments. The Tribe provides the following fines and assessments:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Issuance of an order directing compliance with <cite path="|II|361|II">this article</cite>. The Tribal Court shall have jurisdiction to enforce such orders.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Minimum fine and maximum civil forfeiture.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Whoever knowingly commits an act which is a violation of any order or regulation applicable to any person who transports or causes to be transported or shipped hazardous materials shall be subject to the following fines:</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>A minimum fine of $250 per violation.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>A maximum civil forfeiture of $25,000 per violation, and if such violation is a continuing one, each day of violation constitutes a separate offense, per day (other than those relating to container manufacturing which are limited to a civil forfeiture of $25,000 per violation).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>In determining the amount of any such fine, the Tribe will consider seven criteria:</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>Nature and circumstance of violation.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>Extent and gravity of violation.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[3]</num>
              <text>Degree of respondent's culpability.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[4]</num>
              <text>Respondent's history of prior offenses.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[5]</num>
              <text>Respondent's ability to pay.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[6]</num>
              <text>Effect of penalty on respondent's ability to stay in business.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[7]</num>
              <text>Such other matters as justice may require (especially corrective actions).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Criminal penalties for willful violations of up to $5,000 or one year of imprisonment, or both.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Hearing. Formal administrative hearing on the record is not required by the Hazardous Materials Transportation Act (HMTA) but is available at the option of the alleged violator.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Acting knowingly. For purposes of this section, a person shall be considered to have acted knowingly if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Such a person has actual knowledge of the facts giving rise to the violation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A reasonable person acting in the circumstances and exercising due care would have such knowledge.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>F.</num>
        <text>Non-Indians. Non-Indians shall be subject to <cite path="|I|132">Chapter 132</cite>, Article V, Civil Remedial Forfeitures, of this Code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>G.</num>
        <text>Other actions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Tribal Attorney may bring an action in Tribal Court for equitable relief to redress a violation by any person of a provision of <cite path="|II|361|II">this article</cite>. The Tribal Court shall have jurisdiction to determine such actions and may grant such relief as is necessary or appropriate, including mandatory or prohibitive injunctive relief, interim, equitable relief and punitive damages.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>If the Tribe has reason to believe that an imminent hazard exists, it may petition the Tribal Court for an order suspending or restricting the transportation of the hazardous material responsible for such imminent hazard or for such other order as is necessary to eliminate or ameliorate such imminent hazard.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-9</num>
      <heading>Responsible party.</heading>
      <text>The owner or owners of the hazardous materials and the transporter or transporters of the hazardous materials shall be strictly liable, jointly and severally, for any injury resulting from transporting said hazardous materials through the Menominee Reservation or on tribal land wherever situated.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container cache:ref-path="II|361|III">
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>III</num>
    <heading>Resource Conservation and Recovery [Adopted 8-18-1994 by Ord. No. 94-12]</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-10</num>
      <heading>Purpose.</heading>
      <text>The purpose of <cite path="|II|361|III">this article</cite> is to establish special laws and procedures in addition to current tribal laws regarding the Menominee Tribe's partial authorization of the Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (hereinafter RCRA) authority pursuant to 40 CFR 270 et seq. The Menominee Indian Tribe is required to follow the below enacted rules as a condition of its partial RCRA authorization. These special laws supersede and are in addition to currently enacted tribal law.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§361-11">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-11</num>
      <heading>Applicability.</heading>
      <text>These rules apply only to matters concerning the implementation and enforcement of the Menominee Tribe's partial RCRA authorization through Menominee Tribal Ordinance No. 92-14.<fn path="|II|§361-11|footnotes|2">2</fn> The requirements of <cite path="|II|361|III">this article</cite> are in addition to the requirements of any other chapters and rules.</text>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>2</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: See Art. I of <cite path="|II|361">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-12</num>
      <heading>Rules and procedures.</heading>
      <text>The below rules and procedures shall, in addition to other tribal rules and procedures, apply to the Menominee Indian Tribe's implementation and enforcement of its partial RCRA authorization:</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>The Menominee Indian Tribe or its enforcement agency shall have the authority to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Restrain immediately by order or by suit in Tribal Court any person from engaging in any unauthorized activity which is endangering or causing damage to public health or the environment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Sue in courts of competent jurisdiction to enjoin any threatened or continuing violation of any program requirement, including permit conditions, without the necessity of a prior revocation of the permit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Assess or sue to recover in court civil penalties in at least the amount of $5,000 per day for any program violation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Obtain criminal penalties in at least the amount of $5,000 per day for each violation and imprisonment for at least six months against any person who knowingly transports any hazardous waste to an unpermitted facility; who treats, stores, or disposes of hazardous waste without a permit; or who makes any false statement or representation in any application, label, manifest, record, report, permit, or other document filed, maintained, or used for the purposes of RCRA program compliance.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>The Menominee Tribe or its enforcement agency shall provide for public participation in the tribal enforcement process by providing:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Assurances that the tribal agency or enforcement authority will:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Investigate and provide written response to all citizen complaints duly submitted;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Not oppose intervention by any citizen where permissive intervention may be authorized by statute, rule, or regulations; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Publish and provide at least 30 days for public comment on any proposed settlement of a tribal enforcement action.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-13</num>
      <heading>Information available to EPA.</heading>
      <text>The Menominee Indian Tribe or its enforcement agency shall provide authority for any information obtained or used in the administration of the tribal program to be available to the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) upon request without restriction.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§361-14">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-14</num>
      <heading>Exposure assessments.</heading>
      <text>The Menominee Indian Tribe shall allow assessment information be made available to the Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry [see the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation and Liability Act (CERCLA) § 104(i)].<fn path="|II|§361-14|footnotes|3">3</fn></text>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>3</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: See 42 U.S.C. § 9601 et seq.</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-15</num>
      <heading>Availability of information.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>All records shall be available to the public unless they are exempt from the disclosure requirements of the Federal Freedom of Information Act (FOIA), 5 U.S.C. § 552;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>All nonexempt records will be available to the public upon request regardless of whether any justification or need for such records has been shown by the requestor;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>The same types of records would be available to the public from the Tribe as would be available from EPA; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Information is provided to the public in substantially the same manner as EPA as indicated in 40 CFR Part 2.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-16</num>
      <heading>Protection of confidential information.</heading>
      <text>The Menominee Indian Tribe or its enforcement agency shall protect confidential business information (CBI) to the same degree as indicated in 40 CFR Part 2.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container cache:ref-path="II|361|IV">
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>IV</num>
    <heading>Storage Tanks for Flammable Liquids [Adopted 11-18-1999 by Ord. No. 99-27]</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-17</num>
      <heading>Adoption of Code by reference.</heading>
      <text>Pursuant to the authority vested by the Menominee Constitution, Article III, and Bylaw II, § 2(i), the Safe Storage, Installation, and Operation of Flammable and Combustible Liquids for Aboveground Storage Tanks and Underground Storage Tanks Code, attached hereto and incorporated herein, is enacted into Menominee law. This code is available for inspection at the office of the Tribal Chairperson of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin. The effective date of <cite path="|II|361|IV">this article</cite> shall be January 1, 2000.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container cache:ref-path="II|361|V">
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>V</num>
    <heading>Liquefied Petroleum Gases [Adopted 8-24-2000 by Ord. No. 00-08]</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-18</num>
      <heading>Authority.</heading>
      <text>The Menominee Tribal Legislature adopts <cite path="|II|361|V">this article</cite> regarding storage of liquefied petroleum gases under the authority of the Menominee Constitution, Article III, and Bylaw II, § 2(i).</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-19</num>
      <heading>Purpose.</heading>
      <text>The purpose of <cite path="|II|361|V">this article</cite> is to provide safe installation, operation, use, maintenance and transportation of liquefied petroleum gas equipment and systems to establish minimum safeguards to life, health and property by the adoption of reasonable and effective standards relating to liquefied gas systems.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-20</num>
      <heading>Applicability.</heading>
      <text>The rules of <cite path="|II|361|V">this article</cite> shall apply to the design, construction, location, installation, operation, repair and maintenance of equipment for the storage, handling and use of liquefied petroleum gases in dwellings, public buildings and places of employment. The rules shall also apply to the transportation of liquefied petroleum gases by tank truck or tank trailer, as well as Article II, Hazardous Materials Transportation, of <cite path="|II|361">this chapter</cite>, but not to railroads engaged in interstate commerce or to equipment used by them.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§361-21">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-21</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>The following words and terms, when used in <cite path="|II|361|V">this article</cite>, have the following meanings, unless the context clearly indicates otherwise:</text>
      <text>APPROVED — Acceptable to the Department. Note: The Department will ordinarily accept items approved by a nationally recognized testing laboratory.</text>
      <text>AUTHORITY HAVING JURISDICTION — The Tribe or its authorized deputies responsible for approving equipment, installations or procedures.</text>
      <text>CERTIFIED INSPECTOR — An individual who holds a valid credential as a certified boiler-pressure vessel inspector.</text>
      <text>CHAIRPERSON — The Chairperson of the Legislature of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin.</text>
      <text>CONTAINER — All vessels such as tanks, cylinders, bottles or drums used for transporting or storing of liquefied petroleum gases.</text>
      <text>DEPARTMENT — The Environmental Services Department of the Tribe that administers environmental codes and regulations.</text>
      <text>DWELLING UNIT — A structure, or part of a structure, which is used or intended to be used as a home, residence or sleeping place by one person or more persons maintaining a common household, to the exclusion of all others.</text>
      <text>GAS SYSTEM — A liquefied petroleum gas system.</text>
      <text>OUT OF SERVICE — The temporary or permanent prohibition of a liquefied gas system from further service because of one or more violations regarding the safety of the system.<fn path="|II|§361-21|footnotes|4">4</fn></text>
      <text>PERSON — An individual, firm, copartnership, corporation, company, association, joint-stock association, including any trustee, receiver, assignee, or similar representative thereof, or government, Indian tribe in furtherance of a commercial enterprise.</text>
      <text>PLACE OF EMPLOYMENT — Every place, whether indoors or out or underground, and the premises appurtenant thereto, where either temporarily or permanently any industry, trade or business is carried on or where any process or operation directly or indirectly related to any industry, trade or business is carried on and where any person is directly or indirectly employed by another for direct or indirect gain or profit, but does not include any place where persons are employed in private domestic service which does not involve the use of mechanical power or in farming.</text>
      <text>PRESSURE VESSEL — A container for the containment of pressure, either internal or external. This pressure may be obtained from an external source or by the application of heat from a direct or indirect source or any combination thereof.</text>
      <text>PUBLIC BUILDING — Any structure, including exterior parts of the building, such as a porch, exterior platform or steps providing means of ingress or egress, used in whole or in part as a place of resort, assemblage, lodging, trade, traffic, occupancy, or use by the public or by three or more tenants.</text>
      <text>QUALIFIED TRIBAL INSPECTOR — A person authorized by the Tribe (the Environmental Services Department) responsible for approving equipment, installations or procedures.</text>
      <text>RESERVATION — All land within the exterior boundaries of the Menominee Indian Reservation and other lands held in trust by the United States for the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin or any of its members.</text>
      <text>SECONDHAND VESSEL — A pressure vessel that has changed location subsequent to the original installation.</text>
      <text>TRIBAL LEGISLATURE — The Legislature of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin. TRIBE — The Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin.</text>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>4</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Amended at time of adoption of Code (see <cite path="|I|1|II">Ch. 1, General Provisions, Art. II</cite>).</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§361-22">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-22</num>
      <heading>Installation application form.</heading>
      <text>Every person, firm, association or corporation installing equipment using liquefied petroleum gas in containers of 125 gallons' or larger water capacity shall complete an installation application form found at Attachment "A" (MIT-1).<fn path="|II|§361-22|footnotes|5">5</fn> The installation application form shall be completed at the time of installation, shall be kept at the liquefied petroleum gas installation and shall be available for review by an authorized representative of the Department. For installations using containers of 1,000 gallons' or larger water capacity, a copy of the installation form shall be submitted to the Department 10 days prior to installation. Note: The liquefied petroleum gas installation application form is available from the Environmental Services Department at P.O. Box 670, Keshena, WI 54135 (715) 799-3096.</text>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>5</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Attachment "A" is available from the Environmental Services Department.</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§361-23">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-23</num>
      <heading>Approval required; application; plans and specifications.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Department approval. Department approval shall be obtained before commencing construction on any liquefied petroleum gas installation using containers of 1,000 gallons' or larger water capacity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Plans, specifications and information. Prior to approval, plans, specifications and information submitted to the Department for review and approval must contain the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>At least two sets of plans which are clear, legible and permanent copies, one set of specifications, fees and a completed application.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The name of the owner; the name of the person, firm or corporation proposing the construction or installation, if other than the owner; and the address of the facility, including the names of adjacent streets and highways.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>A plot plan, drawn to a minimum scale of one inch equals 20 feet, indicating the location of the facility or installation.<fn path="|II|§361-23|footnotes|6">6</fn></text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The location, size and capacity of each container.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>The type of container supports, clearances, type of venting and pressure relief used and combined capacity of all venting and relief valves on each container.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Plans for service stations involving the use of a key-, card- or code-operated dispensing unit shall indicate the location of emergency controls and shall include the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The location and details of the key-, card- or code-operated dispensing devices.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>A copy of the agreement between the key, card or code holder and the station owner.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>A copy of the program used to train those persons who will operate the key-, card- or code-operated dispensing devices.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Approval. Approval of plans is based upon compliance with the requirements of <cite path="|II|361|V">this article</cite>. Storage, handling and use of liquefied petroleum gases are subject to compliance with Article II, Hazardous Materials Transportation, of <cite path="|II|361">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Application for approval. Applications for approval of a liquefied petroleum tank installation shall be made in writing on form MIT-1. Note: See Attachment "A" for an example of form MIT-1.<fn path="|II|§361-23|footnotes|7">7</fn></text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Application processing time. The Department shall process all applications and shall approve, conditionally approve or deny the application in writing within 15 working days of receipt of the appropriate application and fee.</text>
      </para>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>6</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Amended at time of adoption of Code (see <cite path="|I|1|I">Ch. 1, General Provisions, Art. I</cite>).</text>
        </footnote>
        <footnote>
          <num>7</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Attachment "A" is available from the Environmental Services Department.</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-24</num>
      <heading>Revocation of approval.</heading>
      <text>The Department may revoke any approval issued under the provisions of <cite path="|II|361|V">this article</cite> for any false statements or misrepresentations of facts upon which the approval was based.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-25</num>
      <heading>Expiration of approval.</heading>
      <text>Plan approval by the Department shall expire one year after the date indicated on the approved plans if construction has not commenced within that year.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-26</num>
      <heading>Enforcement and inspections.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Enforcement. The rules in <cite path="|II|361|V">this article</cite> shall be enforced by the Department, any authorized agent or employee of the Department, and/or the Menominee Tribal Police Department. The Department shall refer all violations of <cite path="|II|361|V">this article</cite> to the Menominee Tribal Prosecutor, who shall prosecute all such violations of <cite path="|II|361|V">this article</cite>. The Court, upon conviction, shall assess the penalties provided in <cite path="§361-29">§ 361-29</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Inspections. Inspections shall be conducted during or after construction or installation by an authorized representative of the Department to ascertain whether or not the construction or installation conforms to the conditionally approved plans, the conditional approval letter, and the provisions of <cite path="|II|361|V">this article</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-27</num>
      <heading>Fees.</heading>
      <text>Fees shall be submitted to the Department as outlined in the installation application (MIT-1), Section 5. Fees must be submitted at the time the application for approval is submitted. No plan examinations, approvals or inspections may be made until the fees are received.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§361-28">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-28</num>
      <heading>Petition for variance.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Procedure. The Department shall consider and may grant a variance to <cite path="|II|361|V">this article</cite> upon receipt of a fee, a completed petition for variance form from the owner and a position statement from the fire department having responsibility, provided that an equivalency is established in the petition for the variance which meets the intent of the rule being petitioned. The Department may impose specific conditions in a petition for variance to promote the protection of the health, safety or welfare of the employees or the public. Violation of those conditions under which the petition is granted shall constitute a violation of <cite path="|II|361|V">this article</cite>. Note: See Attachment "B" for an example of a petition for variance application (MIT-2).<fn path="|II|§361-28|footnotes|8">8</fn></text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Petition processing time. Except for priority petitions, the Department shall review and make a determination on a petition for variance within 30 business days of receipt of all calculations, documents and fees required to complete the review.</text>
      </para>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>8</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Attachment "B," the petition for variance application, is available from the Environmental Services Department.</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§361-29">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-29</num>
      <heading>Violations and penalties.<fn proof="needed" path="|II|§361-29|footnotes|9">9</fn></heading>
      <text>Any person, firm, association or corporation who or which violates any standard, rule or regulation adopted by the Tribe or issues a false installation statement will be fined not less than $25 nor more than $100 and/ or imprisoned not less than 30 days nor more than six months.</text>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>9</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Amended at time of adoption of Code (see <cite path="|I|1|II">Ch. 1, General Provisions, Art. II</cite>).</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-30</num>
      <heading>Adoption of standards by reference.</heading>
      <text>The Tribe adopts and incorporates by reference into <cite path="|II|361|V">this article</cite> the liquefied petroleum gas standards listed below. Note: Copies of <cite path="|II|361|V">this article</cite> and including listed standards are on file in the Chairperson's and Department's offices.</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>American Petroleum Institute, 1220 L Street Northwest, Washington DC 20005. Design and Construction of Liquefied Petroleum Gas Installations, API Standard 2510, 7th Edition, May 1995.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>National Fire Protection Association, 11 Tracy Drive, Avon, MA 02322-9908. National Fuel Gas Code, NFPA No. 54-1996; Liquefied Petroleum Gas Code, NFPA No. 58-1998; Recreational Vehicles, NFPA No. 1192-1999, <cite>Chapter 2</cite>, Fuel Systems and Equipment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>National Fire Protection Association, 11 Tracy Drive, Avon, MA 02322-9908. Compressed Natural Gas Vehicular Fuel Systems, NFPA No. 52-1998.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-31</num>
      <heading>Amendments to NFPA standards.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Location of containers. The following are Department rules in addition to the requirements in NFPA No. 58, <cite path="§3-2">Section 3-2</cite>.2.2:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The setbacks for aboveground containers specified in Table 3-2.2.2 of NFPA No. 58 may be reduced to a minimum of 15 feet if a four-hour fire-rated wall is placed between the container and the building or property line that may be built upon. The fifteen-foot distance shall be measured from the side of the fire wall away from the tank to the building or property line.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Fire walls used for setback reduction shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Extend laterally three feet beyond the container and three feet above the container.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Be placed at lease 10 feet from the container.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Allow the fire department access to the building and the container.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Be constructed on no more than two sides of the container.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>The setback reduction allowed in <cite path="§361-31|A|(1)">Subsection A(1)</cite> applies to containers of 1,201 to 50,000 gallons' water capacity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Containers to be filled. Substitute the following wording for NFPA No. 58, <cite path="§4-2">Section 4-2</cite>.2.1: "Containers shall be filled only by the owner or upon the owner's authorization."</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-32</num>
      <heading>Liquefied petroleum gas facilities.</heading>
      <text>All liquefied petroleum gas facilities shall be constructed, installed, operated and maintained as specified in the standards listed in <cite path="§361-30">§ 361-30</cite>.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-33</num>
      <heading>Self-service to vehicle fuel tanks and recreational equipment.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>General. No person, except the following, may dispense any liquefied gases unless the dispensing is through approved liquefied petroleum gas dispensing devices or devices pending approval:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Trained authorized employee of a bulk storage plant, container charging plant or service station.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Trained authorized motor vehicle fleet employees.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Location of key-, card- or code-operated dispensing systems.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Attended locations. Liquefied petroleum fueling facilities may be located in areas accessible or open to the general public, provided that the facility is equipped with key-, card- or code-operated dispensing devices listed or approved by a nationally recognized testing laboratory and an attendant is on duty at all times when liquefied petroleum gas is being dispensed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Nonattended locations. Dispensing of liquefied petroleum gas may be permitted without an attendant, provided that the dispensing facility is not freely accessible or open to the general public and the facility is equipped with approved key-, card- or code-operated dispensing devices.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Posting of signs. A permanent sign providing an emergency twenty-four-hour service call telephone number in letters at least one inch high shall be posted at the dispensing device in all nonattended locations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Public self-service prohibited. Self-service of liquefied gas by the general public shall be prohibited.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-34</num>
      <heading>Fuel supply tanks for liquefied petroleum cargo tank trucks.</heading>
      <text>Every motor vehicle operated by liquefied petroleum gas fuel shall be equipped with a liquefied petroleum gas fuel supply tank separate from and in no way connected to any liquefied petroleum cargo tank on or attached to the motor vehicle.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>361-35</num>
      <heading>Secondhand pressure vessels.</heading>
      <text>The use of secondhand pressure vessels, having a water capacity in excess of 1,000 gallons, and intended for liquefied petroleum gas service, shall be prohibited, unless the following conditions are satisfied:</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Manufacturer's data report. The original manufacturer's report is available. If the original manufacturer's report is unavailable, documentation acceptable to the Department shall be submitted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Alterations and repairs by welding. All alterations and repairs by welding are documented in writing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Other requirements. An inspection of the pressure vessel has been performed at its new location by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
