<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" cache:ref-path="II|512">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>512</num>
  <heading>SURFACE WATER</heading>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="History">Adopted by the Legislature of the Menominee Indian Tribe 11-22-2004 by Ord. No. 04-22. Amendments noted where applicable</annotation>
    <annotation type="General References">Conservation Code — See <cite path="|II|287">Ch. 287</cite>.</annotation>
    <annotation type="General References">Cultural Resource Management Plan — See <cite path="|II|293">Ch. 293</cite>. Forest management and development — See <cite path="|II|340">Ch. 340</cite>. Gravel, sand and fill removal — See <cite path="|II|354">Ch. 354</cite>.</annotation>
    <annotation type="General References">Hazardous materials — See <cite path="|II|361">Ch. 361</cite>. Mining — See <cite path="|II|415">Ch. 415</cite>.</annotation>
    <annotation type="General References">Sewers and sewage disposal — See <cite path="|II|495">Ch. 495</cite>. Water — See <cite path="|II|562">Ch. 562</cite>.</annotation>
  </annotations>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>I</num>
    <heading>General Provisions</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-1</num>
      <heading>Purpose.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text><cite path="|II|512">This chapter</cite> governs water management decisions and activities that affect waters of the Reservation. All waters of the Reservation are designated outstanding Menominee resource waters (OMRW) or outstanding national resource waters (ONRW). All activities that affect water quality, water quantity, and uses of waters of the Reservation shall be regulated by the Tribe. <cite path="|II|512">This chapter</cite> prohibits unauthorized discharges of substances to waters and wetlands of the Menominee Indian Reservation and regulates water quality, water quantity, and activities that affect water quality, water quantity, and uses of waters of the Reservation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Water quality standards shall serve as basic precepts for the protection of water quality. In all cases where potential uses and criteria are in conflict, water quality standards shall protect the general interest of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Minimum water requirements to sustain the beauty (aesthetics) and stability of the biological, physical, and chemical integrity of waters of the Reservation shall be met at all times. Regulations herein set forth are intended to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Acknowledge and establish general policies for the protection and maintenance of the quality of surface waters and wetlands within the Menominee Reservation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Identify, to the extent possible, existing uses of waters of the Reservation and to provide a mechanism to allow the designation of uses of such water resources;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Establish minimum criteria for protecting and maintaining water quality and to achieve the water quality goals identified herein;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Establish an antidegradation policy and implementation methods necessary to assure the maintenance and protection of water quality;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Establish procedures for the ongoing review and revision of the standards;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Establish procedures for application, consideration, issuance, condition, or denial of permits for discharges to surface waters and wetlands of the Reservation consistent with Sections 401, 402 and 404 of the Clean Water Act;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Establish enforcement measures and penalties for noncompliance with the standards;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>Identify methods to implement, achieve, and maintain desired water quality required to achieve these goals;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(9)</num>
          <text>For substances detected in waters of the Reservation, establish criteria for the protection of existing and designated uses of Reservation waters and wetlands to assure the continuation of such uses for the future generations of the Tribe;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(10)</num>
          <text>Establish water quality standards and an antidegradation policy meeting provisions of 40 CFR Parts 131 and 132 to provide protection of waters of the Reservation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(11)</num>
          <text>Establish special unique protection measures for OMRWs and ONRWs.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Water quality standards shall serve as a basis for developing and implementing control strategies that protect the water quality interests and existing and designated uses of the Tribe, including but not limited to the protection of public health and welfare, traditional and contemporary cultural, ceremonial, spiritual, and religious practices and prospective uses of all waters of the Reservation for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Tribal water supplies;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Propagation of fish and other aquatic life and wild and domestic animals and associated consumptive and nonconsumptive uses;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Wildlife habitat and natural food chain maintenance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Harvest of plants and animals for human consumption, e.g., wild rice and sturgeon and other life forms associated with aquatic and riparian habitats;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Domestic and recreational purposes; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Agricultural, silvicultural (tribal sustained-yield forestry practices), aquacultural, commercial, industrial, navigational, and other uses.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-2</num>
      <heading>Applicability.</heading>
      <text><cite path="|II|512">This chapter</cite> applies to all surface waters and wetlands located within the exterior boundaries of the Menominee Reservation and to all facilities, practices and activities which may affect the quality and flow requirements desirable to achieve the water quality goals stated herein for waters of the Reservation. Additionally <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> applies to waters within the tract of land owned by the Tribe named "Middle Village"; the legal description for this property can be found at the Tribal Community Development Department, P.O. Box 910, Keshena, WI 54135.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§512-3">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-3</num>
      <heading>Procedure for review and revision of water quality standards.</heading>
      <text>The Tribe may promulgate new rules or amend rules governing facilities, practices or activities if the Tribe determines that the amendment or promulgation of such rules is necessary to protect waters of the Reservation, aquatic life, public health, safety or welfare, and designated and existing uses and to achieve the goals of these standards. The Tribe shall review and, if appropriate, revise the water quality regulations at any time, or at least on a triennial basis, and hold public hearings for the purpose of reviewing and revising applicable water quality standards. The requirements of <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> are in addition to the requirements of any other chapters, rules, and ordinances established by the Tribe.</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Public participation time line for review or revision of water quality standards.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Public notification. The Department will provide no less than 30 days' notice to the public in advance of agency action to permit time for public response.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Public consultations. This includes but is not limited to public hearings, public meetings, and advisory groups. The Department will provide a timely distribution of information sufficiently in advance of decisionmaking to assimilate the public views on the Department's action.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Public hearings. Notice of public hearings, whether mandatory or discretionary, shall be publicized and mailed to interested and affected parties at least 45 days prior to the date of the hearing.</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>However, where the Department determines that there are no substantial documents that must be reviewed for effective hearing participation and that there are no complex or controversial matters to be addressed by the hearing, the notice requirement may be reduced to no less than 30 days.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>The Department may further reduce or waive the hearing notice requirement in emergency situations where the Department or Legislature determines that there is an imminent danger to public health.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[3]</num>
              <text>Reports, documents and data relevant to the discussion at the public hearing shall be available to the public at least 30 days before the hearing. Materials relevant to the hearing that will further assist public participation may be made available earlier.<fn path="|II|§512-3|footnotes|1">1</fn></text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Public meetings. Public meetings are any assemblies or gatherings (such as conferences, informational sessions, seminars, workshops, or other activities) which the Department intends to be open to anyone wishing to attend. The requirements of <cite path="§512-3|A|(2)">Subsection A(2)</cite> are applicable to public meetings, except that the Department may reduce notification of public meetings to no less than 30 days, if there is good reason that longer notice cannot be provided.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Responsiveness summaries. The Department shall prepare responsiveness summaries at specific decision points in program regulations or in the approved public participation work plan. Responsiveness summaries are also required for rule-making activities. Each responsiveness summary shall identify the public participation activity conducted; describe the matters on which the public was consulted; summarize the public's views, significant comments, criticisms and suggestions; and set forth the Department's specific responses in terms of modifications of the proposed action or an explanation for rejection of proposals made by the public. Responsiveness summaries shall also include evaluations by the Department of the effectiveness of the public participation program and evaluations from any advisory group and provide an opportunity for other participating members of the public to contribute to the evaluation. (In the case of programs with multiple responsiveness summary requirements, these analyses need only be prepared and submitted with the final summary required.) Lastly, responsiveness summaries shall be forwarded to the appropriate decisionmaking official and shall be made available to the public.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Notice of intention to adopt rules and opportunity to submit data. Any proposed changes or revisions to these standards shall be preceded by a public notice posted at the Neopit and the Keshena post offices, County Courthouse and Tribal Office Building; additionally, all requirements of <cite path="|I|177">Chapter 177</cite>, Posting Procedures, of this Code shall be met, and a copy of the notice shall be mailed to all persons who have made timely request to the committee or the Department for information regarding the proposed rule-making proceedings.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Such notice shall include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Reference to the authority under which the rule is proposed;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>A statement of either the terms or substance of the proposed rule or a description of the subjects and issues involved; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The time, place, and manner in which interested persons may present their views thereon.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>All interested persons should be given a reasonable opportunity to submit data, views, or arguments in writing. Opportunity for a public hearing may be granted if requested in a timely manner and determined by the Legislature to be in the public interest. The Legislature shall fully consider all oral comments and written submissions prior to making its final determination.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>No regulatory proceedings shall be held on any final rule until 20 days have passed from the posting date in which notice is given of the adoption of said rule by the Tribal Legislature. This regulatory proceeding is in accordance with the Constitution and Bylaws of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin, Bylaw II, Section 2(d).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>No rule hereafter adopted is valid unless adopted in substantial compliance with this section or, if an emergency rule designated as such, adopted in compliance with <cite path="§512-3|C">Subsection C</cite>. In any proceeding, a rule cannot be contested on the grounds of noncompliance with the procedural requirements of this section, as now or hereafter amended, after one year has elapsed from the effective date of the rule.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Emergency rules and amendments. If a committee or the Department recommends, and the Tribal Legislature so finds, that immediate adoption or amendment of a rule is necessary for the preservation of the public health, safety, or general welfare of the Reservation population, and that observance of the requirements of notice and opportunity to present views on the proposed action would be contrary to the public interest, the Legislature may dispense with such requirements and immediately adopt the rule or amendment as an emergency rule or amendment. The Legislature finding and a brief statement of the reasons for its finding shall be incorporated in the emergency rule or amendment. An emergency rule or amendment shall not remain in effect for longer than 60 days after adoption. This regulatory proceeding is in accordance with the Constitution and Bylaws of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin, Bylaw II, Section 2(g).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Rules filed with the Chairperson and public inspection.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Legislature shall file with the Chairperson, the presiding officer of the Tribal Legislature, a true copy of all rules now in effect and being implemented. The Chairperson shall keep a permanent register of such rules and all rules subsequently adopted by the Legislature. This permanent register shall be open to public inspection during normal business hours.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Emergency rules shall become effective upon their adoption by the Legislature. All other rules hereafter shall become effective upon the expiration of 20 days following their publication, unless a later date is required by applicable law or specified in the rule.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Statement of purpose of rules and how implemented.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>When a committee or the Department proposes that the Legislature take action to adopt a rule, the sponsoring committee shall ensure that the proposed rule is accompanied by a statement which generally describes the purpose of the proposed rule and how to implement it. Such statements shall contain, but not be limited to, the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>A title, a description of the rule's purpose, the name of the sponsoring committee, the legal authority, and any other information which may be of assistance in identifying the proposed rule or its purpose.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>A summary of the proposed rule.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The Department personnel who are responsible for drafting the proposed rule and who will be responsible for implementation and enforcement of the proposed rule.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Upon filing the proposed rule with the Chairperson, the sponsoring committee shall have copies of all statements on file and available for public inspection.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Petition for adoption, amendment, or repeal of rules. Any interested person may petition a committee and request that such committee propose that the Legislature promulgate, amend, or repeal any rule. With in 60 days after the submission of the petition, or at the next regular meeting of the committee if it does not meet within this sixty-day period, the committee shall formally consider the petition and within 30 days thereafter shall either deny the petition in writing (stating the reason for the denial) or initiate rule-making proceedings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>F.</num>
        <text>Certification. The Tribe may issue certifications pursuant to the requirements of Section 401 of the Clean Water Act. Revisions adopted by the Tribe shall be applicable for use in issuing tribal water certifications.</text>
      </para>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>1</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Amended at time of adoption of Code (see <cite path="|I|1|II">Ch. 1, General Provisions, Art. II</cite>).</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§512-4">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-4</num>
      <heading>Authority.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>The water quality standards program administered by the Menominee Tribe pertains to the management and protection of water resources which are within the borders of the Menominee Reservation and held by the Menominee Tribe, within the borders of the Menominee Indian Reservation and held by the United States in trust for the Menominee Tribe, within the Menominee Indian Reservation and held by a member of the Menominee Tribe if such property interest is subject to a trust restriction or alienation, or otherwise within the borders of the Menominee Indian Reservation and land which may be added to the Reservation under any law of the United States.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>These rules under <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> shall be governed by Article I (Jurisdiction) of the Constitution and Bylaws of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin, whereby the governmental powers of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin, a federally recognized sovereign Indian tribe, shall, consistent with applicable federal law, extend to all persons and subjects and to all lands and other property, including natural resources listed in <cite path="§512-4|A">Subsection A</cite> above. The governmental powers of the Tribe shall, consistent with applicable federal law, also extend outside the exterior boundaries of the Reservation to any persons, subjects, facilities, industries, farmers, municipalities, utilities, or mining operations or real property which is, or may hereafter be, included within the jurisdiction of the Tribe under any law of the Tribe and the United States. Any person who violates any regulation or law set forth under <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> shall be prosecuted under tribal law, whereby, under Article III, Section 2 of the Tribal Constitution and Bylaws (Powers of the Tribal Judiciary), the Tribal Judiciary shall be vested with all judicial powers of the Tribe, including the power to decide cases in which a person is accused by the Tribe of committing an offense against the laws of the Tribe. The powers granted to the judiciary by <cite path="§512-4|B.">this subsection</cite> shall include judicial powers restored or granted the Tribe by any law of the United States or other competent authority. In the absence of tribal law on point, the laws and courts of the United States shall apply.<fn path="|II|§512-4|footnotes|2">2</fn></text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>The Menominee Tribal Water Quality Standards are intended to fulfill the minimum requirements of the Clean Water Act (33 U.S.C. § 1342) and its implementing regulations, as amended.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Repealing effect; abrogation and greater restrictions. Ordinance No. 87-29, its amendments and motions thereto pertaining are hereby repealed and replaced by <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite>. Where <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> imposes greater restrictions than those contained in other ordinances, the provisions of <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> shall govern.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>The Tribe reserves the right to amend or repeal any or all parts of <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> at any time. All the rights, privileges, or immunities conferred by <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> or by acts done pursuant thereto shall exist subject to the power of the Tribe. Nothing in <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> shall be construed to constitute a waiver of the sovereign immunity of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin or a consent to jurisdiction by any forum not expressly authorized to exercise jurisdiction under <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite>. The water quality standards established under <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> are not intended to control, and shall not be invalidated by, natural background phenomena or acts of God.</text>
      </para>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>2</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Amended at time of adoption of Code (see <cite path="|I|1|II">Ch. 1, General Provisions, Art. II</cite>).</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§512-5">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-5</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>As used in <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite>, the following terms shall have the meanings indicated: ACUTE TOXICITY —</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>The ability of a substance to cause poisonous effects that result in severe biological harm or death soon after a single exposure or dose.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>A relatively short-term lethal or other adverse effect to a test organism, that is a representative sensitive organism, caused by pollutants with a duration of exposure generally less than four days for fish and large invertebrates and shorter times for smaller organisms.</text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>ANTHROPOGENIC — Caused by or related to, either directly or indirectly, human actions. ANTIDEGRADATION — See Article VI of this chapter.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>AQUATIC LIFE — Animal and plant or other life that resides in water at some stage in life history.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>BACKGROUND CONDITIONS — The biological, chemical, and physical conditions of a water body upstream from a point or nonpoint source of pollution under consideration. Background sampling location(s) in an enforcement action will be upstream from the point of discharge but not upstream from other discharges and inflows. If several discharges to any water body exist and an enforcement action is being taken for possible violations of standards, background sampling will be undertaken immediately upstream from each discharge.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>BEST MANAGEMENT PRACTICES (BMPs) — Schedules of activities, prohibitions or practices, maintenance procedures, and other management activities or engineered structures, or combinations of these, to prevent or reduce pollution to waters of the Reservation. Best management practices also include treatment requirements, operating procedures, and practices to control plant site runoff, spillage or leaks, sludge or waste disposal, or drainage from raw material storage.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>BIOACCUMULATION —</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>The process whereby substances increase in concentration in living organisms, that are very slowly metabolized or excreted, as the organism breathes contaminated air or water, drinks contaminated water, or eats contaminated food.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>The process of a chemical accumulating in a biological food chain by being passed from one organism to another as the contaminated organism is preyed upon by another organism.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>The process whereby a substance or substances increase(s) in concentration in organisms relative to the ambient water concentration(s).</text>
        <text>BIOASSAY —</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>A toxicity test using selected organisms to determine the acute or chronic effects of a chemical pollutant or whole effluent.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>An evaluation using organisms to measure the effect of a substance, factor, or condition by comparing before and after data.</text>
        <text>BIOCONCENTRATION — A process by which there is a net accumulation of a chemical directly from water into aquatic organisms.</text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>BIOTIC INTEGRITY — A measure of the overall health of an ecosystem. CEREMONIAL, RELIGIOUS AND SPIRITUAL USE — See Article II of this chapter.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>CHRONIC TOXICITY — The capacity of a substance to cause long-term poisonous effects in an organism after long-term exposure.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>COMPLIANCE ORDER — A legal document signed by the Tribe directing a person, business, or other party to take corrective action(s) or refrain from an activity and fulfill certain directives. The order describes the violations and actions to be taken and can be enforced in court. Such orders may be issued and the respondent may be ordered to pay a penalty for violations in addition to corrective action.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>CONTAMINANT — A chemical or biological substance in a form that can be incorporated into or onto or be ingested by and that harms aquatic organisms, consumers of aquatic organisms, or users of the aquatic environment.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>CONTROL DOCUMENT — See "permit."</aftertext>
      <aftertext>CULTURAL USE — See Article II of this chapter.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>DEGRADATION — Lowering of the existing quality of waters of the Reservation, including but not limited to the chemical, physical, and biological characteristics and values associated with waters of the Reservation. Undesirable changes in the beds and banks of waters of the Reservation, including but not limited to objectionable deposits and changes in shoreland and wetland vegetation, local ecology, bank stability, and local hydraulics shall constitute degradation.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>DEPARTMENT — The Environmental Services Department of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin or other department designated by the Tribal Legislature as responsible for implementation of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin Water Quality Standards.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>DESIGNATED USE — Use(s) of the waters of the Reservation that is designated herein; see Article II.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>DESIGN LOW FLOW — The design low flows must be used unless data exists to demonstrate that an alternative low flow design is appropriate for water bodies and pollutant-specific conditions [40 CFR Part 132, Appendix F, Procedure 3, Sec. (E)(1)]. See "low flow."</aftertext>
      <aftertext>DIRECTOR — The Director of the Environmental Services Department of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin or other department designated by the Tribal Legislature as responsible for implementation of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin Water Quality Standards.<fn path="|II|§512-5|footnotes|3">3</fn></aftertext>
      <aftertext>DISCHARGE — When used without qualification means the discharge of a pollutant.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>DISCHARGE OF A POLLUTANT — Any addition of any pollutant or combination of pollutants to waters of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin from any point source. This definition includes additions of pollutants into waters of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin from surface runoff which is collected or channelled by man; discharges through pipes, sewers, or other conveyances owned by a state, municipality, or other person which do not lead to a treatment works; and discharges through pipes, sewers, or other conveyances leading into privately owned treatment works.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>DISCHARGER(S) — Person(s) who engages in activities resulting in discharge to tribal waters.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>DISEASE — Alteration of the state of a plant or animal body, or some of its organs, which interrupts or disturbs the proper performance of the bodily function, including but not limited to pathogenic effects; diseases include chronic, acute, and subclinical types, as well as indirect changes, e.g., changes to reproductivity, behavior, and susceptibility, and direct mortality.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>DRAINAGE BASIN — A water body and the land area drained by it.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>ECOSYSTEM — The interacting system of a biological community and its (biotic and abiotic) environmental surroundings.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>EFFLUENT — Wastewater, treated or untreated, that flows from a discrete point of discharge.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>EFFLUENT LIMITATION(S) — Any restriction imposed by the Tribe, EPA, and/or other federal entity on quantities, discharge rates, and concentrations of pollutants which are discharged from point sources into water.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>ENFORCEMENT ACTION — Any action taken by the Tribe, including the Tribal Environmental Services Department, Tribal Department of Conservation, and Tribal Police Department, and/or EPA to force compliance with this chapter, including but not limited to monetary penalties.<fn path="|II|§512-5|footnotes|4">4</fn></aftertext>
      <aftertext>ENTITY — An individual, firm, corporation, association, partnership, consortium, joint venture, commercial entity, company, industry, or mining operation, the United States government, a state, municipality, commission, political subdivision of a state, Indian tribe, or any interstate body, or an agent or employee thereof.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>EPA — The United States Environmental Protection Agency.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>EROSION — The process of wearing away of land surface by wind or water. This process occurs naturally but can be caused or increased by activities, including but not limited to farming, residential or industrial development, construction activities, timber cutting, and stream crossing activities, e.g., culvert and bridge placement.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>ETHNOHYDROLOGICAL USE — Uses of water and associated natural resources that are unique to Menominee ways of life, including but not limited to harvesting wild rice, lake sturgeon, and medicinal and certain other plant and animal species, and the associated cultural phenomenon; see Article II.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>EUTROPHICATION — The process of fertilization that causes high productivity and biomass in an aquatic ecosystem. Eutrophication can be a natural process or it can be a cultural process accelerated by an increase of nutrient loading to a lake resulting from human activity.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>EXISTING USES — Those uses actually attained by Menominee peoples in a water body on or after November 28, 1975, whether or not they are included in the water quality standards.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>EXOTIC SPECIES — Species of plants or animals that are generally considered unwanted nuisance organisms or populations that are not native but have been introduced, including but not limited to rusty crayfish, zebra mussels, sea lamprey, purple loosestrife, and Eurasian milfoil.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>FEASIBILITY REPORT — Analysis and report of the practicability of a proposed action. A feasibility report should outline an analysis of the proposed activities; site description; name of person(s) proposing a new or increased discharge or other activity that may require a permit from the Tribe; potential loadings estimates; water quality, quantity and other impacts; antidegradation demonstration; and benefits that the Tribe will realize from said water and/or environmental alteration under consideration.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>FISH, WILDLIFE AND AQUATIC LIFE USE — See Article II of this chapter.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>FOOD CHAIN/WEB — Sequences of organisms, each of which uses other members in the ecosystem as a food source; strategies include but are not limited to herbivorism, carnivorism, parasitism, and symbiotic relationships. Often complex feeding networks occur within an ecosystem, whereby members may belong to one or more chains. Members of a chain are interdependent, so that a disturbance to one species can disrupt the entire system.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>GREAT LAKES INITIATIVE (GLI) — The water quality standards for the Great Lakes as found at 40 CFR Part 132, as amended.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>HABITAT — The place where individuals and/or populations of living organisms live and the surrounding living and nonliving ecosystem. "Habitat" generally includes food, cover, and other basic requirements for individuals and populations to lead healthy life cycles.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>HABITAT AND NATURAL FOOD CHAIN MAINTENANCE USE — See Article II of this chapter.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>HAZARDOUS SUBSTANCE(S) — As defined by the United States EPA in 40 CFR 261.3 and in Chapter 361, Article I of this Code.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>HAZARDOUS WASTE — As defined by the United States EPA in 49 CFR 171.8 and in Chapter 361, Article II of this Code.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>HEAVY METALS — Inorganic elements with high atomic weights, including but not limited to mercury, chromium, copper, cadmium, arsenic, and lead.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>INDICATOR SPECIES — An organism, species, or community whose characteristics reflect the presence of certain environmental conditions.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>INDUSTRIAL — Refers to organized enterprise(s) and activities that often have discharges and/or emissions of waste(s) and/or by-product(s) associated with them, including but not limited to manufacturing plants, paper mills, companies engaged in industrial production or service, mining activities, including dewatering practices, foundries, and factories.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>LOADING(S) — The addition of a substance to a water body; the concentration of a substance within a discharge multiplied by the flow of the discharge over a specified time expressed as concentration/unit time. The Tribe shall require the use of low flows as standard applications for evaluating loadings.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>LOW FLOW — The seven-day, ten-year stream design flow (7Q10) or the four-day, three-year biologically based stream design flow for chronic aquatic life criteria or values; the one-day, ten-year stream design flow (1Q10) for acute aquatic life criteria or values; the harmonic mean flow for human health criteria or values; or the ninety-day, ten-year flow (90Q10) for wildlife criteria [40 CFR Part 132, Appendix F, Procedure 3, Sec. (E)(1)]. See "design low flow."</aftertext>
      <aftertext>METABOLITE — A substance that is the product of biological changes to a chemical.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>MICROGRAMS PER LITER (ug/l) — Equivalent to 10-6 kilograms per liter or parts per billion (ppb), assuming unit density.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>MILLIGRAMS PER LITER (mg/l) — Equivalent to 10-3 kilograms per liter or parts per million (ppm), assuming unit density.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>MITW — Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>MITW WQS — Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin Water Quality Standards.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>MIXING ZONE — A limited area or volume of water where initial dilution of a discharge takes place and where certain numeric water quality criteria can be exceeded but acutely toxic conditions are prevented. See Article VI.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>MONITORING — A scientifically designed system of continuing standardized measurements and observations and the evaluation thereof.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>MS4 — Municipal separate storm sewer system, defined as all separate storm sewers that are owned or operated by the United States or a state, city, town, borough, county, parish, district, association, or other public body having jurisdiction over disposal of sewage, industrial wastes, stormwater, or other wastes, including special districts under state or tribal law, such as a sewer district, flood control district or drainage district, or similar entity, or an Indian tribe or an authorized Indian tribal organization, or a designated and approved management agency that discharges to waters of the United States.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>NANOGRAMS PER LITER — Equivalent to 10-9 kilograms per liter or parts per trillion (ppt), assuming unit density.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>NATIONAL POLLUTANT DISCHARGE ELIMINATION SYSTEM (NPDES) — The national program for issuing, modifying, revoking and reissuing, terminating, monitoring and enforcing permits and imposing and enforcing pretreatment requirements under Sections 307, 402, 318, and 405 of the Clear Water Act (CWA). The term includes an approved program.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>NATURAL CONDITIONS —</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>The normal background physico-chemical characteristics and other physical, chemical, and biological conditions of water and the course in which it flows or is situated and the normal background daily and seasonal variations in weather, climatic, and atmospheric conditions that affect these waters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>The levels of nonanthropogenic substances/chemicals present in ambient water that are from natural, as opposed to man-induced, sources.</text>
        <text>NATURAL PHYSICO-CHEMICAL CHARACTERISTICS — Natural background levels for parameters including but not limited to dissolved oxygen, oxygen demand, pH, temperature, suspended solids, dissolved ions, organics, and metals.</text>
        <text>NAVIGABLE WATERS — Waters with beds and banks and sufficiently deep and wide for navigation with a canoe or other small craft. Navigable waters of the United States are those waters that are subject to the ebb and flow of the tide and/or are presently used, or have been used in the past, or may be susceptible for use to transport tribal, interstate or foreign commerce or other intermittent waterways that may be deemed by the Director to fulfill purposes of navigation. A determination of navigability, once made, applies laterally over the entire surface of the water body and is not extinguished by other actions or events which impede or destroy the navigable capacity.</text>
        <text>NEW AND EXISTING HYDROLOGIC MODIFICATIONS — Include, but are not limited to, dams and other impoundments, straightening and flow alteration activities, wetland drainages, and withdrawal of water.</text>
        <text>NONPOINT SOURCE POLLUTION — Pollution sources that are diffuse and do not have a single point of origin and are not introduced into a receiving stream or other body of water from a specific outlet. The pollutants are generally carried off land by runoff, urban runoff and other sources of pollution that generally cannot be classified as point sources of pollution. Common sources include agriculture, urban areas, certain industrial activities, construction sites, dams and other hydrologic and hydraulic modifications, private on-site waste treatment systems, and land disposal.</text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>NPDES — See "National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System." OMRW — Outstanding Menominee resource water; see Article VI. ONRW — Outstanding national resource water; see Article VI.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>PERMIT — An authorization, license, or equivalent control document issued by the Tribe, EPA, an approved state, United States Army Corps of Engineers (USACE), or other federal agency to implement the requirements of this chapter, the CWA, and other regulations, including but not limited to a tribal water quality certification, a tribal water permit or a permit issued under the NPDES program.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>PERSON — See "entity."</aftertext>
      <aftertext>PESTICIDE — A substance intended for preventing, destroying, repelling or mitigating any pest. Also, any substance or mixture of substances intended for use as a plant regulator, defoliant, or desiccant.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>pH — The negative logarithm of the hydrogen ion activity concentration when expressed as moles per liter, or pH = -log (H+).</aftertext>
      <aftertext>PICOGRAMS PER LITER (pg/l) — The picograms of a substance per liter of solution is equivalent to 10-12 kilograms per liter or parts per quadrillion (ppq), assuming unit density.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>PLANTS — All living aquatic and terrestrial plants in the kingdom Plantae, including but not limited to nonvascular and vascular plants, emergent and submergent vegetation, algae, mosses, ferns, liverworts, shrubs, trees, and wild rice.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>POINT SOURCE — Any discernible, confined, and discrete conveyance, including but not limited to a pipe, ditch, channel, tunnel, conduit, well, discrete fissure, container, rolling stock, concentrated animal feeding operation, landfill leachate collection system, vessel or other floating craft, from which pollutants are or may be discharged.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>POLLUTANT — Dredged spoil, solid waste, incinerator residue, filter backwash, sewage, garbage, sewage sludge, munitions, chemical wastes, biological materials, all radioactive materials, heat, wrecked or discarded equipment, rock, sand, cellar dirt, nutrients, toxic substances, pesticides, and industrial, municipal, and agricultural waste (and their components and breakdown products) discharged into water or entering through other means.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>POLLUTION — Generally, the presence of matter or energy whose nature, location, or quantity produces undesired environmental effects; under the Clean Water Act, for example, the term is defined as the man-made or man-induced alteration of the physical, biological, and radiological integrity of water.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>POLLUTION PREVENTION — Measures taken to reduce the generation of a substance and/or mitigate for an activity that could be harmful to living organisms in the environment.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>PRIMARY WASTE TREATMENT — This treatment consists of the first steps in wastewater treatment during which sedimentation cells/tanks, and possibly screens, are used to remove most materials that settle or will float.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>PUBLICLY OWNED TREATMENT WORKS (POTW) — Treatment works owned by the Tribe or municipality. This includes any devices and systems used in the storage, treatment, recycling and reclamation of municipal sewage or industrial wastes of a liquid nature. It also includes sewers, pipes and other conveyances only if they convey wastewater to a POTW treatment plant. Privately owned treatment works, federally owned treatment works and other treatment plants not owned by municipalities are not considered publicly owned treatment works.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>RECREATIONAL USE — See Article II of this chapter.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>REMEDIAL ACTION — Remedies required to address problems associated with contaminated sites, nonpermitted activities, or activities that threaten or are detrimental to designated and other uses.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>RISK ASSESSMENT — A qualitative and quantitative evaluation to define the hazards posed to human health and/or the environment.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>RUNOFF — That part of precipitation, snowmelt, or irrigation water that drains off land, in sheet flow, in rivulets, or in defined watercourses, into surface water. This water can carry sediments and pollutants into receiving waters.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>RUN-OF-RIVER — Hydraulic condition whereby instantaneous inflow equals instantaneous outflow.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>SANITARY SURVEY — A thorough investigation and evaluation of a surface water and/or groundwater, including but not limited to sampling to determine the extent and cause of any bacteriological contamination.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>SECONDARY WASTE TREATMENT — The second step in most waste treatment systems in which aerobic bacterial treatment of wastewater removes floating and settling solids and about 90% of the oxygen-demanding substances and suspended solids.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>SEDIMENTS — Soil, sand, gravel, and minerals eroded from land by water or air, or introduced through anthropogenic activity, that generally settle to the bottom of surface water.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>SEWAGE — The waste and wastewater discharged into sewers from homes and industry.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>SPAWNING AREA — Regions and areas in a water body, including but not limited to riffles, beds, backwaters, marshes, and wetlands, where fish concentrate breeding activities and subsequently eggs are hatched.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>SPRING — A (natural) source of water issuing from the ground.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>STATISTICALLY SIGNIFICANT NUMBER OF SAMPLES — A sufficient number of samples to render a statistically valid conclusion.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>SURFACE WATER — All waters open to the atmosphere, including rivers, streams, creeks, lakes, reservoirs, impoundments, and wetlands, but excluding sewage lagoons and other facilities constructed for the treatment of wastewater, settling ponds, and cooling lakes.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>TERTIARY WASTE TREATMENT —</aftertext>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Advanced treatment of wastewater that goes beyond the secondary or biological stage and removes pollutants, e.g., metals, organics, and nutrients, and most biological oxygen demand and suspended solids.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Any treatment beyond biological.</text>
        <text>TOXIC SUBSTANCE — A substance that can cause death, disease, behavioral abnormalities, cancer, genetic mutations, teratogenic effects, physiological or reproductive malfunction or physical deformities in any organism or its offspring through concentration and/or bioaccumulation in the food chain, acting alone or in combination with other substances or breakdown products. These include, but are not limited to, PCBs, heavy metals, pesticides, hazardous wastes, and other components of discharges, effluent, and emissions and other pollution sources that result in atmospheric deposition of these substances.</text>
        <text>TRIBAL LEGISLATURE — The nine-member governing body of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin elected by tribal members and empowered with authority and jurisdiction contained in the Constitution and Bylaws of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin.</text>
      </para>
      <aftertext>TRIBAL WATER PERMIT — See Article VIII of this chapter.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>TRIBE — The Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin, a federally recognized sovereign Indian tribe. TRIBUTARY — A stream or creek inlet flowing into a larger body of water.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>UNAUTHORIZED CONDITIONS — Existing conditions stemming from anthropogenic causes that violate portions of this chapter.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>UNAUTHORIZED DISCHARGE OF SUBSTANCE(S) — Chemicals, toxic substances, hazardous substances or wastes, components of industrial discharge(s), heavy metals, organic compounds, pesticides, discharge(s), loadings, or other pollutants that enter ONRW or affect OMRW designated waters of the Reservation without prior issuance of a tribal water permit.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>URBAN RUNOFF — Stormwater from city streets and adjacent domestic or commercial properties, construction and other surface disturbance sites, and parking lots that may pick up terrestrial contamination and carry pollutants of various kinds into sewer systems and/or receiving waters.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>UTILITY LINE — Any pipe or pipeline for the transportation of any gaseous, liquid, liquefiable, or slurry substance, for any purpose, and any cable, line or wire for the transmission for any purpose of electrical energy, telephone and telegraph messages, and radio and television communication.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>WASTEWATER — The spent or used water from individual homes, a community, a farm, or an industry that contains dissolved or suspended matter and/or other pollutants.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>WATERSHED — The land area that drains water into rivers, streams, creeks, intermittent streams, wetlands, or lakes.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>WATERS OF THE RESERVATION — Such accumulations of water, surface and underground, natural and artificial, public and private, or parts thereof, which are wholly or partially within, flow through, or border upon the Menominee Reservation, but the term does not include any private or municipal pond, or any pond, reservoir or facility built for reduction or control of pollution or cooling of water prior to discharge unless the discharge therefrom causes or threatens to cause water pollution.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>WETLANDS — Areas that are inundated or saturated by surface water or groundwater at a frequency and duration sufficient to support, and that under normal circumstances do support, a prevalence of vegetation typically adapted for life in saturated (hydric) soil conditions. Wetlands generally include, but are not limited to, swamps, marshes, bogs, and similar areas.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>WILDLIFE — All living creatures in the kingdom Anamalia, including but not limited to mammals, birds, reptiles, amphibians, fish, clams, crustaceans, and other invertebrate animals.</aftertext>
      <aftertext>WILDLIFE HABITAT AND NATURAL FOOD CHAIN USE — See Article II of this chapter.</aftertext>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>3</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Amended at time of adoption of Code (see <cite path="|I|1|II">Ch. 1, General Provisions, Art. II</cite>).</text>
        </footnote>
        <footnote>
          <num>4</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Amended at time of adoption of Code (see <cite path="|I|1|II">Ch. 1, General Provisions, Art. II</cite>).</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-6</num>
      <heading>Acronyms.</heading>
      <text>As used in <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite>, the following acronyms shall have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <text>BCC	Bioaccumulative chemicals of concern</text>
      <text>BMPs	Best management practices</text>
      <text>BOD	Biochemical oxygen demand</text>
      <text>C1	Candidate species</text>
      <text>CCC	Criterion continuous concentration</text>
      <text>CERCLA	Comprehensive Environmental Response Compensation and Liability Act</text>
      <text>CF	Conversion factor</text>
      <text>CMC	Criterion maximum concentration</text>
      <text>CWA	Clear Water Act</text>
      <text>EPA	Environmental Protection Agency</text>
      <text>ESA	Endangered Species Act</text>
      <text>FWS	United States Fish and Wildlife Service</text>
      <text>GLI	Great Lakes Initiative</text>
      <text>HCV	Human cancer value</text>
      <text>HNV	Human noncancer value</text>
      <text>MITW	Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin</text>
      <text>MITW WQS	Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin Water Quality Standards</text>
      <text>ML	Minimum level</text>
      <text>MS4	Municipal separate storm sewer system</text>
      <text>NEPA	National Environmental Policy Act</text>
      <text>NOI	Notice of intent</text>
      <text>NOT	Notice of termination</text>
      <text>OMRW	Outstanding Menominee resource waters</text>
      <text>ONRW	Outstanding national resource waters</text>
      <text>NPDES	National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System</text>
      <text>PEL	Preliminary effluent limitations</text>
      <text>PEQ	Projected effluent quality</text>
      <text>PMP	Pollutant minimization program</text>
      <text>POTW	Publicly owned treatment works</text>
      <text>POWTS	Private on-site wastewater treatment system</text>
      <text>SS	Suspended solids</text>
      <text>SWMP	Stormwater management plan</text>
      <text>SWPPP	Stormwater pollution prevention plan</text>
      <text>WET	Whole effluent toxicity</text>
      <text>WLA	Waste load allocation</text>
      <text>WQBEL	Water-quality-based effluent limitation</text>
      <text>WQS	Water quality standards</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>II</num>
    <heading>Designated Uses</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-7</num>
      <heading>Designated water uses.</heading>
      <text>Water uses designated herein shall be protected and water quality and quantity shall be maintained at present and/or natural conditions in order to protect and maintain designated, existing, and other beneficial uses of tribal waters. Criteria listed in Article V shall be used as standards to protect water quality, drinking water sources, fish, wildlife and aquatic life, human health, cultural, ceremonial, religious, and spiritual uses, habitat and natural food chain maintenance, and other consumptive and nonconsumptive designated, existing, and other beneficial uses. All waters of the Reservation will be protected to support the following designated uses:</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Fish, wildlife and aquatic life use. All waters of the Reservation are designated to provide for the protection and propagation of balanced ecosystems for indigenous fish (as well as rainbow trout and kokanee salmon), wildlife and aquatic life, including wild rice (Zizania aquatica), lake sturgeon (Acipenser fulvescens), and other plants and animals, and the protection of human health from disease related to consumption of fish, wildlife, and aquatic life, as well as the protection of these organisms from disease. All streams and rivers of the Reservation are further designated to provide a self-sustaining trout fishery, in addition to certain lakes marked with a "(T)" in Article III. The following ecosystems and their associated uses shall be protected:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Cold water ecosystems. These ecosystems include surface waters capable of supporting a community of cold water fish and other aquatic life, or serving as a spawning area and or overwintering area for cold water fish species, including trout (Salmonidae), sculpins (Cottidae), and certain minnow (Cyprinidae) species. This category shall apply to all streams and rivers of the Reservation, except (lower) portions of the Wolf River as noted in <cite path="§512-7|A|(2)">Subsection A(2)</cite> below, and to lakes that are marked with a "(T)" in Article III.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Warm water ecosystems. These ecosystems include surface waters capable of supporting a community of warm water sport fish or that serve as spawning areas for warm water sport fish. This designation shall apply to all lakes of the Reservation, with the exception of lakes that are marked with a "(T)" in Article III, and portions of the Wolf River during certain times of year because the river will support both warm and cold water fish.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Wetlands. These ecosystems include areas that are defined as such and may include wild rice beds. Article IV of <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> provides additional language regarding wetlands.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Recreation use. All waters of the Reservation are designated for full-body recreational use, which necessitates primary contact with the water, including underwater swimming and incidental ingestion of water through participation in the recreational activity. Recreational uses also include white water rafting, canoeing, fishing, and wading, and other uses.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Ceremonial, religious and spiritual use. All waters of the Reservation are used for ceremonial and spiritual purposes by tribal members (and descendants). The Tribe holds water sacred, and our historic past epitomizes this statement. The original five clans of the Menominee, consisting of the Bear, Eagle, Wolf, Crane, and Moose, depended on water to sustain life and used water to perform their ceremonial responsibilities. Additional historic and modern ceremonial uses of water include, but are not limited to, uses in the annual Sturgeon Ceremony, wild rice harvest, and the harvesting of medicinal plants from waters of the Reservation. Traditional religious use of water in Big Drum Ceremonies, the sweat lodge, and other ceremonies is (still) practiced today. These uses may involve, among other things, primary direct contact, drinking and inhalation of water. Recognizing the ceremonial and traditional use of water and its life-giving properties is important for the spiritual significance of the Menominee people.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Cultural use. All waters of the Reservation, and aquatic natural resources, are designated for historic, traditional, and cultural uses. Cultural water uses encompass all ethnohydrological uses of water associated with unique Menominee ways of life. These uses include, but are not limited to, the ethnobotanical harvest and medicinal use of numerous plants associated with aquatic, wetland, and riparian habitats, as well as basic socioeconomic uses of waters of the Reservation for sustenance. Aquatic plants that grow in waters of the Reservation are vital to continuation of Menominee culture through the use of those plants for medicinal purposes by Menominee people.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>All living things on the Menominee Reservation in some way use the waters of the Reservation to sustain life. People, animals, birds, plants, trees, and insects use water and have their place in Menominee culture.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Waters of the Reservation shall be maintained and protected in such an ecological condition that will allow (traditional) Menominee educational uses associated with waters of the Reservation to continue perpetually.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Cultural educational uses shall include, but not be limited to, ethnohydrological learning experiences that are passed from one generation to the next regarding the harvest of plants and animals. Culturally, to the Menominee people, waters of the Reservation are as significant as the forest ecosystem and will continue to be regarded with the same deference. The Tribe protects the forest ecosystem with sustained yield forestry management practices; this same (everlasting) treatment shall be afforded waters of the Reservation, for it is the very essence of sustaining life which is critical to maintaining the culture of the Menominee people. Cultural uses are very significant to the Tribe, indigenous forest-dwelling people that have for more than five millennia relied upon the water in the Tribe's historic range to sustain unique Menominee ways of life.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Fish and wildlife habitat and natural food chain maintenance use.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>All waters, and aquatic and riparian ecosystems, of the Reservation are designated for wildlife habitat and natural food chain maintenance. Naturally occurring food chains/webs shall be maintained, including but not limited to predator-prey relationships, browsing and grazing strategies, and symbiotic relationships related to food acquisition. The Tribe realizes direct benefits from this usage, including specific and general ecological benefits, consumptive and nonconsumptive environmental and natural resource uses, including but not limited to the taking of fish, furbearers, waterfowl, wild rice, and other aquatic life for human consumption, and cultural, spiritual, and religious benefits and aesthetic and other legitimate benefits and uses. Menominee cultural beliefs indicate that humans fit into the natural food chain; therefore, natural food chain maintenance associated with aquatic and riparian areas must be protected and/or restored.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Waters of the Reservation shall also be protected in order to provide continued ecological support for a number of rare, threatened, endangered, and culturally significant species, including but not limited to the bald eagle (Haliaeetus luecocephalus), osprey (Pandion haliaetus), red-shouldered hawk (Buteo lineatus), slippershell mussel (Alasmidonta viridis), blandings turtle (Emydoidea blandingii), pine marten (Martes americana), lake sturgeon (Acipenser fulvescens), sandhill crane (Grus canadensis), timber wolf (Canis lupus), common loon (Gavia immer), pygmy snaketail dragonfly (Ophiogomphus howeii), Karner blue butterfly(Lycaeides melissa samuelis), Phlox moth (Schinia indiana), Missouri rock cress (Arabis missouriensis var deamii), Indian cucumber root (Medeola virginiana), pitcher plant (Sarracenia purpurea), and cranberries, among others.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>F.</num>
        <text>Navigation use. All navigable waters of the Reservation are designated for navigational uses for tribal purposes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>G.</num>
        <text>Forestry use. All waters of the Reservation are designated to support a healthy forest ecosystem and to provide adequate water conditions for propagation of native tree species that are subject to Menominee sustained yield forestry management and for other agricultural purposes that befit the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>H.</num>
        <text>Public drinking water supply use. All waters of the Reservation shall be protected for use as municipal public drinking water supplies. Groundwater for all other users is protected by <cite path="|II|562">Chapter 562</cite>, Article I, Groundwater Quality, of this Code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>I.</num>
        <text>Industrial water supply use. All waters of the Reservation shall be available for regulated industrial use(s), except those waters that are designated outstanding national resource waters.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>III</num>
    <heading>Waters of the Reservation</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-8</num>
      <heading>List of water bodies.</heading>
      <text>Waters of the Reservation make up part of the Great Lakes basin and drain into Lake Michigan via the Wolf River Lower Green Bay Watershed and the Oconto River Upper Green Bay Watershed. The following two tables list the water bodies within the Reservation according to <cite path="§512-8|A">Subsection A</cite>, Lakes, and <cite path="§512-8|B">Subsection B</cite>, Rivers, Streams, and Creeks.</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Lakes of the Menominee Reservation.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <th>Lake Names</th>
                <th colspan="3">Location</th>
                <th>Base Map Key</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <th>T-N</th>
                <th>R-E</th>
                <th>Sec.</th>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Askennette Springs (T)</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>E-9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Bass Lake (Southeast)</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>25</td>
                <td>Q-24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Bass Lake (Lower)</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>12</td>
                <td>B-6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Bass Lake (Upper) (T)</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>1</td>
                <td>A-6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Beauprey Lake</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>19</td>
                <td>J-19</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Beauprey Springs (T)</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>10</td>
                <td>H-22</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Berry Lake</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>24</td>
                <td>P-24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Big Blacksmith Lake (L.L.)</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>O-21</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Big Injun Lake</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>34</td>
                <td>F-22</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Brigham Lake</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>17</td>
                <td>C-8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Burney Lake (Nahwahquaw)</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>21</td>
                <td>J-3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Coon Lake</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>25</td>
                <td>Q-24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Cott Lake</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>C-10</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Crowell Lake</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>18</td>
                <td>C-7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Crystal Springs Lake (T)</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>8</td>
                <td>B-20</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Deadman Springs Lake (T)</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>C-15</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Elma Lake (Peters) (T)</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>35</td>
                <td>F-5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Founder Lake</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>11</td>
                <td>B-23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Frechette's (Camp Pond) Lake (T)</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>32</td>
                <td>F-8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Fredenberg Lake</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>26</td>
                <td>E-23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Grignon Lake</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>12</td>
                <td>H-24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Half Moon Lake</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>32</td>
                <td>L-20</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Hazel Lake</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>18</td>
                <td>C-7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Hemlock Lake</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>21</td>
                <td>J-3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Kemmet Springs Lake (T)</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>3</td>
                <td>A-4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Keshena Lake</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>24</td>
                <td>P-18</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Labelle Lake</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>9</td>
                <td>H-21</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Lamotte Lake</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>19</td>
                <td>P-19</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Laverne Lake</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>9</td>
                <td>B-9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Herman's Lake</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>7</td>
                <td>B-7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Little Blacksmith Lake (L.L.)</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>O-21</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Little Rice Lake</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>36</td>
                <td>R-24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Little Sand Lake (Lyon's)</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>23</td>
                <td>P-23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Long Lake (Long Marsh)</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>O-23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Lower McCall Lake (T)</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>24</td>
                <td>D-12</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Marsh Lake (Waupoose)</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>2</td>
                <td>G-23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>McCall Lake (T)</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>24</td>
                <td>D-12</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Moshawqutt Lake</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>24</td>
                <td>O-24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Neconish Lake</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>20</td>
                <td>D-2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Neopit Mill Pond (T)</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>19</td>
                <td>J-7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Noseum Lake (T)</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>E-3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>North Springs (T)</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>4</td>
                <td>A-3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Perch Lake</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>26</td>
                <td>Q-23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Perote Lake</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>9</td>
                <td>B-9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Peshtigo Lake (L.L.)</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>17</td>
                <td>O-20</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Pine Lake (Mud)</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>26</td>
                <td>Q-23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Pine Lake (Section 9)</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>9</td>
                <td>H-21</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Pywaosit Lake (L.L.)</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>23</td>
                <td>P-23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Rainbow Pond</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>O-22</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Red Springs (T)</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>20</td>
                <td>J-2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Rice Lake</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>35</td>
                <td>R-23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Round Lake</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>21</td>
                <td>P-21</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Rushes (Rush) Lake</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>3</td>
                <td>M-22</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Sand Lake</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>22</td>
                <td>P-22</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Saint Joseph Lake (Church)</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>2</td>
                <td>G-23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Sapokesick Lake (L.L.)</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>O-22</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Skice Lake (L.L.)</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>19</td>
                <td>P-19</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Spring Lake (L.L.)</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>17</td>
                <td>O-20</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Stone Lake</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>4</td>
                <td>M-21</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Stoney Lake (Cool)</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>7</td>
                <td>N-19</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Sunia Lake</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>19</td>
                <td>D-19</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Teabeau Lake</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>E-9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Turtle Lake</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>3</td>
                <td>A-22</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Vejo Lake</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>35</td>
                <td>F-23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Wah-Toh-Sah Lake (L.L.)</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>19</td>
                <td>P-19</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Walleye Pond (Gravel Pit)</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>O-16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Waukau Lake</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>31</td>
                <td>L-19</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Weso Lake</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>1</td>
                <td>A-24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Additional unnamed lakes</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
        <text>NOTES:</text>
        <text>(L.L.)	–	Component	lakes making up present Legend Lake.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(T)</num>
          <text>–	Lakes that presently support or are capable of supporting trout species; these are designated cold water ecosystems.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Rivers, streams, and creeks of the Menominee Reservation.</text>
        <text>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <th>Lake Names</th>
                <td/>
                <th colspan="3">Location</th>
                <td/>
                <th>Base Map Key</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td/>
                <th>T-N</th>
                <th>R-E</th>
                <th>Sec.</th>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Big Eddy Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>26</td>
                <td>K-17</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Bowhunter Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>35</td>
                <td>L-11</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Burnt Shanty Creek</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>2</td>
                <td>A-17</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Camp 2 Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>6</td>
                <td>G-1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Camp 7 Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>23</td>
                <td>J-5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Camp 12 Creek</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>20</td>
                <td>D-14</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Camp 15 Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>21</td>
                <td>J-9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Chickney Creek</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>22</td>
                <td>P-16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Crow Rapids Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>32</td>
                <td>L-8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Dalles Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>3</td>
                <td>G-16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Deadman Creek</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>22</td>
                <td>D-16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Ducknest Creek</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>27</td>
                <td>E-16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Elma Creek</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>36</td>
                <td>F-6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Elton Creek</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>3</td>
                <td>A-10</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Evergreen River</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>27</td>
                <td>E-16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>First North Branch Mill Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>32</td>
                <td>L-8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>First South Branch Oconto River</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>4</td>
                <td>A-21</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Fish Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>18</td>
                <td>I-13</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Five Islands Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>18</td>
                <td>I-19</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Florence Creek</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>2</td>
                <td>A-5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Founder Creek</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>C-23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Gardner Creek</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>Q-13</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Jackson Creek</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>12</td>
                <td>N-24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Kinepoway Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>35</td>
                <td>L-17</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Lazy Creek</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>27</td>
                <td>E-16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Linzy Creek</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>12</td>
                <td>N-24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Little West Branch Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>33</td>
                <td>L-15</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Little West Branch Wolf River</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>24</td>
                <td>J-6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>McCall Creek</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>20</td>
                <td>D-14</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Menominee Creek</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>C-5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Miller Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>32</td>
                <td>L-8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Minnow Creek</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>2</td>
                <td>M-17</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>North Branch Allender Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>34</td>
                <td>L-10</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>North Branch Menominee Creek</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>C-4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>North Branch Oshkosh Creek</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>Q-15</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>North Branch Weso Creek</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>1</td>
                <td>A-24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Noseum Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>3</td>
                <td>G-4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Oshkosh Creek</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>27</td>
                <td>Q-16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Peavy Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>26</td>
                <td>K-11</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Pecore Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>12</td>
                <td>H-24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Pendelton Creek</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>6</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Pine Creek</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>35</td>
                <td>R-23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Rapids Creek</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>34</td>
                <td>F-16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Red River</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>33</td>
                <td>L-3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Rice Creek</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>34</td>
                <td>R-22</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Second North Branch Mill Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>32</td>
                <td>L-8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Soman Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>24</td>
                <td>J-18</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>South Branch Oconto River</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>C-24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Squaw Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>2</td>
                <td>G-11</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Tall Timber Creek</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>7</td>
                <td>B-13</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Third North Branch Mill Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>36</td>
                <td>L-6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Tourtillott Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>14</td>
                <td>20</td>
                <td>J-8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Tousey Creek</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>33</td>
                <td>L-3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Wayka Creek</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>2</td>
                <td>M-17</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Weso Creek</td>
                <td>30</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>1</td>
                <td>A-24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>West Branch Chickney Creek</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>O-15</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>West Branch Red River</td>
                <td>29</td>
                <td>13</td>
                <td>31</td>
                <td>L-1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>West Branch Wolf River</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>2</td>
                <td>M-17</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>Wolf River</td>
                <td>28</td>
                <td>15</td>
                <td>35</td>
                <td>R-17</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </text>
        <text>Additional unnamed and/ or intermittent streams and creeks</text>
        <text><strong>NOTE</strong>: All rivers, streams, and creeks are designated cold water ecosystems capable of supporting trout fisheries.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container cache:ref-path="II|512|IV">
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>IV</num>
    <heading>Wetlands</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-9</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>As used in <cite path="|II|512|IV">this article</cite>, the following terms shall have the meanings indicated:</text>
      <text>CUMULATIVE IMPACTS — Attributable to the proposed activity which may occur, based upon past or reasonably anticipated impacts on wetland functional values of similar activities in the affected area.</text>
      <text>MITIGATION PROJECT — The restoration, enhancement or creation of wetlands to compensate for adverse impacts to other wetlands. "Mitigation project" includes using credits from a wetland mitigation bank.</text>
      <text>PRACTICABLE ALTERATIVES — Available and capable of being implemented after taking into consideration cost, available technology and logistics in the light of overall project purposes.</text>
      <text>WATER DEPENDENCY or WETLAND DEPENDENCY — The activity is of a nature that requires location in or adjacent to surface waters or wetlands to fulfill its basic purpose.</text>
      <text>WETLAND MITIGATION BANK — A system of accounting for wetland loss and compensation that includes one or more sites where wetlands are restored, enhanced or created to provide transferable credits to be subsequently applied to compensate for adverse impacts to other wetlands.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-10</num>
      <heading>Purpose.</heading>
      <text>The purpose of <cite path="|II|512|IV">this article</cite> is to establish water quality standards to protect, preserve, restore, and enhance the quality of waters in wetlands and other waters of the Reservation influenced by wetlands. These standards are intended to protect tribal rights and interest, public health and welfare and the present and prospective uses of wetlands, including designated, existing, and other beneficial uses. Conditions necessary to protect water-quality-related functions and values of wetlands are set forth in <cite path="|II|512|IV">this article</cite>. Wetland water quality standards serve as a basis for developing and implementing strategies to achieve the purposes of <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> and also serve as a basis for decisions in regulatory, permitting, or planning activities that impact water quality and impact wetlands.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-11</num>
      <heading>Wetland functions and values.</heading>
      <text>Natural hydrological and hydraulic conditions necessary to support the biological, chemical, and physical characteristics naturally present in wetlands, including wild rice beds, shall be maintained, preserved, restored, and protected to prevent significant adverse impacts to the wetlands. The following water-quality-related functional values or uses of wetlands shall be protected, within the range of natural variation:</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Stormwater and floodwater storage and retention and the moderation of water level fluctuation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Hydrologic functions, including the maintenance of dry season stream flow, the discharge of groundwater to a wetland, the recharge of groundwater from a wetland to another area and the flow of groundwater through a wetland;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Filtration or storage of sediments, nutrients, or toxic substances that would otherwise adversely impact the quality of waters of the Reservation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Shoreline protection against erosion through the dissipation of wave energy and water velocity and anchoring of sediments;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Habitat for aquatic organisms in the food chain/web, including but not limited to fish, crustaceans, mollusks, insects, annelids, planktonic organisms and the plants and animals upon which these aquatic organisms feed and depend upon for their needs in all life stages;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>F.</num>
        <text>Habitat for resident and transient wildlife species, including mammals, birds, reptiles, and amphibians, for breeding, resting, nesting, escape cover, travel corridors and food; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>G.</num>
        <text>Recreational, cultural, educational, scientific and natural aesthetic values and other uses.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-12</num>
      <heading>Narrative criteria.</heading>
      <text>The following criteria shall be used to assure the maintenance or enhancement of the functional values identified above:</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Liquids, fill or other solids or gas may not be present in amounts which may cause significant adverse impacts to wetlands;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Floating or submerged debris, oil, or other material may not be present in amounts which may interfere with tribal rights or interest or which may cause significant adverse impacts to wetlands;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Materials producing color, odor, taste or unsightliness may not be present in amounts which may cause significant adverse impacts to wetlands;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Concentrations or combinations of substances which are toxic or harmful to human, animal or plant life may not be present in amounts which individually or cumulatively may cause significant adverse impacts to wetlands;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Hydrological and hydraulic conditions necessary to support the biological and physical characteristics naturally present in wetlands shall be protected to prevent significant adverse impacts on:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Water currents, erosion or sedimentation patterns;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Water temperature variations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The chemical, nutrient and dissolved oxygen regime of the wetland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The movement of aquatic fauna;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>The pH of the wetland; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Water levels or elevations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>F.</num>
        <text>Existing habitats and populations of wetland animals and vegetation, especially wild rice, shall be maintained by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Protecting habitat through regulation of fluctuating water levels;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Protecting food supplies for fish and wildlife;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Protecting reproductive and nursery areas; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Preventing conditions conducive to the establishment or proliferation of nuisance organisms and exotic species.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-13</num>
      <heading>Implementation.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Applicability. Activities subject to the requirements of <cite path="|II|512|IV">this article</cite> include, but are not limited to, permits, reviews and approvals necessary for the Department to fulfill the requirements of water quality certification. <cite path="|II|512|IV">This article</cite> shall apply to new or increased point source discharges to wetlands.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Metallic minerals. Wetland alterations that are directly caused by operations on a metallic mineral prospecting site or mining site shall be regulated pursuant to specific wetland standards.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Exemptions. <cite path="|II|512|IV">This article</cite> does not apply to the following activities:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Sedimentation and stormwater detention basins and associated conveyance features operated and maintained only for sediment detention and flood storage purposes.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Active sewage lagoons, cooling ponds, waste disposal pits, fish rearing ponds and landscape ponds.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Actively maintained farm drainage and roadside ditches.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Artificial wetlands within active nonmetallic mining operations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Activities exempted from federal regulations. Examples include certain silvicultural and agricultural activities exempted under Section 404 of the Clean Water Act (33 U.S.C. § 1344).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-14</num>
      <heading>Department determinations.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>The Department shall review all proposed activities subject to <cite path="|II|512|IV">this article</cite> and shall determine whether the project proponent has shown, based on the factors in <cite>Subsections D and E</cite>, if the activities are in conformance with the provisions of <cite path="|II|512|IV">this article</cite>. The Department shall, upon request, meet with a project proponent and other interested persons to make a preliminary assessment of the scope for an analysis of alternatives and the potential for compliance with <cite path="|II|512|IV">this article</cite>.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Department shall review the application for completeness within 30 days of receipt of the application. The Department shall notify the applicant of any additional information reasonably necessary to review the application. An application may not be considered complete until the requirements of the National Environmental Policy Act have been met.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The applicant shall submit, at any time during the review process, additional information which the Department finds to be reasonably necessary for review of the application.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>For all activities that meet the criteria listed in <cite path="§512-12">§ 512-12</cite> and that do not require authorization under other regulations or ordinances, the Department shall make a final decision on an application within 60 working days of receipt of a complete application from the project proponent.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The limit of 60 working days does not apply if the Department determines that weather conditions prevent the Department from making a decision in that time frame.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>The Department may rely upon wetland boundary determinations made by other agencies and consultants. If there is a dispute concerning a wetland boundary delineation, the review of the delineation shall be consistent with the procedures identified in the Corps of Engineers Wetlands Delineation Manual, 1987, as determined by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Wetland functional values and the impact of a proposed activity upon those functional values shall be determined using wetland ecological evaluation methods accepted by the Department and appropriate to the affected wetland. The Department shall consider available land use studies in its determinations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>To protect all present and prospective future uses of wetlands, the following factors shall be considered by the Department in making determinations under this section:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Wetland dependency of the proposal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Practicable alternatives to the proposal which will avoid and minimize adverse impacts to wetlands and will not result in other significant adverse environmental consequences.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Impacts that may result from the activity on the maintenance, protection, restoration or enhancement of standards under <cite path="§512-12">§ 512-12</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Cumulative impacts attributable to the proposed activity which may occur, based upon past or reasonably anticipated impacts on wetland functional values of similar activities in the affected area.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Potential secondary impacts on wetland functional values from the proposed activity.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Any potential adverse impacts to wetlands in ONRW areas.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Any potential adverse impact to wetlands in environmentally sensitive areas.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Findings.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Except as provided in <cite path="§512-14|D|(2)">Subsection D(2)</cite>, (3) and (4), the Department shall make a finding that the requirements of <cite path="|II|512|IV">this article</cite> are satisfied if it determines that the project proponent has shown all of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>No practicable alternative exists which would avoid adverse impacts to wetlands.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>If <cite path="§512-14|E|(1)(a)">Subsection E(1)(a)</cite> is met, all practicable measures to minimize adverse impacts to the functional values of the affected wetlands have been taken.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>If <cite path="§512-14|E|(1)(a)">Subsection E(1)(a)</cite> and (b) are met, utilizing the factors in <cite path="§512-14|D|(2)">Subsection D(2)</cite> through (7) and considering potential wetland functional values provided by any mitigation project that is part of the subject application, the Department may find that the activity will not result in significant adverse impacts to wetland functional values, significant adverse impacts to water quality or other significant adverse environmental consequences.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>For all activities that will adversely affect a wetland in a tributary to an ONRW water, the Department may not consider potential functional values provided by any mitigation project that is part of the subject application.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>For all activities which meet one or more of <cite path="§512-14|E|(1)(a)">Subsection E(1)(a)</cite>, (b), and (c), the Department, utilizing the factors in <cite path="§512-11">§ 512-11</cite> and considering potential wetland functional values provided by any mitigation project that is part of the subject application, shall make a finding that the requirements of this article are satisfied if it determines that the project proponent has shown that the activity will not result in significant adverse impacts to wetland functional values, significant adverse impacts to water quality or other significant adverse environmental consequences. The Department may limit the scope of the analysis of alternatives under <cite path="§512-14|D|(2)">Subsection D(2)</cite>, as determined at the preliminary assessment meeting under <cite path="§512-14|A">Subsection A</cite>, if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The activity is wetland dependent.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The surface area of the wetland impact is 0.10 acre or less.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>All wetlands that may be affected by an activity are less than one acre in size, located outside a one-hundred-year floodplain, and not any of the following types:</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>Deep marsh.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>Ridge and swale complex.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[3]</num>
              <text>Ephemeral pond in a wooded setting.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[4]</num>
              <text>Sedge meadow or fresh wet meadow not dominated by reed canary grass.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Mitigation projects and the use of wetland mitigation banks shall be carried out in coordination with the Department and the United States Army Corps of Engineers in accordance with established guidelines for mitigation projects and wetland mitigation banks.</text>
          <text><strong>Note: </strong>Examples of wetland ecological evaluation methods include, but are not limited to, Wetland Evaluation Technique (FHWA/COE), Wisconsin Wetland Evaluation Methodology, Hollands-Magee (IEP/Normandeau), Minnesota Wetland Evaluation Methodology for the North Central United States and the Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources Rapid Assessment Method.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container cache:ref-path="II|512|V">
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>V</num>
    <heading>Water Protection Criteria</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-15</num>
      <heading>Purpose.</heading>
      <text>Narrative and numeric criteria are established herein to govern water management decisions within the drainage basins which affect waters of the Reservation and to preserve and enhance the quality of these waters and to protect designated, existing, and other beneficial uses of tribal waters. Persons engaging in new or existing activities or practices that affect water protection criteria for waters of the Reservation are required to obtain a tribal water permit, see Article VIII. Municipal, industrial, commercial, and domestic activities or practices or other activities which produce a point discharge shall be controlled by issuance of a tribal water permit in addition to meeting Clean Water Act Sections 401 and 402 (NPDES) and other requirements, so that all waters meet the following criteria and conditions and so all downstream uses are protected. Certain activities and practices that do not fall within the purview of NPDES regulation shall be regulated by <cite path="|II|512|V">this article</cite> and chapter.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-16</num>
      <heading>Applicability.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Water protection criteria shall apply to waters of the Reservation during all periods of the year, including low flow water conditions. Criteria shall not be exceeded except where natural background conditions cause such exceedence to occur. All waters of the Reservation shall be free from chemicals, materials, and substances attributable to wastewater or other discharge and nonpoint pollution at levels that are toxic or contribute to violation and/or exceedence of water protection criteria.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Waters of the Reservation shall meet the following narrative and numeric criteria. Additionally these criteria, consistent with Article VI, Antidegradation Policy, shall serve as the basis for development of effluent limitations applicable to point source dischargers through NPDES permits and for tribal water permit purposes.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-17</num>
      <heading>Narrative criteria.</heading>
      <text>Narrative criteria shall apply to govern water management decisions and activities that affect waters of the Reservation and to protect and enhance water quality. The following criteria shall apply:</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Substances that will cause objectionable deposits on the shore or in the bed of a body of water shall not be present in amounts found to be of public health significance or nuisance, nor in amounts which are harmful to animal, plant or aquatic life.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Floating or submerged debris, oil, scum or other material shall not be present in amounts found to be of public health significance or nuisance, nor in amounts which are harmful to animal, plant or aquatic life.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Substances and materials producing color, odor, taste, turbidity, or unsightliness shall not be present in amounts found to be of public health significance or nuisance, nor in amounts which are harmful to animal, plant or aquatic life.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Substances, chemicals, and materials shall not be present in amounts that produce, or contribute to the production of, nuisance aquatic life.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>All waters shall at all places and at all times be free from hazardous substances, toxic, corrosive, or other deleterious substances, chemicals, and materials which, alone or in combination with other substances or in combination with other components of discharges or their breakdown products, are acutely or chronically toxic, carcinogenic, or teratogenic and injure or bioaccumulate, biomagnify, bioconcentrate, or produce adverse physiological responses in human beings and/or fish and aquatic life or which interfere directly or indirectly with designated, existing or other uses. Certain exceptions may be granted for limited mixing zones; see Article VIII, Tribal Water Permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>F.</num>
        <text>All waters shall be free from exotic nuisance species, e.g., purple loosestrife, sea lampreys, Eurasian milfoil, zebra mussels, etc.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>G.</num>
        <text>All waters shall at all places and at all times be free from unauthorized discharges of substances, structures, or objects.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>H.</num>
        <text>Toxic, radioactive, nonconventional, or deleterious material(s), hazardous waste, hazardous material, or other unauthorized discharges of substances shall not be present in waters of the Reservation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>I.</num>
        <text>Activities that damage the beauty, stability and integrity of waters of the Reservation shall be avoided.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>J.</num>
        <text>Biological/ecological communities associated with waters of the Reservation and their biotic and abiotic components and relationships shall be protected. The Wolf River is identified as a resource of special significance. The Wolf River is a complex ecosystem characterized by the presence of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Balanced populations of rare and common species, including but not limited to brook, rainbow, and brown trout, walleye, lake sturgeon, salamander, slippershell and snuffbox mussels, bald eagle, osprey, red-shouldered hawk, pine marten, black bear, river otter, sandhill crane, odanate, plecopteran, tricopteran, ephemeropteran, and a plethora of more common furbearers, waterfowl, shorebirds, and other vertebrate, invertebrate, and plant species;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Diverse unique habitats, including but not limited to wild rice beds, grass islands, thousands of acres of associated wetlands, marshes, swamp conifer and swamp hardwood forest types, breeding and migratory waterfowl habitats, staging areas, nursery areas, white water rapids, waterfalls, dells, granitic outcroppings, riffles and pools, springs, mudflats, sandbars, and spawning areas for numerous fish species, including trout and lake sturgeon; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Associated ecological phenomenon, including but not limited to historic and natural spawning migration, including trout, lake sturgeon, and walleye, predator-prey relationships, e.g., raptor-piscivore and piscivore-piscivore relationships, groundwater and surface water interactions, altruism and other ethological occurrences, and symbiotic relationships between different species.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>K.</num>
        <text>In order to preserve the Wolf River ecosystem, the wild and scenic nature of the river, the diversity of life that depends on the river and its resource value and uses to the Tribe at its present high quality, water quality and quantity in the Wolf River shall be maintained and protected. Conditions that must be met are specified below:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Toxic substances or pollutants shall not be present in the ONRW designated waters of the Wolf River at levels that exceed natural and background concentrations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Flow shall meet naturally occurring rates and levels, i.e., run-of-river conditions.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Temperature, dissolved oxygen, pH, dissolved and suspended solids, dissolved and total carbon, hardness, conductivity, and turbidity levels shall be maintained within the range(s) of natural seasonal and daily variability for the protection of fish, aquatic life and wildlife. The quality and quantity of Wolf River water supporting wild rice shall sufficiently support the propagation and maintenance of healthy wild rice ecosystems.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§512-18">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-18</num>
      <heading>Numeric criteria.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Numeric criteria shall apply to all waters of the Reservation in order to govern water management decisions and activities that enter and/or affect these waters and to protect and enhance water quality. Numeric criteria concentrations shall not be exceeded in waters of the Reservation. No release of substances is permitted which alone or in combination with other substances, or in combination with other components of discharges, or their breakdown products and/or metabolites, would be acutely or chronically toxic, carcinogenic, teratogenic, or otherwise cause significant adverse biological affects to the functions and uses of subject waters and injure or bioaccumulate, bioconcentrate, or produce adverse physiological responses in human beings and/or fish and aquatic life or interfere directly or indirectly with designated, existing, or other uses. The synergistic effects of a proposed discharge and existing discharges and naturally occurring conditions shall also be considered. The following numeric criteria shall apply to waters of the Reservation. (Note: More stringent effluent limitations than those specified herein may be imposed at the discretion of the Director for any pollutant where necessary to meet water quality standards for water receiving the treated discharge.)</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>The criteria of the Water Quality Standards for the Great Lakes System found at 40 CFR Part 132 are incorporated by reference as minimum numeric criteria for water bodies (including wetlands) that comprise part of the Great Lakes drainage.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Where applicable, and for isolated waters (including wetlands), the Department shall employ the National Water Quality Criteria [corrected April 1999, EPA-822-Z-99-001 as amended (<cite path="revcom.pdf">this article</cite>. The Department shall use its discretion to employ numeric criteria consistent with the overall purpose and goals of these standards when considering discharge proposals for isolated waters. In all cases, uses shall be protected and maintained.)] in place of or in addition to the numeric criteria identified in this article. The Department shall use its discretion to employ numeric criteria consistent with the overall purpose and goals of these standards when considering discharge proposals for isolated waters. In all cases, uses shall be protected and maintained.<fn path="|II|§512-18|footnotes|5">5</fn></text>
      </para>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>5</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: The tables which immediately followed this section are now included at the end of <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§512-19">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-19</num>
      <heading>Analytical methods.<fn path="|II|§512-19|footnotes|6">6</fn></heading>
      <text>The analytical testing methods used to measure or otherwise required to evaluate discharge proposals and compliance with water quality criteria and standards shall, to the extent practicable, be in accordance with the Guidelines Establishing Test Procedures for the Analysis of Pollutants (40 CFR Part 136, as amended) and/or the most recent edition of Standard Methods for the Examination of Water and Wastewater (published by the American Public Health Association, American Water Works Association, and the Water Environment Federation) and/or other generally acceptable scientific procedures employed with the concurrence of the Department.</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>For evaluations of toxicity of non-GLI waters, bioassay techniques will be selected as suited to the purpose at hand at the discretion of the Director. As a general guideline bioassays will be conducted using fish and other organisms that are indigenous to the receiving waters and water quality conditions which approximate those of the receiving waters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>The Director may also require analytical methods consistent with those found in Ch. NR 219, Wis. Adm. Code, as requirements to fulfill the objectives of this section.</text>
      </para>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>6</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Amended at time of adoption of Code (see <cite path="|I|1|II">Ch. 1, General Provisions, Art. II</cite>).</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-20</num>
      <heading>Additional criteria for use protection.</heading>
      <text>In addition to numeric and narrative criteria established above, designated uses shall be protected according to the following additional criteria. These criteria shall be met at all times, except where seasonal and natural background conditions prohibit meeting these criteria.</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Fish, wildlife, and aquatic life use protection. Natural physico-chemical characteristics of waters, including dissolved oxygen, temperature, suspended solids, dissolved ions, pH, conductivity, alkalinity, and oxygen demand, are very important in determining the status of that particular ecosystem and its ability to support various groups of organisms living in that community. Deviations from natural conditions and characteristics, for even short periods of time, can be detrimental and/or cause stress to aquatic community ecosystems. The following water quality criteria are established to protect aquatic life, and, except for natural conditions, all waters of the Reservation shall meet the following criteria, and also apply to all publicly owned treatment works and all privately owned domestic sewage treatment works which discharge to surface waters. Additional regulations apply to private on-site wastewater treatment systems (POWTS) which are regulated by <cite path="|II|495">Chapter 495</cite>, Article I, Private Sewage Systems, of this Code.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Dissolved oxygen. The dissolved oxygen content in rivers, streams, and creeks of the Reservation shall not be lowered to less than seven mg/l at any time, or lowered to less than five mg/l for lakes. The daily minimum effluent dissolved oxygen level shall be 4.0 mg/l.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Temperature. There shall be no temperature changes that may adversely affect fish and aquatic life; natural daily and seasonal temperature fluctuations shall be maintained. [Note: Temperature and dissolved oxygen levels for waters of the Reservation, especially waters designated as trout waters and cold water ecosystems, may not be altered from natural background conditions and levels to such an extent that trout populations and other indicator species are adversely affected, especially during spawning seasons (approximately early April to mid May and mid September to the end of October; depending upon water temperature and other factors).]</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>pH. The pH shall not be altered more than 0.5 unit outside of the natural conditions. Natural daily and seasonal pH fluctuations shall be maintained. The effluent pH should be within the range of 6.0 to 9.0.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Discharges of substances are not permitted that alone or in combination with other materials present are toxic to fish and other aquatic life, including wild rice, wildlife, trout, lake sturgeon, and other species.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Effluent limitations. Publicly owned treatment works and privately owned domestic sewage treatment works, which are facilities that treat domestic wastewater, shall meet as a minimum the effluent limits specified:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Where the receiving water consists of cold water communities, warm water sport fish communities, and warm water forage fish communities:</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>The following effluent limits for BOD5 apply:</text>
              <para>
                <num>[a]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average may not exceed 30 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[b]</num>
                <text>The seven-day average may not exceed 45 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[c]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average percent removal may not be less than 85%.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>The following effluent limits for SS apply:</text>
              <para>
                <num>[a]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average may not exceed 30 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[b]</num>
                <text>The seven-day average may not exceed 45 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[c]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average percent removal may not be less than 85%.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[3]</num>
              <text>The effluent pH shall be within the range of 6.0 to 9.0.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[4]</num>
              <text>Upon request by the permittee, the Department may substitute the parameter CBOD5 for the parameter BOD5 and the following effluent quality levels of CBOD5 shall be applicable:</text>
              <para>
                <num>[a]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average may not exceed 25 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[b]</num>
                <text>The seven-day average may not exceed 40 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[c]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average percent removal may not be less than 85%.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[5]</num>
              <text>More stringent effluent limitations than those specified may be imposed for any pollutant where necessary to meet water quality standards for water receiving the treated discharge.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Where the receiving water is only capable of supporting limited communities of forage fish and other aquatic life:</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>The following effluent limits for BOD5 apply:</text>
              <para>
                <num>[a]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average may not exceed 15 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[b]</num>
                <text>The daily maximum may not exceed 30 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[c]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average percent removal may not be less than 85%.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>The following effluent limits for SS apply:</text>
              <para>
                <num>[a]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average may not exceed 20 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[b]</num>
                <text>The daily maximum may not exceed 30 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[c]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average percent removal may not be less than 85%.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[3]</num>
              <text>The following effluent limits for NH3 -N apply:</text>
              <para>
                <num>[a]</num>
                <text>The seven-day average may not exceed 3.0 mg/l from May 1 through October 31.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[b]</num>
                <text>The seven-day average may not exceed 6.0 mg/l from November 1 through April 30.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[4]</num>
              <text>The effluent pH shall be within the range of 6.0 to 9.0.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[5]</num>
              <text>The daily minimum effluent dissolved oxygen level shall be 4.0 mg/l.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[6]</num>
              <text>Upon request by the permittee, the Department may substitute the parameter CBOD5 for the parameter BOD5 and the following effluent quality levels of CBOD5 shall be applicable:</text>
              <para>
                <num>[a]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average may not exceed 12 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[b]</num>
                <text>The daily maximum may not exceed 25 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[c]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average percent removal may not be less than 85%.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[7]</num>
              <text>More stringent effluent limitations than those specified may be imposed for any pollutant where necessary to meet water quality standards for water receiving the treated discharge.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Where the receiving quality or habitat severely limits the capability to support communities of aquatic life due to natural circumstances:</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>The following effluent limits for BOD5 apply:</text>
              <para>
                <num>[a]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average may not exceed 20 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[b]</num>
                <text>The seven-day average may not exceed 30 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[c]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average percent removal may not be less than 85%.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>The following effluent limits for SS apply:</text>
              <para>
                <num>[a]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average may not exceed 20 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[b]</num>
                <text>The seven-day average may not exceed 30 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[c]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average percent removal may not be less than 85%.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[3]</num>
              <text>The effluent pH shall be within the range of 6.0 to 9.0.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[4]</num>
              <text>The daily minimum effluent dissolved oxygen level shall be 4.0 mg/l.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[5]</num>
              <text>Upon request by the permittee, the Department may substitute the parameter CBOD5 for the parameter BOD5 and the following effluent quality levels of CBOD5 shall be applicable:</text>
              <para>
                <num>[a]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average may not exceed 25 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[b]</num>
                <text>The seven-day average may not exceed 40 mg/l.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[c]</num>
                <text>The thirty-day average percent removal may not be less than 85%.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[6]</num>
              <text>More stringent effluent limitations than those specified may be imposed for any pollutant where necessary to meet water quality standards for water receiving the treated discharge.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Where it is determined by the Department that one or more factors in <cite path="§512-20|A|(5)(a)">Subsection A(5)(a)</cite> to (c) may interfere with the objectives and requirements of <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite>, a variance from the criteria may be considered by the Department, provided that existing uses of the receiving waters are protected and maintained. Certain waters of the Tribe may not be capable of providing viable habitat for propagation of fish, shellfish, wildlife, recreation in and on the water, or other uses because of:</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>The presence of in-place pollutants;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>Low natural stream flow;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[3]</num>
              <text>Natural background conditions; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[4]</num>
              <text>Irretrievable cultural alterations.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Recreational use protection.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Recreational water fecal coliform density from the last five successive sets of samples collected on five different days within a thirty-day period shall not exceed a geometric mean of 300 per 100 milliliters (ml) nor shall the fecal coliform density of any sample exceed 1,000 per 100 milliliters. When it is determined that recreational water must be closed, daily samples shall be collected and analyzed during the period of closure. The recreational water may be reopened if the fecal coliform density in two consecutive daily samples is less than 200 per 100 milliliters.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The EPA has suggested that E. coli or enterococci organisms shall be used in addition to fecal coliform as indicators of the water quality fully supporting recreational uses. A geometric mean of five samples should not exceed 126 E. coli organisms per 100 milliliters or 33 enterococci organisms per 100 milliliters. A single sample should not exceed 235 E. coli or 61 enterococci organisms per 100 milliliters.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>If contamination is indicated by the criteria in <cite path="§512-20|B|(1)">Subsection B(1)</cite> or (2), water samples should be analyzed for fecal streptococcus and staphylococcus to aid in identifying the source of contamination. If there is evidence of complaints of eye, ear, nose, throat, or skin irritation, the water should be analyzed for otitis externs. The Menominee Tribe/Indian Health Service sanitary survey should also be considered.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Cultural use and ceremonial, religious, and spiritual use protection.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Natural characteristics of waters of the Reservation necessary for the protection of Menominee cultural, ceremonial, religious, and spiritual uses of waters shall be maintained and protected. These characteristics shall include but not be limited to water quality, water quantity, other hydrologic and hydraulic factors, and (existing) biological/ecological communities. Especially significant are water factors related to, or that may adversely affect, the existence of wild rice and sturgeon populations within the waters of the Reservation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Waters of the Reservation shall be maintained and protected in such an ecological condition that will allow (traditional) Menominee educational uses associated with waters of the Reservation to continue perpetually. Cultural education uses shall include, but not be limited to, ethnohydrological learning experiences that are passed from one generation to the next regarding the harvest of plants and animals. Certain cultural, ceremonial, religious, and spiritual uses involve primary direct contact with water; therefore, National Primary Drinking Water Standards shall apply. Additionally, waters of the Reservation shall be protected for public drinking water supply use.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Fish and wildlife habitat and natural food chain maintenance use protection.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Substances at levels that may damage fish and wildlife and their habitats, natural food chain maintenance, human health, designated uses and other values, e.g., human consumption of fish and wildlife, and may further result in restrictions on fish and wildlife consumption, or other impairment of uses, shall be prohibited. Substances capable of changing the chemical, physical, or biological integrity of the waters of the Reservation sufficient to cause any of the following are prohibited:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Restrictions on fish and wildlife consumption.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Tainting of fish and wildlife flavor.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Degradation of fish and wildlife populations.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Fish tumors or other deformities.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Bird or animal deformities or reproduction problems and/or bioaccumulation in these animals.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>Degradation of benthos.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text>Restrictions on dredging activities and contributions to the need for the same.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text>Eutrophication or undesirable algae.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Restrictions on drinking water consumption or taste and odor problems.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(j)</num>
            <text>Beach closings or other recreational impairments.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(k)</num>
            <text>Degradation of aesthetics.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(l)</num>
            <text>Added costs to agriculture, forestry, or industry.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(m)</num>
            <text>Degradation of phytoplankton and zooplankton populations.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(n)</num>
            <text>Loss of fish and wildlife habitat.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Furthermore, the quality of waters capable of supporting wild rice shall be of sufficient quantity and quality as to permit the propagation and maintenance of healthy wild rice ecosystems in rivers, streams, creeks, and lakes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-21</num>
      <heading>Methods for deriving criteria.</heading>
      <text>Site-specific criteria may be developed by the Tribe, or required of an applicant, in order for the Department to adequately consider a discharge proposal. For waters within the Great Lakes basin, criteria shall be developed consistent with Appendix F to 40 CFR Part 132, March 23, 1995 (Site-Specific Modifications to Criteria and Values), and the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Aquatic life criteria. Refer to Appendix A to 40 CFR Part 132, March 23, 1995, for Great Lakes water quality initiative methodologies for developments aquatic life criteria and values.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Bioaccumulation factors. Refer to Appendix B to 40 CFR Part 132, March 23, 1995, for Great Lakes water quality initiative methodologies for deriving bioaccumulation factors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Human health criteria. Refer to Appendix C to 40 CFR Part 132, March 23, 1995, for Great Lakes water quality initiative methodologies for development of human health criteria and values.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Wildlife criteria. Refer to Appendix D to 40 CFR Part 132, March 23, 1995, for Great Lakes water quality initiative methodologies for development of wildlife criteria.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container cache:ref-path="II|512|VI">
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>VI</num>
    <heading>Antidegradation Policy</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-22</num>
      <heading>Policies.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Classification. All waters of the Reservation shall be designated either outstanding national resource waters (ONRW) or outstanding Menominee resource waters (OMRW). All waters of the Reservation, existing in-stream water uses, and the level of water quality and quantity necessary to protect the existing uses shall be maintained and protected.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Outstanding national resource waters (ONRW).</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The main stem of the Wolf River, from the north line of the Reservation downstream to the Highway M Bridge, shall be designated an outstanding national resource water (ONRW). Consistent with "zero discharge" provisions (PL 92-500, 1972, as amended) of the Clean Water Act, <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> requires that no new or increased discharges will be allowed to enter ONRWs. No existing discharge water shall enter ONRW designated waters of the Reservation without a tribal water permit. ONRWs shall be guaranteed unique high levels of protection.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The Tribe hereby designates such specified waters as outstanding national resource waters for the purpose of prohibiting the new or increased discharge of Lake Superior bioaccumulative substances of immediate concern from point sources in these areas.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Designation of outstanding Menominee resource waters (OMRW).</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>All waters of the Reservation not otherwise designated ONRW are considered high-quality waters classified as outstanding Menominee resource waters (OMRW). OMRWs shall not be degraded below their present water quality.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>No new or increased discharges shall be permitted within the drainage basins that affect waters of the Reservation, unless it is determined by the Department or the Tribal Legislature that the issuance of a tribal water permit for the discharge, and accompanying water quality degradation resulting from said discharge, will provide necessary social and economic benefits to the Tribe. The tribal procedures used for evaluating said discharge(s) can be found in this and other articles.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Implementation policy. Procedures described herein shall apply to discharges or loadings that enter ONRW or affect OMRW of the Reservation. Persons or entities currently engaging in discharges or loadings that enter ONRW designated waters of the Reservation shall obtain a tribal water permit within one year of enactment of <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite>. No new or increased discharges shall be allowed to enter ONRW designated waters of the Reservation. Persons or entities proposing new or increased discharges or loadings that will affect OMRW designated waters of the Reservation shall obtain a tribal water permit; furthermore, additional permits and certifications may be required before such activities can be undertaken. The following outlines general procedures the Tribe will use to evaluate the aforementioned activities:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The applicant must provide information describing the activities that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Currently result in discharge or loading that enters ONRW designated waters of the Reservation; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Might result in new or increased discharge or loadings that may affect OMRW designated waters of the Reservation.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The applicant must demonstrate that any existing, new, or increased discharge will provide specific economic and social developments and/or benefits necessary to the Tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The applicant must demonstrate that existing, new, or increased effluent will not interfere with or become injurious to any designated, existing, or other beneficial uses. Water quality necessary to support these uses shall be maintained and protected.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The applicant must submit detailed plans and descriptions of proposed resource management methods, pollution prevention, and technological and best management practices that will be implemented to manage and minimize impacts resulting from proposed activities.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>The applicant must obtain a tribal water permit. [Note: Additional permits and/or certifications may be required; for example, if a NPDES permit is required, additional compliance (over and above <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite>) with public notice and intergovernmental coordination requirements listed at 40 CFR Parts 25 and 29, and after due consideration of such technical, economic, social and other criteria as provided by Sections 301 and 302 of the CWA, 33 U.S.C. §§ 1311 and 1312, shall be met in order to allow lower water quality.]</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Where the quality of the waters exceeds levels necessary to support propagation of fish, shellfish, and wildlife and recreation in and on the water, that quality shall be maintained and protected unless the Tribe finds, after full satisfaction of the intergovernmental coordination and public participation provisions of the Tribe's continuing planning process, that allowing lower water quality is necessary to accommodate important economic or social development in the area in which the waters are located. In allowing such degradation or lower water quality, the Tribe shall assure water quality adequate to protect existing uses fully. Further, the Tribe shall assure that there shall be achieved the highest statutory and regulatory requirements for all new and existing point sources and all cost-effective and reasonable best management practices for nonpoint source control. In those cases where potential water quality impairment associated with a thermal discharge is involved, the antidegradation policy and implementation method shall be consistent with Section 316 of the Clean Water Act.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Outstanding national resource waters will not be subject to lowering of water quality for economic or social development purposes.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Consideration of any application must be consistent with Section 7(a) of the Wild and Scenic Rivers Act (16 U.S.C. § 1278).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-23</num>
      <heading>Antidegradation standard.</heading>
      <text>This antidegradation standard shall be applicable to any action or activity by any source, point or nonpoint, of pollutants that is anticipated to result in an increased loading of BCCs to surface waters of the Great Lakes system and for which independent regulatory authority exists requiring compliance with water quality standards. Pursuant to this standard:</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Existing in-stream water uses, as defined pursuant to 40 CFR 131, and the level of water quality necessary to protect existing uses shall be maintained and protected. Where designated uses of the water body are impaired, there shall be no lowering of the water quality with respect to the pollutant or pollutants which are causing the impairment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Where, for any parameter, the quality of the waters exceeds levels necessary to support the propagation of fish, shellfish, and wildlife and recreation in and on the waters, that water shall be considered high quality, and that quality shall be maintained and protected unless the Tribe finds, after full satisfaction of intergovernmental coordination and public participation provisions of the Tribe's continuing planning process, that allowing lower water quality is necessary to accommodate important economic or social development in the area in which the waters are located. In allowing such degradation, the Tribe shall assure water quality adequate to protect existing uses fully. Further, the Tribe shall assure that there shall be achieved the highest statutory and regulatory requirements for all new and existing point sources and all cost-effective and reasonable best management practices for nonpoint source control. The Tribe shall utilize the antidegradation implementation procedures adopted pursuant to the requirements of <cite path="|II|512|VI">this article</cite> in determining if any lowering of water quality will be allowed.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Where high-quality waters constitute an outstanding national resource, such as waters of parks and wildlife refuges and waters of exceptional recreational or ecological significance, that water quality shall be maintained and protected; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>In those cases where the potential lowering of water quality is associated with a thermal discharge, the decision to allow such degradation shall be consistent with Section 316 of the Clean Water Act (CWA).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§512-24">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-24</num>
      <heading>Antidegradation implementation procedures.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Definitions. In addition to definitions contained elsewhere in <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite>, the following shall apply: BCC — Bioaccumulative chemicals of concern; see Tables 5 and 6.<fn path="|II|§512-24|footnotes|7">7</fn></text>
        <text>CONTROL DOCUMENT — Any authorization issued by the Department or federal agency to any source of pollutants to waters under its jurisdiction that specifies conditions under which the source is allowed to operate.</text>
        <text>HIGH-QUALITY WATERS — Water bodies in which, on a parameter-by-parameter basis, the quality of the waters exceeds levels necessary to support propagation of fish, shellfish, and wildlife and recreation in and on the water.</text>
        <text>LAKE SUPERIOR BASIN — For the purposes of the MITW WQS, each of the references to "Lake Superior" and "Lake Superior basin" shall include Great Lakes tributary waters that also flow to Lake Michigan.</text>
        <text>LAKE SUPERIOR BASIN OUTSTANDING NATIONAL RESOURCE WATERS — Outstanding national resource waters and those waters designated as such by the Tribe consistent with the September 1991 Bi-National Program to Restore and Protect the Lake Superior Basin. The purpose of such designations shall be to prohibit new or increased discharges of Lake Superior bioaccumulative substances of immediate concern from point sources in these areas.</text>
        <text>LAKE SUPERIOR BIOACCUMULATIVE SUBSTANCES OF IMMEDIATE CONCERN — A list of substances identified in the September 1991 Bi-National Program to Restore and Protect the Lake Superior Basin. They include 2, 3, 7, 8-TCDD; octachlorostyrene; hexachlorobenzene; chlordane; DDT, DDE, and other metabolites; toxaphene; PCBs; and mercury. Other chemicals may be added to the list following the Tribe's assessment of environmental effects and impacts and after public review and comment.</text>
        <text>OUTSTANDING NATIONAL RESOURCE WATERS — Those waters designated as such by the Tribe. The Tribal designation shall describe the quality of such waters to serve as the benchmark of the water quality that shall be maintained and protected. Waters that may be considered for designation as outstanding national resource waters include but are not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Water bodies that are recognized as important because of protection through official action, such as federal or tribal law, presidential or secretarial action, international treaty, or interstate compact, due to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Having exceptional recreational significance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Having exceptional ecological significance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Having other special environmental, recreational, or ecological attributes; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Waters whose designation as outstanding national resource waters is reasonably necessary for the protection of other waters so designated.</text>
          <text>SIGNIFICANT LOWERING OF WATER QUALITY —</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A significant lowering of water quality occurs when there is a new or increased loading of any BCC from any regulated existing or new facility, either point source or nonpoint source, for which there is a control document or reviewable action, as a result of any activity, including but not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Construction of a new regulated facility or modification of an existing regulated facility such that a new or modified control document is required.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Modification of an existing regulated facility operating under a current control document such that the production capacity of the facility is increased.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Addition of a new source of untreated or pretreated effluent containing or expected to contain any BCC to an existing wastewater treatment works, whether public or private.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>A request for an increased limit in an applicable control document.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Other deliberate activities that, based on the information available, could be reasonably expected to result in an increased loading of any BCC to any waters of the Great Lakes system.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding the above, changes in loadings of any BCC within the existing capacity and processes and that are covered by the existing applicable control document are not subject to an antidegradation review. These changes include but are not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Normal operational variability;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Changes in intake water pollutants;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Increasing the production hours of the facility (e.g., adding a second shift); or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Increasing the rate of production.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The Director may exclude from an antidegradation review new effluent limits based on improved monitoring data or new water quality criteria or values that are not a result of changes in pollutant loading.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>For all waters, the Director shall ensure that the level of water quality necessary to protect existing uses is maintained. In order to achieve this requirement, and consistent with 40 CFR 131.10, water quality standards use designations must include all existing uses. Controls shall be established as necessary on point and nonpoint sources of pollutants to ensure that the criteria applicable to the designated use are achieved in the water and that any designated use of a downstream water is protected. Where water quality does not support the designated uses of a water body or ambient pollutant concentrations exceed water quality criteria applicable to that water body, the Director shall not allow a lowering of water quality for the pollutant or pollutants preventing the attainment of such uses or exceeding such criteria.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>For outstanding national resource waters:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Director shall ensure, through the application of appropriate controls on pollutant sources, that water quality is maintained and protected.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Exception. A short-term, temporary (i.e., weeks or months) lowering of water quality may be permitted by the Director.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>For high-quality waters, the Director shall ensure that no action resulting in a lowering of water quality occurs unless an antidegradation demonstration has been completed pursuant to <cite path="§512-25">§ 512-25</cite> of <cite path="|II|512|VI">this article</cite> and the information thus provided is determined by the Director pursuant to <cite path="§512-26">§ 512-26</cite> of <cite path="|II|512|VI">this article</cite> to adequately support the lowering of water quality.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The Director shall establish conditions in the control document applicable to the regulated facility that prohibit the regulated facility from undertaking any deliberate action, such that there would be an increase in the rate of mass loading of any BCC, unless an antidegradation demonstration is provided to the Director and approved pursuant to <cite path="§512-26">§ 512-26</cite> of <cite path="|II|512|VI">this article</cite> prior to commencement of the action. Imposition of limits due to improved monitoring data or new water quality criteria or values or changes in loadings of any BCC within the existing capacity and processes and that are covered by the existing applicable control document are not subject to an antidegradation review.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>For BCCs known or believed to be present in a discharge, from a point or nonpoint source, a monitoring requirement shall be included in the control document. The control document shall also include a provision requiring the source to notify the Director of any increased loadings. Upon notification, the Director shall require actions as necessary to reduce or eliminate the increased loading.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Exemptions. Except as the Director may determine on a case-by-case basis that the application of these procedures is required to adequately protect water quality, or as the affected water body is an outstanding national resource water as defined in this section, the procedures in this definition do not apply to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Short-term, temporary (i.e., weeks or months) lowering of water quality;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Bypasses that are not prohibited at 40 CFR 122.41(m); and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Response actions pursuant to the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation and Liability Act (CERCLA), as amended, or similar federal or tribal authorities, undertaken to alleviate a release into the environment of hazardous substances, pollutants or contaminants which may pose an imminent and substantial danger to public health or welfare.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>7</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Tables 5 and 6 are included at the end of <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-25</num>
      <heading>Antidegradation demonstration.</heading>
      <text>Any entity seeking to lower water quality in a high-quality water or create a new or increased discharge of Lake Superior bioaccumulative substances of immediate concern in a Reservation water must first, as required by <cite path="§512-24">§ 512-24</cite> of <cite path="|II|512|VI">this article</cite>, submit an antidegradation demonstration for consideration by the Director. The Tribe should tailor the level of detail and documentation in antidegradation reviews to the specific circumstances encountered. The antidegradation demonstration shall include the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Pollution prevention alternatives analysis. Identify any cost-effective pollution prevention alternatives and techniques that are available to the entity that would eliminate or significantly reduce the extent to which the increased loading results in a lowering of water quality.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Alternative or enhanced treatment analysis. Identify alternative or enhanced treatment techniques that are available to the entity that would eliminate the lowering of water quality and their costs relative to the cost of treatment necessary to achieve applicable effluent limitations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Lake Superior. For waters designated as outstanding national resource waters pursuant to <cite path="|II|512|VI">this article</cite>, any entity proposing a new or increased discharge of any Lake Superior bioaccumulative substance of immediate concern to the Lake Superior basin shall identify the best technology in process and treatment to eliminate or reduce the extent of the lowering of water quality. In this case, the requirements in <cite path="§512-25|B">Subsection B of this section</cite> do not apply.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Important social or economic development analysis. Identify the social or economic development and the benefits to the area in which the waters are located that will be foregone if the lowering of water quality is not allowed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Special provision for remedial actions. Entities proposing remedial actions pursuant to the CERCLA, as amended, corrective actions pursuant to the Resource Conservation and Recovery Act, as amended, or similar actions pursuant to other federal or tribal environmental statutes or ordinances may submit information to the Director that demonstrates that the action utilizes the most cost-effective pollution prevention and treatment techniques available and minimizes the necessary lowering of water quality, in lieu of the information required by <cite>Subsections B through D</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-26</num>
      <heading>Antidegradation decision.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Once the Director determines that the information provided by the entity proposing to increase loadings is administratively complete, the Director shall use that information to determine whether or not the lowering of water quality is necessary and, if it is necessary, whether or not the lowering of water quality will support important social and economic development in the area. If the proposed lowering of water quality is either not necessary or will not support important social and economic development, the Director shall deny the request to lower water quality. If the lowering of water quality is necessary and will support important social and economic development, the Director may allow all or part of the proposed lowering to occur as necessary to accommodate the important social and economic development. In no event may the decision reached under this section allow water quality to be lowered below the minimum level required to fully support existing and designated uses. The decision of the Director shall be subject to the public participation requirements of 40 CFR 25.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>For water bodies classified as outstanding national resource waters pursuant to <cite path="|II|512|VI">this article</cite>, any entity requesting to lower water quality in Reservation waters as a result of the new or increased discharge of any Lake Superior bioaccumulative substance of immediate concern shall be required to install and utilize the best technology in process and treatment as identified by the Director.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-27</num>
      <heading>Implementation procedures.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Procedure 1: Site-specific modification to criteria and values.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Requirements for site-specific modification to criteria and values. Criteria and values may be modified on a site-specific basis to reflect local environmental conditions as restricted by the following provisions. Any such modifications must be protective of designated uses and aquatic life, wildlife or human health and be submitted to EPA for approval. In addition, any site-specific modifications that result in less stringent criteria must be based on a sound scientific rationale and shall not be likely to jeopardize the continued existence of endangered or threatened species listed or proposed under Section 4 of the Endangered Species Act (ESA) or result in the destruction or adverse modification of such species' critical habitat. More stringent modifications shall be developed to protect endangered or threatened species listed or proposed under Section 4 of the ESA, where such modifications are necessary to ensure that water quality is not likely to jeopardize the continued existence of such species or result in the destruction or adverse modification of such species' critical habitat. More stringent modifications may also be developed to protect candidate (C1) species being considered by the United States Fish and Wildlife Service (FWS) for listing under Section 4 of the ESA, where such modifications are necessary to protect such species. All site-specific modifications are applicable to aquatic life, wildlife, and human health criteria.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The Department shall incorporate a water-quality-based effluent limitation (WQBEL) in a NPDES permit for the discharge of pollutants described in <cite path="§512-27|A|(1)">Subsection A(1)</cite> in accordance with Procedure 1, Appendix F to 40 CFR Part 132, March 23, 1995, Great Lakes Water Quality Initiative.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Procedure 2: Variances from water quality standards for point sources.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Applicability. The Tribe may grant a variance to a WQS which is the basis of a water quality based effluent limitation included in a National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System (NPDES) permit. A WQS variance applies only to the permittee requesting the variance and only to the pollutant or pollutants specified in the variance. A variance does not affect, or require the Tribe to modify, the corresponding water quality standard for the water body as a whole.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The Tribe's procedure for considering and granting a variance from water quality standards for point sources shall be implemented according to the following reference document: refer to Procedure 2, Appendix F to 40 CFR Part 132, March 23, 1995, Great Lakes Water Quality Initiative.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Procedure 3: Total maximum daily loads, waste load allocations for point sources, load allocations for nonpoint sources, waste load allocations in the absence of a TMDL, and preliminary waste load allocations for purposes of determining the need for water-quality-based effluent limits. The Tribe herein adopts the provisions of Procedure 3, Appendix F to 40 CFR Part 132, March 23, 1995, Great Lakes Water Quality Initiative, for the purpose of developing total maximum daily loads (TMDLs), waste load allocations (WLAs) in the absence of TMDLs, and preliminary waste load allocations for purposes of determining the need for water-quality-based effluent limits (WQBELs), except as specifically provided in accordance with said reference.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Procedure 4: Additivity. The Tribe herein adopts provisions to protect human health from the potential adverse additive effects from both the noncarcinogenic and carcinogenic components of chemical mixtures in effluents utilizing procedures found in Procedure 4, Appendix F to 40 CFR Part 132, March 23, 1995, Great Lakes Water Quality Initiative.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Procedure 5: Reasonable potential to exceed water quality standards.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>If the Department determines that a pollutant is or may be discharged into the Great Lakes system at a level which will cause, have the reasonable potential to cause, or contribute to an deviation above any Tier I criterion or Tier II value, the Department shall incorporate a water-quality-based effluent limitation (WQBEL) in a NPDES permit for the discharge of that pollutant. When facility-specific effluent monitoring data is available, the permitting authority shall make this determination by developing preliminary effluent limitations (PEL) and comparing those effluent limitations to the projected effluent quality (PEQ) of the discharge in accordance with the following procedures. In all cases, the permitting authority shall use any valid, relevant, representative information that indicates a reasonable potential to exceed any Tier I criterion or Tier II value.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The Department shall incorporate a water-quality-based effluent limitation (WQBEL) in a NPDES permit for the discharge of pollutants described in <cite path="§512-27|E|(1)">Subsection E(1)</cite> in accordance with Procedure 5, Appendix F to 40 CFR Part 132, March 23, 1995, Great Lakes Water Quality Initiative.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>F.</num>
        <text>Procedure 6: Whole effluent toxicity requirements. The Tribe herein adopts whole effluent toxicity provisions in accordance with Procedure 6, Appendix F to 40 CFR Part 132, March 23, 1995, Great Lakes Water Quality Initiative, including definitions contained in said reference.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>G.</num>
        <text>Procedure 7: Loading limits. Whenever a water-quality-based effluent limitation (WQBEL) is developed, the WQBEL shall be expressed as both a concentration value and a corresponding mass loading rate.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Both mass and concentration limits shall be based on the same permit averaging periods, such as daily, weekly, or monthly averages, or in other appropriate permit averaging periods.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The mass loading rates shall be calculated using effluent flow rates that are consistent with those used in establishing the WQBELs expressed in concentration.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>H.</num>
        <text>Procedure 8: Water-quality-based effluent limitations below the quantification level. When a water-quality-based effluent limitation (WQBEL) for a pollutant is calculated to be less than the quantification level:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Permit limits. The Department shall designate as the limit in the NPDES permit the WQBEL exactly as calculated.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Analytical method and quantification level.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The permitting authority shall specify in the permit the most sensitive, applicable analytical method specified in or approved under 40 CFR Part 136, or other appropriate method if one is not available under 40 CFR Part 136, to be used to monitor for the presence and amount in an effluent of the pollutant for which the WQBEL is established and shall specify in accordance with <cite path="§512-27|H|(2)(b)">Subsection H(2)(b)</cite> of this procedure the quantification level that can be achieved by use of the specified analytical method.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The quantification level shall be the minimum level (ML) specified in or approved under 40 CFR Part 136 for the method for that pollutant. If no such ML exists, or if the method is not specified or approved under 40 CFR Part 136, the quantification level shall be the lowest quantifiable level practicable. The permitting authority may specify a higher quantification level if the permittee demonstrates that a higher quantification level is appropriate because of effluent-specific matrix interference.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The permit shall state that, for the purpose of compliance assessment, the analytical method specified in the permit shall be used to monitor the amount of pollutant in an effluent down to the quantification level, provided that the analyst has complied with the specified quality assurance/quality control procedures in the relevant method.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The permitting authority shall use applicable tribal procedures to average and account for monitoring data. The permitting authority may specify in the permit the value to be used to interpret sample values below the quantification level.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Special conditions. The permit shall contain a reopener clause authorizing modification or revocation and reissuance of the permit if new information generated as a result of special conditions included in the permit indicates that presence of the pollutant in the discharge at levels above the WQBEL. Special conditions that may be included in the permit include, but are not limited to, fish tissue sampling, whole effluent toxicity (WET) tests, limits and/or monitoring requirements on internal waste streams, and monitoring for surrogate parameters. Data generated as a result of special conditions can be used to reopen the permit to establish more stringent effluent limits or conditions, if necessary.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Pollutant minimization program. The permitting authority shall include a condition in the permit requiring the permittee to develop and conduct a pollutant minimization program for each pollutant with a WQBEL below the quantification level. The goal of the pollutant minimization program shall be to maintain the effluent at or below the WQBEL. In addition, The Department may consider cost-effectiveness when evaluating the requirements of a PMP. The pollutant minimization program shall include, but is not limited to, the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>An annual review and semiannual monitoring of potential sources of the pollutant, which may include fish tissue monitoring and other bio-uptake sampling;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Quarterly monitoring for the pollutant in the influent to the wastewater treatment system;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Submittal of a control strategy designed to proceed toward the goal of maintaining the effluent below the WQBEL;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Implementation of appropriate, cost-effective control measures consistent with the control strategy; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>An annual status report that shall be sent to the permitting authority, including:</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>All minimization program monitoring results for the previous year;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>A list of potential sources of the pollutant; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[3]</num>
              <text>A summary of all action undertaken pursuant to the control strategy.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Any information generated as a result of <cite path="§512-27|H|(4)">Subsection H(4)</cite> can be used to support a request for subsequent permit modifications, including revisions to (e.g., more or less frequent monitoring), or removal of the requirements of <cite path="§512-27|H|(4)">Subsection H(4)</cite>, consistent with 40 CFR 122.44, 122.62 and 122.63.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Procedure 9: Compliance schedules.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Limitations for new Great Lakes dischargers. When a permit issued on or after March 23, 1997, to a new Great Lakes discharger (defined in 40 CFR 132.2) contains a water-quality-based effluent limitation (WQBEL), the permittee shall comply with such a limitation upon the commencement of the discharge.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Limitations for existing Great Lakes dischargers.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Any existing permit that is reissued or modified on or after March 23, 1997, to contain a new or more restrictive WQBEL may allow a reasonable period of time, up to five years from the date of permit issuance or modification, for the permittee to comply with that limit, provided that the Tier I criterion or whole effluent toxicity (WET) criterion was adopted (or, in the case of a narrative criterion, Tier II value, or Tier I criterion derived pursuant to the methodology in Appendix A of Part 132, was newly derived) after July 1, 1977.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>When the compliance schedule established under <cite path="§512-27|I|(2)(a)">Subsection I(2)(a)</cite> goes beyond the term of the permit, an interim permit limit effective upon the expiration date shall be included in the permit and addressed in the permit's fact sheet or statement of basis. The administrative record for the permit shall reflect the final limit and its compliance date.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>If a permit establishes a schedule of compliance under <cite path="§512-27|I|(2)(a)">Subsection I(2)(a)</cite> which exceeds one year from the date of permit issuance or modification, the schedule shall set forth interim requirements and dates for their achievement. The time between such interim dates may not exceed one year. If the time necessary for completion of any interim requirement is more than one year and is not readily divisible into stages for completion, the permit shall require, at a minimum, specified dates for annual submission of progress reports on the status of any interim requirements.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Delayed effectiveness of Tier II limitations for existing Great Lakes discharges.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Whenever a limit (calculated in accordance with Procedure 3) based upon a Tier II value is included in a reissued or modified permit for an existing Great Lakes discharger, the permit may provide a reasonable period of time, up to two years, in which to provide additional studies necessary to develop a Tier I criterion or to modify the Tier II value. In such cases, the permit shall require compliance with the Tier II limitation within a reasonable period of time, no later than five years after permit issuance or modification, and contain a reopener clause.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The reopener clause shall authorize permit modifications if specified studies have been completed by the permittee or provided by a third party during the time allowed to conduct the specified studies and the permittee or a third party demonstrates, through such studies, that a revised limit is appropriate. Such a revised limit shall be incorporated through a permit modification and a reasonable time period, up to five years, shall be allowed for compliance. If incorporated prior to the compliance date of the original Tier II limitation, any such revised limit shall not be considered less stringent for purposes of the antibacksliding provisions of Section 402(o) of the Clean Water Act.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>If the specified studies have been completed and do not demonstrate that a revised limit is appropriate, the permitting authority may provide a reasonable additional period of time, not to exceed five years, with which to achieve compliance with the original effluent limitation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Where a permit is modified to include new or more stringent limitations, on a date within five years of the permit expiration date, such compliance schedules may extend beyond the term of a permit consistent with <cite path="§512-27|H|(2)(b)">Subsection H(2)(b)</cite> of this procedure.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>If future studies [other than those conducted under <cite path="§512-27|I|(3)(a)">Subsection I(3)(a)</cite>, (b) or (c) above] result in a Tier II value being changed to a less stringent Tier II value or Tier I criterion, after the effective date of a Tier II based limit, the existing Tier II based limit may be revised to be less stringent if:</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>It complies with Section 402(o)(2) and (3) of the CWA;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>In nonattainment waters, where the existing Tier II limit was based on Procedure 3, the cumulative effect of revised effluent limitation based on <cite path="§512-27|I|(3)(c)">Subsection I(3)(c)</cite> above will assure compliance with water quality standards; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[3]</num>
              <text>In attained waters, the revised effluent limitation complies with the Tribe's antidegradation policy and procedures.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container cache:ref-path="II|512|VII">
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>VII</num>
    <heading>Nonpoint Source Water Pollution Control; Stormwater General Permit</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-28</num>
      <heading>Purpose.</heading>
      <text><cite path="|II|512|VII">This article</cite> provides requirements for a permit to discharge stormwater resulting from construction and nonconstruction activity.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-29</num>
      <heading>Applicability.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>As of March 10, 2003, all construction and nonconstruction activity resulting in a discharge of stormwater to a river, lake, or wetland of the Menominee Indian Reservation shall require a permit.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Section 402(p)(2)(B) of the 1987 CWA requires NPDES permits for stormwater discharges associated with industrial activity. On November 16, 1990, the EPA published Phase I of the national stormwater regulations. Sources regulated under Phase I include discharges from municipal separate storm sewer systems with populations of generally 100,000 or more and 11 categories of industrial activity. The EPA has defined stormwater discharges associated with industrial activity to include stormwater discharges from construction sites which disturb five or more acres [see 40 CFR 122.26(b)(14)(x)].</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>On December 8, 1999, the EPA published Phase II of the national stormwater regulations. Phase II regulates stormwater discharges from small municipal separate storm sewer systems and discharges associated with small construction activity, including construction sites which disturb between one and five acres [40 CFR 122.26(b)(15)(i)]. This permit addresses construction sites regulated under both the Phase I and Phase II rules. However, the requirements for small construction sites will not be effective until March 10, 2003, the date by which these sources are to comply with the Phase II stormwater regulations.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Stormwater general permit for discharges from construction activities. Construction sites exposed to stormwater runoff (rainfall and snowmelt) can result in soil erosion and off-site transport of sediment, particularly if these sites are not properly managed through implementation and maintenance of sound erosion and sediment control practices. In addition, if construction sites are not properly managed, other construction-related wastes can be discharged in stormwater.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The stormwater general permit covers the Menominee Indian Reservation for all stormwater discharges from construction sites which disturb five or more acres.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The stormwater general permit covers the Menominee Indian Reservation for all stormwater discharges from small municipal separate storm sewer systems and discharges associated with small construction activity, including construction sites which disturb between one and five acres.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Permit application procedures for construction-related stormwater discharges shall be followed in accordance with <cite path="§512-30">§ 512-30</cite> of <cite path="|II|512|VII">this article</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Stormwater discharge permit for nonconstruction activity. Prior to October 1, 1994, discharges composed entirely of stormwater shall not be required to obtain a stormwater discharge permit except:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A discharge with respect to which a permit has been issued prior to February 4, 1987.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A discharge associated with industrial activity.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Nonmunicipal separate storm sewers. For stormwater discharges associated with industrial activity from point sources which discharge through a nonmunicipal or nonpublicly owned separate storm sewer system, the Director may issue a single stormwater permit, with each discharger a co-permittee to a permit issued to the operator of the portion of the system that discharges into waters of the United States, or individual permits to each discharger of stormwater associated with industrial activity through the nonmunicipal conveyance system.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>All stormwater discharges from industrial activity that discharge through a stormwater discharge system that is not a municipal separate storm sewer must be covered by an individual permit, or a permit issued to the operator of the portion of the system that discharges to waters of the United States, with each discharger to the nonmunicipal conveyance a co-permittee to that permit.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Where there is more than one operator of a single system of such conveyances, all operators of stormwater discharges associated with industrial activity must submit applications.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Any permit covering more than one operator shall identify the effluent limitations or other permit conditions, if any, that apply to each operator.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>A permit must be obtained for discharges composed entirely of stormwater on and after October 1, 1994. Operators shall be required to obtain a NPDES permit only if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The discharge is from a small municipal separate storm sewer system (MS4), all separate storm sewers that are owned or operated by the United States, a state, city, town, borough, county, parish, district, association, or other public body having jurisdiction over disposal of sewage, industrial wastes, stormwater, or other wastes, including special districts under state or tribal law, such as a sewer district, flood control district or drainage district, or similar entity, or an Indian tribe or an authorized Indian tribal organization, or a designated and approved management agency that discharges to waters of the United States, required to be regulated. Operators of small MS4s shall seek coverage under a NPDES permit in accordance with 40 CFR 122.33 through 122.35;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The discharge is a stormwater discharge associated with small construction activity; see <cite path="§512-29|B|(2)">Subsection B(2)</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The Director determines that stormwater controls are needed for the discharge based on waste load allocations that are part of total maximum daily loads (TMDLs) that address the pollutant(s) of concern; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The Director determines that the discharge or category of discharges within a geographic area contributes to a violation of a water quality standard or is a significant contributor of pollutants to waters of the United States.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§512-30">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-30</num>
      <heading>Stormwater pollution prevention plans; permit conditions; endangered species.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Stormwater pollution prevention plans. At least one stormwater pollution prevention plan (SWPPP) shall be developed for each construction project or site. Stormwater pollution prevention plans shall be prepared in accordance with good engineering practices. The SWPPP shall identify potential sources of pollution which may reasonably be expected to affect the quality of stormwater discharges from the construction site. The SWPPP shall describe and ensure the implementation of practices which will be used to reduce the pollutants in stormwater discharges associated with construction activity at the construction site and assure compliance with the terms and conditions of the permit. When developing a SWPPP, applicants must follow the procedures in <cite path="§512-30|E">Subsection E</cite> to determine whether listed endangered or threatened species or critical habitat would be affected by the applicant's stormwater discharges or stormwater-discharge-related activities. The SWPPP must also address historic properties.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Contents of plan. The stormwater pollution prevention plan (SWPPP) shall include the following items:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>A description of the site and the nature of the construction activity;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>A description of the intended sequence of major activities which disturb soils for major portions of the site (e.g., grubbing, excavation, or grading);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Estimates of the total area of the site and the total area of the site that is expected to be disturbed by excavation, grading, or other activities, including off-site borrow and fill areas;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Estimates, including calculations, if any, of the runoff coefficient of the site before and after construction activities are completed;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Existing data describing the surface soils as well as subsoils from United States Natural Resources Conservation Service information; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>The name of the receiving water(s) from United States Geological Service 7.5 minute series topographical maps or other appropriate source.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Each site map shall include a map showing the following items:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Existing topography and drainage patterns, roads and surface waters;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Boundaries of the construction site;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Drainage patterns and approximate slopes anticipated after major grading activities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Areas of soil disturbance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Locations of major structural and nonstructural controls identified in the SWPPP;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Locations where stabilization practices will be employed;</text>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Areas which will be vegetated following construction;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Wetlands and area extent of wetland acreage on the site and locations where stormwater is discharged to a surface water or wetland;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Information on whether listed endangered or threatened species or critical habitats are found in proximity to the construction activity and whether such species may be affected by the applicant's stormwater discharges or stormwater-discharge-related activities; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Information on whether listed historic properties are found on the site and how to address the applicant's stormwater discharges or stormwater-discharge-related activities.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Each SWPPP shall include a description of appropriate controls and measures (i.e., best management practices) that will be implemented at the site to prevent pollutants in stormwater discharges from reaching waters of the United States. The description of erosion controls shall include, when appropriate, the following minimum requirements:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Description of interim and permanent stabilization practices, including a schedule for implementing the practices. Site plans shall ensure that existing vegetation is preserved where attainable and that disturbed portions of the site are stabilized;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Description of structural practices to divert flow away from exposed soils, store flows or otherwise limit runoff and the discharge of pollutants from the site;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Management of overland flow at all sites, unless otherwise controlled by outfall controls;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Trapping of sediment in channelized flow;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Staging construction to limit bare areas subject to erosion;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>Protection of downslope drainage inlets where they occur;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text>Minimization of tracking at all sites;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text>Cleanup of off-site sediment deposits;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(i)</num>
            <text>Proper disposal of building and waste materials at all sites;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(j)</num>
            <text>Stabilization of drainageways;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(k)</num>
            <text>Installation of permanent stabilization practices as soon as possible after final grading; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(l)</num>
            <text>Minimization of dust to the maximum extent practicable.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>No solid materials, including building materials, may be discharged in violation of applicable laws.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Velocity dissipation devices shall be placed at discharge locations and along the length of any outfall channel to provide a nonerosive flow velocity from the structure to a watercourse so that the natural physical and biological characteristics and functions are maintained and protected (e.g., no significant changes in the hydrological regime of the receiving water).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>The Director may, upon request of a permittee or upon finding of just cause, grant modifications to the compliance and reporting schedules or any requirements of a stormwater discharge permit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>All erosion and sediment control measures and other protective measures identified in the SWPPP must be maintained in effective operating condition.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>The SWPPP shall clearly identify the contractor(s) and subcontractor(s) that will install and maintain erosion control and stormwater management measures.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Stormwater management plan requirements. Pollution caused by stormwater discharges from the site after construction is completed, including but not limited to rooftops, parking lots, roadways and the maintenance of grassed areas, shall be addressed by a stormwater management plan. Such plans shall be a requirement of any stormwater individual permit and for stormwater general permits for discharges related to nonconstruction activity.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Practices during construction. The plan shall include a description of management practices that will be installed during the construction process to control peak flow, pollutants and runoff volume that will occur after construction operations have been completed. Stormwater management practices shall be in accordance with applicable federal and tribal regulations. To the extent feasible, the plan shall consider efforts to increase on-site infiltration through conveyance, depression storage and reduction of impervious areas.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Long-term practices. For any permanent structures, provisions shall be made for long-term maintenance. Long-term maintenance provisions for stormwater management structures should be made with the Tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Management practices. Stormwater management practices to control impacts from runoff volume and pollutants may include, but are not limited to, infiltration systems, flow attenuation, constructed wetlands, temporary or permanent ponds, combinations of these practices, or other methods which do not cause significant adverse impact on the receiving water or groundwater.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Retention of records.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Documents. The permittee shall retain copies of all reports required by the permit, and records of all data used to complete the notice of intent to be covered by the permit, for a period of at least three years from the date that the site is finally stabilized. This period may be extended by request of the Director at any time.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Accessibility. The permittee shall retain a copy of the stormwater pollution prevention plan and the stormwater management plan required by this permit (including a copy of the permit language) at the construction site (or other local location accessible to the Director or tribal agency approving sediment and erosion plans, grading plans, or stormwater management plans or the operator of a municipal separate storm sewer receiving discharges from the site) from the date of project initiation to the date of final stabilization.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Standard permit conditions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Continuation of the expired general permit. If this permit is not reissued or replaced prior to the expiration date, it will be administratively continued in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act<fn path="|II|§512-30|footnotes|8">8</fn> and remain in force and effect. Any permittee who was granted permit coverage prior to the expiration date will automatically remain covered by the continued permit until the earlier of:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Reissuance or replacement of this permit, at which time the permittee must comply with the notice of intent conditions of the new permit to maintain authorization to discharge;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The permittee's submittal of a notice of termination;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Issuance of an individual permit for the permittee's discharges; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>A formal permit decision by the Director not to reissue this general permit, at which time the permittee must seek coverage under an alternative general permit or an individual permit.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Duty to mitigate. The permittee shall take all reasonable steps to minimize or prevent any discharge in violation of this permit that has a reasonable likelihood of adversely affecting human health or the environment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Duty to provide information. The permittee shall furnish to the Director or an authorized representative of the Director any information that is requested to determine compliance with this permit or other information.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Oil and hazardous substance liability. Nothing in this permit shall be construed to preclude the institution of any legal action or relieve the permittee from any responsibilities, liabilities, or penalties to which the permittee is or may be subject under Section 311 of the CWA or Section 106 of the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation and Liability Act of 1980 (CERCLA).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Tribal environmental laws.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Nothing in this permit shall be construed to preclude the institution of any legal action or relieve the permittee from any responsibilities, liabilities, or penalties established pursuant to any applicable federal or tribal law or regulation under authority preserved by Section 518 of the Act.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>No condition of this permit shall release the permittee from any responsibility or requirements under other environmental statutes or regulations or ordinances.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Inspection and entry. The permittee shall allow the Director or an authorized representative of the EPA, or an authorized representative of the Tribe, and, where appropriate, in the case of a construction site which discharges through a municipal separate storm sewer, an authorized representative of the municipal owner/operator of the separate storm sewer receiving the discharge, upon the presentation of credentials and other documents as may be required by law, to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Enter upon the permittee's premises where a regulated facility or activity is located or conducted or where records must be kept under the conditions of this permit;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Have access to and copy at reasonable times any records that must be kept under the conditions of this permit; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Inspect at reasonable times any facilities or equipment (including monitoring and control equipment).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Permit actions. This permit may be modified, revoked and reissued, or terminated for cause. The filing of a request by the permittee for a permit modification, revocation and reissuance, or termination or a notification of planned changes or anticipated noncompliance does not stay any permit condition.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Endangered species. To receive coverage under this general permit, applicants must assess the potential effects of their stormwater discharges and stormwater-discharge-related activities on listed species and their critical habitat. To make this assessment, applicants must follow the steps outlined below prior to completing and submitting the notice of intent (NOI) form:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Determine if the construction site is found within designated critical habitat for listed species.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Determine if listed species are located in the county(ies) where the construction activity will occur.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Determine if any federally listed endangered and threatened species may be present in the project area.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Determine if listed species or critical habitats are likely to be adversely affected by the construction activity's stormwater discharges or stormwater-discharge-related activities.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Determine if measures can be implemented to avoid any adverse effects.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Determine if the eligibility requirements can be met as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The stormwater discharges and stormwater-discharge-related activities are not likely to adversely affect listed species or critical habitat;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Formal or informal consultation with the Fish and Wildlife Service (and/or the National Marine Fisheries Service) under Section 7 of the Endangered Species Act (ESA) has been concluded which addresses the effects of the applicant's stormwater discharges and stormwater-discharge-related activities on listed species and critical habitat and the consultation results in either a no jeopardy opinion or a written concurrence by the Service(s) on a finding that the applicant's stormwater discharges and stormwater-discharge-related activities are not likely to adversely affect listed species or critical habitat. A Section 7 consultation may occur in the context of another federal action [e.g., an ESA Section 7 consultation was performed for issuance of a wetlands dredge and fill permit for the project or as part of a National Environmental Policy Act (NEPA) review];</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>The applicant's construction activities are authorized under Section 10 of the ESA and that authorization addresses the effects of the applicant's stormwater discharges and stormwater-discharge-related activities on listed species and critical habitat; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The applicant's stormwater discharges and stormwater-discharge-related activities were already addressed in another operator's certification of eligibility that included the applicant's project area. By certifying eligibility the applicant agrees to comply with any measures or controls upon which the other operator's certification was based.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>8</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: See <cite path="|I|12">Ch. 12</cite>, Administrative Procedures, of this Code.</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-31</num>
      <heading>Application requirements.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Notice of intent (NOI) requirements for construction activity.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Deadlines for notification.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The operator(s) must submit a notice of intent (NOI) in accordance with the requirements at least two days prior to the commencement of construction activities (i.e., the initial disturbance of soils associated with clearing, grading, excavation activities, or other land disturbing activities).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Due to their day-to-day operational control over activities at a project, the operators must ensure compliance with a stormwater pollution prevention plan or other permit conditions (e.g., general contractor or erosion control contractor must submit an NOI at least two days prior to commencing work on site).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>For stormwater discharges from construction projects where the operator changes, including instances where an operator is added after an NOI has been submitted, the new operator must submit an NOI at least two days before assuming operational control over site specifications or commencing work on site.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Operators are not prohibited from submitting late NOI. When a late NOI is submitted, authorization is only for discharges that occur after permit coverage is granted. The Department reserves the right to take appropriate enforcement for any unpermitted activities that may have occurred between the time construction commenced and authorization of future discharges is granted (typically two days after a complete NOI is submitted).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Sources excluded from this general permit solely because they already have an individual permit may request that the individual permit be revoked and that it be covered by the general permit. Upon revocation of the individual permit, the general permit shall apply to the source.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Contents of NOI. The NOI form shall be signed and shall include the following information:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The name, address, and telephone number of the operator filing the NOI for permit coverage.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>An indication of whether the operator is a federal, tribal, private or other public entity.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The name (or other identifier), address, county, and latitude/longitude of the construction project or site.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>An indication of whether the project or site is located within Indian country.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Confirmation that a stormwater pollution prevention plan (SWPPP) has been developed prior to commencing construction activities. Copies of SWPPPs or permits should not be included with the NOI submission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Optional information: the location where the SWPPP may be viewed and the name and telephone number of a contact person for scheduling viewing times.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>The name of the receiving water(s).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Estimates of project start and completion dates and estimates of the number of acres of the site on which soil will be distributed (if less than one acre, enter "1").</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Based on the instructions in <cite path="§512-30|E">§ 512-30E</cite>, whether any listed or proposed threatened or endangered species, or designated critical habitats, are in proximity to the stormwater discharges or stormwater-discharge-related activities to be covered by this permit, and the applicant is certifying eligibility.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Where to submit. A NOI must be signed and sent to the following address:</text>
          <text class="center">Stormwater Notice of Intent Environmental Services Department Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin Menominee Forestry and Environmental Resources Center</text>
          <text>P.O. Box 670</text>
          <text class="center">Keshena, WI 54135</text>
          <text class="center">(715) 799-4937</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Notice of intent requirements for nonconstruction activity.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Operators of nonmunicipal sources shall seek coverage under a stormwater permit that requires:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>A site map showing topography [or indicating the outline of drainage areas served by the outfall(s) covered in the application if a topographic map is unavailable] of the facility, including each of its drainage and discharge structures; the drainage area of each stormwater outfall; paved areas and buildings within the drainage area of each stormwater outfall; each past or present area used for outdoor storage or disposal of significant materials; each existing structural control measure to reduce pollutants in stormwater runoff; each materials loading and access area; each area where pesticides, herbicides, soil conditioners and fertilizers are applied; each area used for hazardous waste treatment, storage or disposal facilities; each well where fluids from the facility are injected underground; and springs and other surface water bodies and wetlands which receive stormwater discharges from the facility.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>An estimate of the area of impervious surfaces (including paved areas and building roofs) and the total area drained by each outfall (within a mile radius of the facility) and a narrative description of the following: significant materials that in the three years prior to the submittal of this application have been treated, stored or disposed in a manner to allow exposure to stormwater; method of treatment, storage or disposal of such materials; materials management practices employed, in the three years prior to the submittal of this application, to minimize contact by these materials with stormwater runoff; materials loading and access areas; the location, manner and frequency in which pesticides, herbicides, soil conditioners and fertilizers are applied; the location and a description of existing structural and nonstructural control measures to reduce pollutants in stormwater runoff; and a description of the treatment the stormwater receives, including the ultimate disposal of any solid or fluid wastes other than by discharge.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>A certification that all outfalls that should contain stormwater discharges associated with industrial activity have been tested or evaluated for the presence of nonstormwater discharges which are not covered by a stormwater permit; tests for such nonstormwater discharges may include smoke tests, fluorometric dye tests, analysis of accurate schematics, as well as other appropriate tests. The certification shall include a description of the method used, the date of any testing, and the on-site drainage points that were directly observed during a test.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Existing information regarding significant leaks or spills of toxic or hazardous pollutants at the facility that have taken place within the three years prior to the submittal of this application.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>Quantitative data based on samples collected during storm events and collected in accordance with 40 CFR 122.21 from all outfalls containing a stormwater discharge associated with industrial activity for the following parameters:</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>Any pollutant limited in an effluent guideline to which the facility is subject;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>Any pollutant listed in the facility's NPDES permit for its process wastewater (if the facility is operating under an existing NPDES permit);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[3]</num>
              <text>Oil and grease, pH, BOD, COD, TSS, total phosphorus, total Kjeldahl nitrogen, and nitrate plus nitrite nitrogen;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[4]</num>
              <text>Flow measurements or estimates of the flow rate, and the total amount of discharge for the storm event(s) sampled, and the method of flow measurement or estimation; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[5]</num>
              <text>The date and duration (in hours) of the storm event(s) sampled, rainfall measurements or estimates of the storm event (in inches) which generated the sampled runoff and the duration between the storm event sampled and the end of the previous measurable (greater than 0.1 inch rainfall) storm event (in hours).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>An operator of an existing or new stormwater discharge that is associated with industrial activity shall also provide the following in addition to information listed above:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Proposed measures, including best management practices, to control pollutants in stormwater discharges during construction, including a brief description of applicable state and local erosion and sediment control requirements;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Proposed measures to control pollutants in stormwater discharges that will occur after construction operations have been completed, including a brief description of applicable state or local erosion and sediment control requirements; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>An estimate of the runoff coefficient of the site and the increase in impervious area after the construction addressed in the permit application is completed, the nature of fill material and existing data describing the soil or the quality of the discharge.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The operator of an existing or new discharge composed entirely of stormwater from an oil or gas exploration, production, processing, or treatment operation or transmission facility is not required to submit a permit application, unless the facility:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Has had a discharge of stormwater resulting in the discharge of a reportable quantity for which notification is or was required pursuant to 40 CFR 117.21 or 40 CFR 302.6 at any time since November 16, 1987; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Has had a discharge of stormwater resulting in the discharge of a reportable quantity for which notification is or was required pursuant to 40 CFR 110.6 at any time since November 16, 1987; or</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Contributes to a violation of a water quality standard.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The operator of an existing or new discharge composed entirely of stormwater from a mining operation is not required to submit a permit application unless the discharge has come into contact with any overburden, raw material, intermediate products, finished product, by-product or waste products located on the site of such operations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Applicants shall provide such other information the Director may reasonably require to determine whether to issue a permit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>Nonconstruction activity that require a stormwater permit:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Noncontact cooling water, condensate and boiler blowdown.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Contaminated groundwater from remedial action operations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Petroleum contaminated water.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Pit/trench dewatering.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Concrete products operations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Nonmetaline mining operations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Swimming pool facilities.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Potable water treatment and conditioning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>Dredging operations: carriage and interstitial water.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>Hydrostatic test water and water supply system water.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>Nondomestic wastewater to subsurface absorption systems.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>Land application of liquid wastes.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Land application of food processing by-product solids.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>Asphalt operations using wet scrubbers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(o)</num>
          <text>Outside washing of vehicles, equipment and other objects.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(p)</num>
          <text>Bypasses and overflows from sanitary sewer collection systems.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Conditional exclusion for no exposure of industrial activities and materials to stormwater. Discharges composed entirely of stormwater are not stormwater discharges associated with industrial activity if there is no exposure of industrial materials and activities to rain, snow, snowmelt and/or runoff and the discharger satisfies all conditions. "No exposure" means that all industrial materials and activities are protected by a storm-resistant shelter to prevent exposure to rain, snow, snowmelt and/or runoff. Industrial materials or activities include, but are not limited to, material handling equipment or activities, industrial machinery, raw materials, intermediate products, by-products, final products, or waste products. Material handling activities include the storage, loading and unloading, transportation, or conveyance of any raw material, intermediate product, final product or waste product.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Qualification. To qualify for this exclusion, the operator of the discharge must:</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>Provide a storm-resistant shelter to protect industrial materials and activities from exposure to rain, snow, snowmelt, and runoff;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>Complete and sign (according to 40 CFR 122.22) a certification that there are no discharges of stormwater contaminated by exposure to industrial materials and activities from the entire facility;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[3]</num>
              <text>Submit the signed certification to the NPDES permitting authority once every five years;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[4]</num>
              <text>Allow the Director to inspect the facility to determine compliance with the "no exposure" conditions;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[5]</num>
              <text>Allow the Director to make any "no exposure" inspection reports available to the public upon request; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[6]</num>
              <text>For facilities that discharge through an MS4, upon request, submit a copy of the certification of no exposure to the MS4 operator, as well as allow inspection and public reporting by the MS4 operator.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Industrial materials and activities not requiring storm-resistant shelter. To qualify for this exclusion, a storm-resistant shelter is not required for:</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>Drums, barrels, tanks, and similar containers that are tightly sealed, provided that those containers are not deteriorated and do not leak ("sealed" means banded or otherwise secured and without operational taps or valves);</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>Adequately maintained vehicles used in material handling; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[3]</num>
              <text>Final products, other than products that would be mobilized in stormwater discharge (e.g., rock salt).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Limitations.</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>Stormwater discharges from construction are not eligible for this conditional exclusion.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>This conditional exclusion from the requirement for a NPDES permit is available on a facility-wide basis only, not for individual outfalls. If a facility has some discharges of stormwater that would otherwise be "no exposure" discharges, individual permit requirements should be adjusted accordingly.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[3]</num>
              <text>If circumstances change and industrial materials or activities become exposed to rain, snow, snowmelt, and/or runoff, the conditions for this exclusion no longer apply. In such cases, the discharge becomes subject to enforcement for unpermitted discharge. Any conditionally exempt discharger who anticipates changes in circumstances should apply for and obtain permit authorization prior to the change of circumstances.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[4]</num>
              <text>Notwithstanding the provisions of <cite path="§512-31|(6)|(7)|(c)|[4]">this subsection</cite>, the NPDES permitting authority retains the authority to require permit authorization (and deny this exclusion) upon making a determination that the discharge causes, has a reasonable potential to cause, or contributes to an in-stream excursion above an applicable water quality standard, including designated uses.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Certification. The "no exposure" certification must require the submission of the following information, at a minimum, to aid the NPDES permitting authority in determining if the facility qualifies for the "no exposure" exclusion:</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>The legal name, address and phone number of the discharger;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>The facility name and address, the county name and the latitude and longitude where the facility is located;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[3]</num>
              <text>The certification must indicate that none of the following materials or activities are, or will be in the foreseeable future, exposed to precipitation:</text>
              <para>
                <num>[a]</num>
                <text>Using, storing or cleaning industrial machinery or equipment, and areas where residuals from using, storing or cleaning industrial machinery or equipment remain and are exposed to stormwater;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[b]</num>
                <text>Materials or residuals on the ground or in stormwater inlets from spills/leaks;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[c]</num>
                <text>Materials or products from past industrial activity;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[d]</num>
                <text>Material handling equipment (except adequately maintained vehicles);</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[e]</num>
                <text>Materials or products during loading/unloading or transporting activities;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[f]</num>
                <text>Materials or products stored outdoors (except final products intended for outside use, e.g., new cars, where exposure to stormwater does not result in the discharge of pollutants);</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[g]</num>
                <text>Materials contained in open, deteriorated or leaking storage drums, barrels, tanks, and similar containers;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[h]</num>
                <text>Materials or products handled/stored on roads or railways owned or maintained by the discharger;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[i]</num>
                <text>Waste material (except waste in covered, nonleaking containers, e.g., dumpsters);</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[j]</num>
                <text>Application or disposal of process wastewater (unless otherwise permitted); and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[k]</num>
                <text>Particulate matter or visible deposits of residuals from roof stacks/vents not otherwise regulated, i.e., under an air quality control permit, and evident in the stormwater outflow.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[4]</num>
              <text>All "no exposure" certifications must include the following certification statement and be signed in accordance with the signatory requirements of 40 CFR 122.22:</text>
              <text>I certify under penalty of law that I have read and understand the eligibility requirements for claiming a condition of no exposure and obtaining an exclusion from NPDES stormwater permitting and that there are no discharges of stormwater contaminated by exposure to industrial activities or materials from the industrial facility identified in this document. I understand that I am obligated to submit a no exposure certification form once every five years to the NPDES permitting authority and, if requested, to the operator of the local MS4 into which this facility discharges (where applicable). I understand that I must allow the NPDES permitting authority, or MS4 operator where the discharge is into the local MS4, to perform inspections to confirm the condition of no exposure and to make such inspection reports publicly available upon request. I understand that I must obtain coverage under a NPDES permit prior to any point source discharge of stormwater from the facility. I certify under penalty of law that this document and all attachments were prepared under my direction or supervision in accordance with a system designed to assure that qualified personnel properly gathered and evaluated the information submitted. Based upon my inquiry of the person or persons who manage the system, or those persons directly involved in gathering the information, the information submitted is to the best of my knowledge and belief true, accurate and complete. I am aware there are significant penalties for submitting false information, including the possibility of fine and imprisonment for knowing violations.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container cache:ref-path="II|512|VIII">
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>VIII</num>
    <heading>Tribal Water Permit</heading>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§512-32">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-32</num>
      <heading>Application for permit; activities requiring permit.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Persons requiring a tribal water permit can obtain a tribal water permit application (see Exhibit A, Sample Application)<fn path="|II|§512-32|footnotes|9">9</fn> from the Menominee Tribal Environmental Services Department:</text>
        <text class="center">Environmental Services Department – Tribal Water Permit</text>
        <text class="center">Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin Menominee Forestry and Environmental Resources Center</text>
        <text>P.O. Box 670</text>
        <text>Keshena, WI 54135</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Departmental determinations for tribal water permits will follow procedures outline in <cite path="§512-14|A">§ 512-14A</cite>. All permit appeals will follow the procedure outlined in Exhibit G.<fn path="|II|§512-32|footnotes|10">10</fn></text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Activities that require a tribal water permit include but are not limited to the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>New or increased discharges to waters that will affect OMRW designated waters of the Reservation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Existing discharges that enter ONRW designated waters of the Reservation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>New or existing hydrological modifications that affect waters of the Reservation; this shall include dams, impoundments, and other structures that affect water quality criteria and/or affect the nature of the waters so as to prohibit the natural spawning runs and other migrational patterns of indigenous fish.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Shoreline disturbance activities that may affect the beds and banks of waters of the Reservation; these activities include many types of shoreland construction, e.g., placement of a seawall or riprap for erosion protection and placement of boat ramps to facilitate the launch or retrieval of watercraft, provided that such boat ramps are deemed to present a potential significant impact to tribal waters in the opinion of the Director.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Stream crossing activities, including skidding trails and bridge and culvert placement, improvement, or replacement and fill placed in wetlands and water bodies in conjunction with the improvement or replacement of bridge and culvert crossings for municipal, township, county, state, tribal, or federal projects. The replacement of historic bridges must be coordinated with the Tribal Department of Historic Preservation. In addition, the existing structure must be removed and the replacement must be constructed on the same or similar alignment with hydraulic capacity that is consistent with the tribal and federal regulations and requirements. The placement of fill material into wetlands is authorized for widening of the road approaches to conform to the width or alignment of the new structure. All excess material must be placed at an upland location. If the project involves changing the channel of a river, creek, or stream, then additional requirements may be applied. These activities also include the installation and removal of submerged utility line crossings; additionally the following special conditions must be met:<fn path="|II|§512-32|footnotes|11">11</fn></text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Utility lines placed across the channel of an authorized federal navigation project must be embedded at least six feet below the authorized channel depth, or to a lesser depth if approved by the Corps of Engineers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Dredged or fill material may be placed as backfill or bedding, regulated by the Tribe, so long as there is no change in preconstruction bottom contours. Excess fill must be removed to an upland disposal area.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The utility line must not be placed within 500 feet of a levee or flood wall constructed and/ or maintained with federal funds.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Utility crossings involving pipelines must comply with Federal Department of Transportation regulations for installation of pipelines.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>All utility lines transporting oil, gas, or other pollutive substances must be equipped with shutoff valves at the upland edge of the water crossing to prevent unnecessary pollution of waters in the event of pipeline failure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Placement of fish barrier structures that prevent the upstream and/or downstream movement of fish, often associated with impoundment structures.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Dredging activities that include the removal, by suction, scooping or scraping devices, of materials channelward of the ordinary high-water mark from navigable waters, provided that all dredged materials are placed on an upland site, not a wetland, and above the ordinary high-water mark.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Placement of new and existing dry fire hydrants that include an intake structure and pipe in or on the bed and banks of water bodies for the purpose of constructing a dry fire hydrant to supply water for firefighting purposes.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Withdrawal of water from (surface) waters of the Reservation. Persons who want to withdraw surface waters from waters of the Reservation shall be restricted to quantity limitations and must obtain a tribal water permit from the Tribe. Typically persons wishing to withdraw surface water from waters of the Reservation will submit a permit application to the Tribe and shall be limited to the following minimum requirements if a permit is issued:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Withdrawal of 25,000 gallons or less of surface water per day from rivers and 1,000 gallons or less per day from lakes (note: withdrawal of water for emergency fire situations is exempt from these requirements).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Withdrawal of surface water by persons shall not adversely affect the quantity of surface water available to any other person, facility, practice or activity. The Department will evaluate each withdrawal for appropriate flows based on existing or acquired flow data. Based on each evaluation, including applications in excess of the above limits, a percentage of the total flow may be permitted to be withdrawn but shall not cause a violation of the use designations or water quality standards of <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite>. Surface water extraction which results in the latter person, facility, practice or activity not being able to obtain sufficient surface water shall constitute adverse effect.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Withdrawal of surface water by persons, facilities, practices, or activities shall not cause a violation of the use designations or water quality standards of <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Persons who propose to withdraw surface water shall submit a feasibility report to the Tribe which documents the quantity of surface water intended to be extracted per day and other relevant narrative and plan drawing information. No facility, practice or activity shall be undertaken until approval of a feasibility report is obtained from the Tribe and a tribal water permit is issued.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Dredging and filling of wetlands that affect waters of the Reservation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The application of pesticides within 200 feet of waters of the Reservation.</text>
          <text>Note: Certain activities listed in <cite path="§512-32|C|(1)">Subsection C(1)</cite> to (11) may require additional permits and/or certification. Such additional permits and certifications shall be obtained by the applicant prior to issuance of a tribal water permit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>9</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Exhibit A is on file with the Environmental Services Department.</text>
        </footnote>
        <footnote>
          <num>10</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Exhibit G is on file with the Environmental Services Department.</text>
        </footnote>
        <footnote>
          <num>11</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Amended at time of adoption of Code (see <cite path="|I|1|II">Ch. 1, General Provisions, Art. II</cite>).</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section cache:ref-path="II|§512-33">
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-33</num>
      <heading>Water quality certification.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Purpose and policy.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text><cite path="|II|512|VIII">This article</cite> establishes procedures and criteria for the application, processing and review of tribal water quality certifications required by the provisions of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act, 33 U.S.C. § 1251 et seq.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>It is the policy of the Department to review all activities which require a federal license or permit which may result in any discharge to waters of the Tribe and to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Deny certification for any activity where the Department does not have reasonable assurance that any discharge will comply with effluent limitations or water-quality-related concerns or any other appropriate requirements of tribal law as outlined in Subsection D;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Grant or grant conditionally certification for any activity where the Department has reasonable assurance that the discharge will comply with effluent limitations, water-quality-related concerns or any other appropriate requirements of tribal law as outlined in Subsection D; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Waive certification for any activity which the Department finds will result in no discharge or any activity that does not fall within the purview of the Department's authority.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Definitions. As used in this section, the following terms shall have the meanings indicated:</text>
        <text>APPLICANT — Any person who applies for any license or permit granted by an agency of the Tribe or federal government to conduct any activity which may result in any discharge into the waters of the Reservation.</text>
        <text>LICENSING OR PERMITTING AGENCY — Any agency of the federal government to which application is made for any license or permit to conduct an activity which may result in any discharge into the waters of the Reservation.</text>
        <text>PERSON — An individual, corporation, partnership, association, municipality, tribal agency, interstate agency or federal agency.</text>
        <text>PRACTICABLE ALTERNATIVES — Alternatives which are available and capable of being implemented after taking into consideration cost, available technology, and logistics in light of realistic project purposes.</text>
        <text>REGIONAL ADMINISTRATOR — The administrator of Region V of the United States Environmental Protection Agency.</text>
        <text>WATER DEPENDENCY — The activity requires location in or adjacent to surface waters or wetlands to fulfill its basic purpose.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Application for certification.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>No person may conduct any activity which may result in any discharge into the waters of the Reservation unless the person has received a certification or waiver under this section. Unless the licensing or permitting agency or the regional administrator submits an application to the Department under 40 CFR 121.13, the applicant shall submit to the Department a complete description of the activity for which certification is sought, including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The name and address of the applicant;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>A description of the facility or activity and of any discharge which may result from the activity or facility, including but not limited to the volume of discharge; the biological, chemical, thermal, and other characteristics of the discharge; a description of the existing physical environment at the site of the discharge; the size of the area affected; the location or locations at which the discharge may enter the waters of the Reservation; and any environmental impact document information and photographs which have been provided to the licensing or permitting agency;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>A description of the function and operation of equipment, facilities, or activities to treat pollutants or other effluents which may be discharged, including specification of the degree of treatment expected to be attained;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The date or dates on which the activity will begin and end, if known, and the date or dates on which the discharge will take place;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>A description of the methods being used or proposed to monitor the quality and characteristics of the discharge and the operation of equipment, facilities, or activities employed in the treatment or control of pollutants or other effluents;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>Information sufficient to determine whether the proposed activity is water dependent;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(g)</num>
            <text>A description of practicable alternatives to the proposed activity and a description of the investigation conducted to determine the viability of such alternatives, including alternative locations, construction design and methods, and operations; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(h)</num>
            <text>All other information as necessary for the Department to determine whether the proposed activity will fulfill the Tribe's water quality standards.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The Department shall review the application for completeness within 30 days of receipt of the application. The Department shall notify the applicant of any additional information reasonably necessary to review the application. An application may not be considered complete until all information necessary for associated permits has been submitted to the Department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The applicant shall submit in timely fashion, at any time during the review process, such additional information which the Department finds to be reasonably necessary for review of the application.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Consistent with the nature and circumstances of each application, the Department may protect as confidential any information the Department deems necessary to protect the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin. Confidentiality determinations shall be made based on the professional judgment of the Department and in light of applicable federal and tribal law.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>Department review of water quality certification application. The Department shall, within 60 business days of receipt of the complete application, determine whether it has reasonable assurance that the proposed activity will:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Result in any discharge; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Comply with the following water quality standards:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Water quality standards of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Water quality standards of the Great Lakes (40 CFR Part 132);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Applicable effluent limitations, pretreatment standards, and standards of performance; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>Any other appropriate requirements of tribal law as provided in 33 U.S.C. § 1341(d).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>Preliminary and final Department action.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Department shall notify the applicant, the federal permitting or licensing agency, and the regional administrator within 120 days of receipt of the complete application of its determination to deny the certification, grant or conditionally grant the certification, or waive certification.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The Department's determination shall be in writing and shall explain the reasons for granting, granting conditionally, denying or waiving certification.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The Department's decision concerning a certification shall include the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The name and address of the applicant;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>A statement that the Department has made its decision about compliance with related tribal water quality standards and denies, grants, grants conditionally or waives certification consistent with that decision.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>A waiver of certification shall include:</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>A statement explaining the determination that no discharge will result from the activity or that the activity does not fall within the purview of the Department's authority;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>A statement advising the licensing or permitting agency and the applicant if the activity proposed requires authorization under requirements of tribal law administered by the Department which are not related to water quality; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[3]</num>
              <text>Where applicable, specific recommendations to the federal permitting authority and the applicant for avoidance of waters of the Reservation. When all reasonable alternatives necessarily result in adverse impacts on waters of the Reservation, a waiver may recommend specific project locations and design and construction techniques which minimize adverse impacts on waters of the Reservation and which minimize overall environmental impacts.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>A grant or conditional grant of certification shall include:</text>
            <para>
              <num>[1]</num>
              <text>A statement that there is a reasonable assurance the activity will be conducted in a manner which will comply with the standards of the Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[2]</num>
              <text>If appropriate, a statement of conditions that the Department deems necessary with respect to the discharge, including necessary monitoring requirements. Monitoring requirements shall include, but not be limited to, provisions that:</text>
              <para>
                <num>[a]</num>
                <text>At least five business days prior to the beginning of the discharge, the applicant shall notify the Department of its intent to commence the discharge.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[b]</num>
                <text>Within five business days after the completion of the discharge, the applicant shall notify the Department of the completion of the discharge.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>[c]</num>
                <text>The applicant shall allow the Department reasonable entry and access to the discharge site in order to inspect the discharge for compliance with the certification and applicable laws.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>[3]</num>
              <text>A statement advising the licensing or permitting agency and the applicant if the activity proposed may require additional authorization under requirements of tribal law administered by the Department which are not related to water quality.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(e)</num>
            <text>A denial of certification shall include a statement explaining why the Department does not have reasonable assurance that the discharge will comply with the Tribe's water quality standards and detailing the standards of concern.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(f)</num>
            <text>All such decisions may also include other information that the Department determines to be appropriate.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Department shall, in the case of a grant or conditional grant of certification:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Notify the applicant, the licensing or permitting agency and known interested persons of its decision.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Cause notice of its decision to be published by the applicant. Such notice to be posted at the Neopit and the Keshena post offices, County Courthouse and Tribal Office Building, and a copy of the notice shall be mailed to all persons who have made timely request to the committee or the Department for information regarding the proposed certification. Notice under <cite path="§512-33|E.|(1)|(b)">this subsection</cite> shall identify the applicant and his or her address, describe the activity and its location, state the Department's determination, and apprise the public of the opportunity to request a hearing under <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite>.<fn path="|II|§512-33|footnotes|12">12</fn></text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The final decision of the Department shall be judicially reviewable in the Menominee Tribal Court.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <footnotes>
        <footnote>
          <num>12</num>
          <text>Editor's Note: Amended at time of adoption of Code (see <cite path="|I|1|II">Ch. 1, General Provisions, Art. II</cite>).</text>
        </footnote>
      </footnotes>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>IX</num>
    <heading>National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System Permit</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-34</num>
      <heading>Conditions for issuance.</heading>
      <text>In issuing NPDES permits for discharges that will affect waters of the Reservation, the United States Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) shall utilize <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> in order to protect waters of the Reservation. Tribal certification for the issuance of discharge permits pursuant to Sections 401, 402 and 404 of the CWA (33 U.S.C. §§ 1341 and 1342) shall be incorporated into the NPDES control document. Tribal certification shall be achieved prior to the EPA decision approving any discharge or issuing any permit for a discharge that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Will enter ONRW designated waters of the Reservation; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>May affect OMRW designated waters of the Reservation.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-35</num>
      <heading>Effect of permit issuance.</heading>
      <text>The issuance of a tribal water permit will indicate the Tribe's approval. Criteria found in <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> shall provide the basis for development of effluent limitations for NPDES permits if it is mutually agreed upon by the Tribe and EPA that a such permit should be issued. The development of effluent limitations shall take into account the interactive effects of other discharges, and components and breakdown products of the same discharge, to the same water body so that numeric criteria and other requirements contained in <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> are met at all times, except where natural and/or background conditions cause an exceedence of the criteria.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>X</num>
    <heading>Enforcement</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix>§</prefix>
      <num>512-36</num>
      <heading>Violations and penalties.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Upon determination of a violation of <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite>, or any rule promulgated under <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite>, the Tribal Environmental Services Department shall issue a compliance order to the responsible party (as indicated in the control document). The compliance order shall direct the responsible party to implement certain conditions and measures, e.g., corrective actions, pollution prevention measures, resource management measures, best management practices, and/or refrainment from certain activities, in order to bring about compliance with <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite>. If conditions and measures contained in the compliance order are not implemented within a stated period of time, then an enforcement action shall be commenced.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Any person that violates <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> or any rule promulgated under <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> shall be subject to an initial forfeiture of $15 to $5,000 for each day of violation under an enforcement action. Second offenses shall be subject to immediate enforcement actions without benefit of a compliance order. The time elapsed prior to the expiration of a compliance order shall not constitute a violation. Each day of violation constitutes a separate offense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Where a violation of <cite path="|II|512">this chapter</cite> is deemed to be the result of negligence on the part of the responsible party, the term of forfeiture, as determined by the Department or a court of competent jurisdiction, may be identified as the date upon which the Department confirmed the existence of said violation.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
